<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="task-post-deployment-considerations" xml:lang="en"
 role="task"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <title>Post-deployment considerations</title>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This article includes important information and tasks that you need to
        consider after you successfully deploy &productname;
        (&productnameshort;).
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="alp-post-deploy-full-disk-encryption">
    <title>Full disk encryption</title>
    <section xml:id="alp-post-deploy-full-disk-encryption-password">
      <title>Change encryption password</title>
      <para>
        During the &productnameshort; deployment, you entered a password that
        is used for disk encryption. To change the password, run the following
        command:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;fdectl passwd</screen>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="alp-post-deploy-full-disk-encryption-tpm">
      <title>TPM device</title>
      <para>
        Without a TPM chip, you need to enter the encryption password to
        decrypt the disk on each &productnameshort; boot. On systems that have
        a TPM 2.0 chip, &productnameshort; deployed with the &alp-installer;
        installer supports the automatic protection of the LUKS volume with a
        TPM device. The requirement is that the machine must use the
        &uefisecboot; enabled.
      </para>
      <para>
        If the &alp-installer; installer detects a TPM 2.0 chip and
        &uefisecboot;, it creates a secondary LUKS key. On the first boot,
        &productnameshort; uses the TPM to protect this key and configure the
        &grub; boot loader to unwrap the key automatically. Be aware that you
        must remove the ISO after the installer has finished and before the
        system boots for the first time. This is because we use the TPM to
        ensure that the system comes up with exactly the same configuration
        before unlocking the LUKS partition.
      </para>
      <para>
        This allows you to use the full disk encryption without having to type
        the disk password on each reboot. However, the disk password is still
        there and can be used for recovery. For example, after updating the
        &grub; boot loader or the SHIM loader, the TPM can no longer unseal the
        secondary key correctly, and &grub; has to fall back to the password.
      </para>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="alp-post-deploy-selinux">
    <title>&selnx;</title>
    <para>
      Security-Enhanced Linux (&selnx;) is a security framework that increases
      system security by defining access controls for applications, processes
      and files on the file system.
    </para>
    <para>
      &productnameshort; ships with &selnx; enabled and set to the restrictive
      <emphasis>enforce</emphasis> mode for increased security. The enforce
      mode can lead to processes or workloads not behaving correctly because
      the default policy may be too strict. If you observe such unexpected
      issues, set &selnx; to the <emphasis>permissive</emphasis> mode that does
      not enforce &selnx; policies but still logs offenses against them called
      <emphasis>Access Vector Rules</emphasis> (AVCs).
    </para>
    <para>
      To set &selnx; to the permissive mode temporarily, run:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;setenforce 0</screen>
    <tip>
      <para>
        To set &selnx; to the permissive mode permanently, edit
        <filename>/etc/selinux/config</filename> and update it to include the
        following line:
      </para>
<screen>SELINUX=permissive</screen>
    </tip>
    <important>
      <para>
        If you entered an &selnx; permissive mode, you need to relabel your
        system until it is back in a good state. The reason is that the
        permissive mode allows you to reach states that are not reachable
        otherwise. To relabel the system, run the following command and reboot
        the system:
      </para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;touch /etc/selinux/.autorelabel
&prompt.root;reboot
</screen>
    </important>
    <para>
      To monitor AVCs, search the Audit log and &systemd; journal for log
      messages similar to the following one:
    </para>
<screen>
type=AVC msg=audit(1669971354.731:25): avc:  denied  { create } \
for pid=1264 comm="ModemManager" scontext=system_u:system_r:modemmanager_t:s0 \
tcontext=system_u:system_r:modemmanager_t:s0 tclass=qipcrtr_socket permissive=0
</screen>
    <para>
      To filter such messages, you can use the following commands:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;tail -f /var/log/audit/audit.log | grep -i AVC</screen>
    <para>
      and
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;journalctl -f | grep -i AVC</screen>
    <para>
      For more advanced search, use the following command:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;ausearch -m avc,user_avc,selinux_err -i</screen>
    <para>
      If such messages appear while using the application that did not behave
      correctly when &selnx; was set to the enforce mode, the policies are too
      restrictive and need updating. You can help to fine-tune &selnx; policies
      by creating a bug report at
      <link xlink:href="https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi?classification=SUSE%20ALP%20-%20SUSE%20Adaptable%20Linux%20Platform"/>.
      Specify <literal>Basesystem</literal> as a component, include the word
      <literal>&selnx;</literal> in the bug subject, and attach the gathered
      unique lines that include AVCs together with reproduction steps.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="alp-post-deploy-enable-root-ssh-login">
    <title>Enabling &rootuser; SSH login</title>
    <para>
      &rootuser; login via SSH is not permitted in &productnameshort; by
      default for security reasons. To enable it, you have the following
      options:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          install the <package>openssh-server-config-rootlogin</package>
          package and reboot the system.
        </para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update pkg in openssh-server-config-rootlogin</command>
&prompt.root;<command>reboot</command>
</screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Add a file containing the snippet <literal>PermitRootLogin
          yes</literal> in the <filename>/etc/sshd/sshd_config.d/</filename>
          directory and reboot, for example:
        </para>
<screen>
&prompt.root;echo 'PermitRootLogin yes' &gt;&gt; /etc/sshd/sshd_config.d/root_login_config
&prompt.root;<command>reboot</command>
</screen>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</topic>

