<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="cockpit-logging-in-without-home-directory"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Logging in without home directory</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        By default, logging into Cockpit as a regular user requires an existing <literal>$HOME</literal> directory. This requirement exists because the system defaults to supporting standard Multi-Factor Authentication (MFA) mechanisms via PAM.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>If a user does not have a $HOME directory—which frequently occurs during the initial login of network users managed via SSSD—the login attempt will fail. If you wish to allow users without home directories to log into Cockpit, you must override the default PAM configuration to disable the look-up for the second-factor authentication file:</para>
  <procedure xml:id="logging-in-without-home-directory">
    <title>Logging in without home directory</title>
<para>If you wish to allow users without home directories to log into Cockpit, you must override the default PAM configuration to disable the look-up for the second-factor authentication file:</para>
    <step>
      <para>
        Copy the system default Cockpit PAM configuration to the administrator override directory:</para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo; cp /usr/lib/pam.d/cockpit /etc/pam.d/cockpit</screen>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Open <filename>/etc/pam.d/cockpit</filename> in an editor and locate the line referencing pam_oath.so at the end of the file.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step><para>Comment out or remove the line entirely:</para>
    <note><para>Disabling this line allows logins without a <literal>$HOME</literal> directory, but it entirely removes the ability to use a second-factor authentication token via pam_oath.</para></note>
      <screen># auth [user_unknown=ignore success=ok] pam_oath.so usersfile=${HOME}/.pam_oath_usersfile no_usersfile_okay window=20 digits=6</screen></step>
    <step><para>Save and close the file.</para>
    
    </step>
  </procedure>
</topic>
