<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="cockpit-logging-into-secondary-server"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Logging in to secondary servers</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="jsindelarova@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        If a server cannot expose the 9090 port, it can still be administered
        using &cockpit;. This topic provides information on logging in to such a
        server.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    If your machine does not have direct access to the 9090 port, you can use
    this machine as a secondary server. Ensure that &cockpit; is installed
    on the machine.
  </para>
  <para>
    There are two ways of logging in to a secondary server: you can
    log in to a secondary server directly or you can use the primary server.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="cockpit-logging-into-secondary-directly">
    <title>Logging in to secondary servers directly</title>
    <para>
      You can log in to any secondary server without logging in to the primary
      server first. This solution can be useful when you do not have
      credentials for the primary server. The primary server will be used as a
      bridge, and you will be connected to the secondary server using SSH.
    </para>
    <para>
      To connect to the secondary server, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          Go to the &cockpit; login page by opening the following address in a
          browser:
        </para>
<screen>https://<replaceable>IP_ADDRESS_OF_MACHINE</replaceable>:9090</screen>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Fill in the credentials for the secondary server.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Expand <guimenu>Other options</guimenu> on the login screen.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Fill in the IP address of the secondary server.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Proceed by clicking <guimenu>Login</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          If you are trying to log in for the first time, you are asked to
          verify the fingerprint. After this, click <guimenu>Accept and
          connect</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cockpit-logging-into-secondary-primary">
    <title>Accessing secondary servers from the primary server</title>
    <para>
      If you have credentials for the primary server, you can access secondary
      servers from the primary one. You must add the
      secondary servers first, as described in
      <xref linkend="cockpit-logging-adding-secondary"/>.
    </para>
    <procedure xml:id="cockpit-logging-adding-secondary">
      <title>Adding a server as secondary</title>
      <step>
        <para>
          Log in to the primary server using the account with the
          <emphasis>system administrator</emphasis> role.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click the
          <replaceable>USERNAME</replaceable>@<replaceable>HOSTNAME</replaceable>
          in the upper-left corner.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click <guimenu>Add new host</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Fill in the host identification and optionally user name that will be
          used to log in to the server. You can assign a color to the machine.
          When the details are complete, click <guimenu>Add</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Verify the fingerprint on the server you want to add. If the
          fingerprint matches or if you have not set up the SSH connection,
          click <guimenu>Trust and add host</guimenu> to proceed.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Fill in the password and, if needed, check <guimenu>Automatic
          login</guimenu>. Cockpit will generate a new SSH key for the user, and
          next time you will be logged in automatically.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
</topic>
