<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="task-managing-software-updates"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Updating &productnameshort; using &cockpit;</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This topic focuses on updating your system using &cockpit;.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    To update your system, proceed as follows:
  </para>
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
        Navigate to the <guimenu>Software updates</guimenu> page.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Click <guimenu>Check for Updates</guimenu> icon to get a list of new package
        updates and patches available for your system. We recommend
        installing the patches marked as important as soon as possible.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Now you can update your system either with immediate reboot, or the
        reboot might be postponed:
      </para>
      <substeps>
        <step>
         <para>
            Click <guimenu>Install all updates</guimenu> to install all updates
            updates. By default, all available updates are selected.
          </para>
          <para>To install specific updates, select <guimenu>Unselect all</guimenu> and then select the required updates and click <guimenu>Install selected updates</guimenu>.</para>
          <para>After the installation is complete, you can reboot your system or click <guimenu>Ignore</guimenu> to postpone the reboot.</para>
        <note><para>When the Web Console is restarted, you will no longer see progress information. However, the update process will continue in the background. Reconnect to continue watching the update process.</para></note>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            To reboot the system after installation, enable the <guimenu>Reboot after completion</guimenu> toggle button. By default, the <guimenu>Reboot after completion</guimenu> toggle button is disabled. You must reboot the system to activate the snapshot with updates. If
            you perform further changes without rebooting the system
            beforehand, a new snapshot will be created from the same point as
            the snapshots with updates. Therefore, the new snapshot will not
            include the updates.
          </para></step><step>
          <para>To view the installed package information, click <guimenu>Package information</guimenu>.</para>
        </step>
        <step><para>In the <guimenu>Reboot</guimenu> window, enter the message for the logged in users and select the time delay for the reboot.</para></step>
        <step><para>Click <guimenu>Reboot</guimenu>.</para></step>
      </substeps></step>
      <step><para>You can view the update history in the <guimenu>Update history</guimenu> section.</para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
</topic>
