<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-customize" role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
 <info>
  <title>Customizing the settings for <productname>&gnome;
    Desktop</productname>
  </title>
  <!-- can be changed via merge
in the assembly -->
  <!-- add author's e-mail -->
  <meta name="maintainer" content="julia.faltenbacher@suse.com"
   its:translate="no"/>
  <abstract>
   <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
   <para> Learn how to customize the settings for <productname>&gnome;
    Desktop</productname>, like changing the background or configuring language
    and keyboard settings to suit your personal taste and needs. </para>
  </abstract>
 </info>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-customize-background">
  <title>Configuring the desktop background</title>
  <para> The desktop background is the image or color that is applied to your
   desktop. You can also customize the image shown when the screen is locked. </para>
  <para> To change the desktop background: </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Change
      Background</guimenu>. </para>
    <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-preferences-background">
     <title>&gnome; Background settings</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_background.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_background.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="description">
       <phrase>&gnome;: changing the desktop background</phrase>
      </textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Select one of the wallpapers (preconfigured images distributed with
     your system) shown in the content area. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Alternatively, click <guimenu>Add Picture</guimenu> to select an
     image from your <filename>Pictures</filename> directory
      (<filename>~/Pictures</filename>) or another location in your file system.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> Close the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> dialog. </para>
    <para> The new background is now shown on your desktop. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-customize-language">
  <title>Configuring language settings</title>
  <para> &productname; can be configured to use any of several languages.
   The language setting determines the language of dialogs and menus and can
   also determine the keyboard and clock layout. </para>
  <para>To configure your language settings, right-click the desktop and choose
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Region &amp;
    Language</guimenu></menuchoice>. </para>
  <para> Here you can choose: </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Language</guimenu>. Choose a language from the list. For the
     change to take effect, you are prompted to <guimenu>Restart</guimenu> the
     desktop session. To do so, you must log out of your session and log back in
     afterward.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <guimenu>Formats</guimenu>. To change the formats for date, number,
     currency and related options, choose a country from the list. For the
     change to take effect, you must log out of your session and log back in
     afterward. </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <note>
   <title>Settings made using <command>ibus-setup</command> do not take effect
  </title>
   <para>
    On &gnome;, settings made using <command>ibus-setup</command> do
    not take effect. <command>ibus-setup</command> can only be used to configure
    IceWM. Instead, always use the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> application:
  </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To change input methods, open the <guimenu>Settings</guimenu> dialog,
      then select <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu> from the navigation pane.
    </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      To change the key combination that switches between input methods,
      use <menuchoice> <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu>
      <guimenu>Keyboard Shortcuts</guimenu> </menuchoice>. Then select the
      category <guimenu>Typing</guimenu> and the entry <guimenu>Switch to next
      input source</guimenu>.
    </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </note>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-customize-keyboard">
  <title>Configuring the keyboard</title>
  <para>
   Refer to <xref linkend="task-GNOME-assistive-technologies"/> for
   additional settings, such as key auto-repetition and cursor blink rate, and
   accessibility features. To configure your keyboard layout, refer to
   <xref linkend="task-GNOME-assistive-technologies-keyboard-mouse"/>.
  </para>
  <para>
    To modify keyboard shortcuts, right-click the desktop and choose
    <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Now select <menuchoice>
    <guimenu>Keyboard</guimenu>
    <guimenu>Keyboard Shortcuts</guimenu>
   </menuchoice>.
  </para>
  <para>
   This dialog shows the keyboard shortcuts that are configured for your
   system. To edit a key combination, click the entry that you want to change.
   To set a new key combination, press the respective keys. To disable a
   shortcut, press <keycap function="backspace"/> instead.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-using-xcompose">
  <title>Using <productname>XCompose</productname> to type special
   characters</title>
  <para>
    &gnome; supports fast input source (keyboard layout) switching
    (<xref linkend="task-GNOME-settings-customize-language"/>). However, if you
    are using <command>xmodmap</command> to create custom keymaps, it may not
    work correctly when you switch between multiple input sources. For example,
    you have two input sources, English and German. Your
    <command>xmodmap</command> commands work fine in the first input source you
    select, but when you switch to the second input source, the same
    <command>xmodmap</command> commands produce incorrect output.
    <command>xmodmap</command> is an older protocol and does not have a full
    view of the keyboard layout, so in more complex situations it causes errors.
   </para>
  <para>
    An alternative method is to use <command>xcompose</command>, a utility that allows 
    you to define custom keyboard shortcuts for special characters. This should 
    work with any input source. This procedure guides you through installing and configuring XCompose:</para>
   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>Install XCompose:</para>
<screen>&prompt.user;sudo zypper install libX11-devel</screen>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Assign a compose key using the <guimenu>Tweaks</guimenu> tool in 
        the <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> overview. Press this key in 
        sequence with one or two additional keys to print a special 
        character. The keys must be pressed in the correct sequence, 
        starting with the compose key.</para>
    </listitem>    
    <listitem>
      <para>
        In the <guimenu>Tweaks</guimenu> tool, navigate to <menuchoice>
        <guimenu>Keyboard &amp; Mouse</guimenu><guimenu>Compose Key</guimenu></menuchoice> 
        and select your command key: </para>
        <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-keyboard-compose">
         <title>Enabling the compose key in Tweaks</title>
         <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
           <imagedata fileref="gnome_tweaks_compose.png" width="80%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
           <imagedata fileref="gnome_tweaks_compose.png" width="80%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <textobject role="description">
           <phrase>&gnome; desktop: enabling compose key in Tweaks</phrase>
          </textobject>
         </mediaobject>
        </figure>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Next, create a <filename>~/.XCompose</filename> file. This is the
        default per-user configuration file. Enter your key mappings in this file,
        as in this example:</para>
<screen>include "%L"
    
&lt;Multi_key> &lt;a> : "α"
&lt;Multi_key> &lt;b> : "β"
&lt;Multi_key> &lt;exclam>  : "¡"</screen>
    
    <para><literal>include "%L"</literal> includes the default compose file for your
       locale, for example, <filename>/usr/share/X11/locale/en_US.UTF-8</filename>. </para>
      <para> The remaining lines specify the compose key, the other key presses, and
       the symbols they are intended to print.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>After you make changes to your compose file, log out of 
      your session and log back in to activate the changes.</para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
    
  <para> Your key assignments are case-sensitive.
    <filename>~/.XCompose</filename> overrides the system files. Use the compose
   file for your locale to see what is already configured, and to copy symbols
   from it into your personal compose file. (These files may have a lot of
   whitespace at the beginning but they are not empty, so keep scrolling.) As
   always, watch out for conflicts with the other keymaps on your system. </para>
  <para> For additional information, see <command>man xcompose</command>. </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-bluetooth">
  <title>Configuring Bluetooth settings</title>
  <para> The Bluetooth module lets you set the visibility of your machine over
   Bluetooth and connect to available Bluetooth devices. To configure Bluetooth
   connectivity, follow these steps: </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>Right-click the desktop and choose <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Bluetooth</guimenu></menuchoice>. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> To use Bluetooth, set the switch at the top on. </para>
    <para> Your computer is visible as long as the Bluetooth panel is open. </para>
    <note>
     <title>Temporary visibility</title>
     <para> The <guimenu>Visibility</guimenu> switch is meant to be used only
      temporarily. You only need to turn it on for the initial setup of a
      connection to a Bluetooth device. After the connection has been
      established, turn off the switch. </para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> On the device you want to connect, turn on Bluetooth connectivity and
     visibility, too. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> If the device has been found and is shown in the list, click it to
     establish a connection to it. </para>
    <para> You are asked whether the PINs of the two devices match. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> If the PINs match, confirm this on <emphasis>both</emphasis> your
     computer and the device. </para>
    <para> The pairing is now established. On your computer, the device in the
     list is shown as <guimenu>Connected</guimenu>. </para>
    <para> Depending on the device type, it is also now available in other
     applications, for example, as a storage device in &nautilus;, or a sound
     device in playback applications. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para> To connect to a paired Bluetooth device, select the device in the list.
   In the dialog that appears, turn the <guimenu>Connection</guimenu> switch on.
   You can send files to the connected device by using the <guimenu>Send
    Files</guimenu> button. If you are connected to a device such as a mobile
   phone, you can use it as a network device by activating the appropriate
   option. </para>
  <para> To remove a connected device from the list on your computer, click
    <guimenu>Remove Device</guimenu> and confirm your choice. To remove the
   pairing, you also need to do so on your device. </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-power-settings">
  <title>Configuring power settings</title>
  <para> Settings available in this dialog depend on your hardware. In the
   following, the options that are typically available when using a laptop are
   described. On a workstation, many of the described options are not available. </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> Right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> In the navigation pane, select <guimenu>Power</guimenu>. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> In the <guimenu>Power Saving Options</guimenu> of the content area,
     set after how many minutes to blank the screen (or to not blank it at all).
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> In the <guimenu>Automatic Suspend</guimenu> section of the dialog,
     configure a time after which the computer is paused after a certain period
     of inactivity. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-mouse-touchpad">
  <title>Configuring mouse and touchpad</title>
  <para> To modify mouse and touchpad options, right-click the desktop and
   choose <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Then select <guimenu>Mouse &amp;
    Touchpad</guimenu>. </para>
  <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-hardware-mouse">
   <title><guimenu>Mouse and Touchpad</guimenu> settings dialog</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_mouse.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_mouse.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject role="description">
     <phrase>&gnome;: configuring mouse and touchpad</phrase>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para> In the <guimenu>General</guimenu> section of the dialog, you can set
     the <guimenu>Primary button</guimenu> orientation (left or right). </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> In the <guimenu>Mouse</guimenu> section of the dialog, use
      <guimenu>Mouse Speed</guimenu> to adjust the sensitivity of the mouse
     pointer. </para>
    <para> With <guimenu>Natural Scrolling</guimenu>, you can set the direction
     in which the content moves when scrolling with the mouse. When natural
     scrolling is turned off, the content moves <emphasis>up</emphasis> while
     pushing the scroll wheel <emphasis>down</emphasis>. When natural scrolling
     is turned on, the content moves in the same direction as the mouse wheel.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para> To test your settings, click <guimenu>Test Your Settings</guimenu>
     and try the pointing device. </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para> For configuration of mouse accessibility options, refer to the <xref
    linkend="task-GNOME-assistive-technologies-keyboard-mouse"/>. </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-printer">
  <title>Installing and configuring printers</title>
  <para> The <guimenu>Printers</guimenu> dialog lets you connect to any
   available local or remote CUPS server and configure printers. </para>
  <para> To start the Printers module, right-click the desktop and choose
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Printers</guimenu></menuchoice>. For
   detailed information, refer to <link
    xlink:href="https://help.gnome.org/users/gnome-help/stable/printing.html.en"
   />. </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-screen">
  <title>Configuring screens</title>
  <para> To specify resolution and orientation for your screen or to configure
   multiple screens, right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Display
    Settings</guimenu>. The configuration options available in this dialog
   depend on whether you have a single or a multiple monitor setup. </para>
  <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-screen-single">
   <title>Configuring single monitor setup</title>

   <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-hardware-screen-single">
    <title>Single monitor settings dialog</title>
    <mediaobject>
     <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_screen_single.png" width="100%"/>
     </imageobject>
     <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_screen_single.png" width="80%"/>
     </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <guimenu>Orientation</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para> If you use a monitor which can change its orientation, you need to
       adjust the display before turning the monitor. Use
        <guimenu>Orientation</guimenu> to do this. Choose the orientation your
       monitor supports, close the selection box and click
        <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <guimenu>Resolution</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para> To change the screen resolution, click
        <guimenu>Resolution</guimenu>. Choose a new value and click
        <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>
      <guimenu>Night Light</guimenu>
     </term>
     <listitem>
      <para> If you are working in a dark environment, your eyes can easily be
       strained by the monitor. To prevent this, change the screen's color
       palette to a warmer tone by turning on <guimenu>Night Light</guimenu>.
       Under <guimenu>Schedule</guimenu>, you can automate this setting by
       specifying at which time <guimenu>Night Light</guimenu> should be turned
       on and off. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-screen-multiple">
   <title>Configuring multiple monitor setup</title>
   <para> To set up an additional monitor, connect the monitor to your computer.
    If your system does not recognize it immediately, or you want to adjust the
    settings, do the following: </para>
   <procedure>
    <step>
     <para> Open the <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> overview and start typing
       <literal>Displays</literal>. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Click <guimenu>Displays</guimenu> to open the panel. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> In the display arrangement diagram, drag your displays to the
      relative positions you want. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Click <guimenu>Primary Display</guimenu> to choose your primary
      display. </para>
     <para> The primary display is the one with the <guimenu>top bar</guimenu>,
      and where the <guimenu>Activities</guimenu> overview is shown. </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para> Select the orientation, resolution or scale, and refresh rate.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guimenu>Apply</guimenu>. The new settings are applied for 20
      seconds before reverting. If you are happy with the settings, click
       <guimenu>Keep Changes</guimenu>.
      </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <para> With two or more screens, these display modes are available: </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Join Display</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
        The screen edges are joined so windows and dialogs can pass from
       one display to another.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Mirror</term>
     <listitem>
      <para> The same content is shown on all displays, with the same resolution
       and orientation for all. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Single display</term>
     <listitem>
      <para> Only one display is configured, effectively turning off the other
       displays. For example, an external monitor connected to a docked laptop
       with the lid closed. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-configure-sound">
  <title>Configuring sound settings</title>
  <para> The <guimenu>Sound</guimenu> tool lets you manage sound devices. Here
   you can select the general output volume or turn the sound off. </para>
  <para> To open the sound settings, right-click the desktop and choose
    <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Sound</guimenu></menuchoice>.</para>
  <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-sound">
   <title>Configuring sound settings</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_sound_devices.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="gnome_sound_devices.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  <para> Use the <guimenu>Output</guimenu> category to select the device for
   sound output. Choose the <guimenu>Balance</guimenu> setting you prefer. </para>
  <para> Use the <guimenu>Input</guimenu> category to set the input device
   volume or to mute the input temporarily. If you have more than one sound
   device, you can also select a default device for audio input in the
    <guimenu>Input Device</guimenu> list. </para>
  <para> You can also choose an <guimenu>Alert Sound</guimenu>. </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-default-apps">
  <title>Configuring default applications</title>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para> To change the default application for common tasks such as browsing
     the Internet, sending e-mails or playing multimedia files, right-click the
     desktop and select 
     <menuchoice><guimenu>Settings</guimenu><guimenu>Default Applications</guimenu></menuchoice>.</para>
    <figure xml:id="fig-gnome-settings-default-apps">
     <title>Default applications</title>
     <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
       <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_preferred_apps.png" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
       <imagedata fileref="gnome_preferences_preferred_apps.png" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </figure>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para> You can choose an application to handle Web, mail, calendar, music,
     videos or photographs. Select one of the available applications from the
     drop-down boxes for the task of your choice. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="task-GNOME-settings-share">
  <title>Configuring session sharing preferences</title>
  <para> To open a configuration dialog for allowing remote logins via SSH,
   right-click the desktop and choose <guimenu>Settings</guimenu>. Then choose
    <guimenu>Sharing</guimenu>. </para>
  <para> Before you can share anything, you need to turn on the switch in the
   upper part of the dialog. The switch also helps you if you quickly need to
   disable all sharing options. </para>
  <para> To enable logging in via SSH, click <guimenu>Remote Login</guimenu> and
   enter the administrator password. </para>
 </section>
</topic>
