<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/article_installation.xml
     and https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_bootstrap_install.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-adding-nodes"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Adding nodes with <command>crm cluster join</command></title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Add more nodes to the cluster with the <command>crm cluster join</command> script.
        The script only needs access to an existing cluster node and completes the basic
        setup on the current machine automatically. For more information, run the
        <command>crm cluster join --help</command> command.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    Perform this procedure on each additional node:
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     Log in to this node as the same user you set up the first node with.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     Start the script:
    </para>
    <para>
     If you set up the first node as &rootuser;, you can start the script with no additional parameters:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>crm cluster join</command></screen>
    <para>
     If you set up the first node as a <command>sudo</command> user, you must specify that user with
     the <option>-c</option> option:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>sudo crm cluster join -c <replaceable>USER@NODE1</replaceable></command></screen>
    <para>
      The script checks whether &chrony; is running, opens the required firewall ports, and
      configures &csync;.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
      If you did not already specify the first node with <option>-c</option>, you are prompted for
      its IP address or host name.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
      If you did not already configure passwordless SSH access between the nodes, you are prompted
      for the password of the first node. If required, the script generates SSH keys for the new node.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
     <para>
       Configure &corosync; for cluster communication:
     </para>
     <substeps>
       <step>
         <para>
           The script proposes an IP address for <literal>ring0</literal>. This network interface
           must have the same device name as the interface used for <literal>ring0</literal> on
           the first node. If it does not, enter the IP address of the correct network interface.
         </para>
       </step>
       <step>
         <para>
           If the cluster has two &corosync; rings configured, the script prompts you for an
           IP address for <literal>ring1</literal>. This network interface must have the same
           device name as the interface used for <literal>ring1</literal> on the first node.
         </para>
       </step>
     </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
     <para>
       The script asked for the admin@alice password again but the log doesn't say why... maybe csync?
     </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
    The script copies the cluster configuration from the first node, adjusts the timeout settings to
    consider the new node, and brings the new node online.
    </para>
  <para>
    You can check the status of the cluster with the <command>crm status</command> command.
  </para>
  <important>
    <title>Secure password for <systemitem>hacluster</systemitem></title>
    <para>
      The <command>crm cluster join</command> script creates a default cluster user and password.
      On each node, replace the default password with a secure one as soon as possible:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>sudo passwd hacluster</command></screen>
  </important>
</topic>
