<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/article_installation.xml
     and https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_bootstrap_install.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-initializing-cluster"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Initializing the cluster with <command>crm cluster init</command></title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Configure the cluster on the first node with the <command>crm cluster init</command>
        script. The script prompts you for basic information about the cluster and configures
        the required settings and services. For more information, run the
        <command>crm cluster init --help</command> command.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <itemizedlist>
    <title>Requirements</title>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        &sleha; is installed and up to date.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        All nodes have at least two network interfaces or a network bond, with static IP addresses
        listed in the <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file along with each node's FQDN and short
        host name.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem condition="twonode">
      <para>
        The &qnet; server is installed. If you log in to the &qnet; server as the &rootuser; user,
        passwordless SSH authentication must be enabled.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    Perform this procedure on only one node:
  </para>
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
        Log in to the first node as either the &rootuser; user or a user with
        <command>sudo</command> privileges.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Start the <command>crm cluster init</command> script:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>sudo crm cluster init</command></screen>
      <para>
        The script checks whether &chrony; is running, opens the required firewall ports, configures
        &csync;, and checks for SSH keys. If no SSH keys are available, the script generates them.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Configure &corosync; for cluster communication:
      </para>
      <substeps>
        <step>
          <para>
            Enter an IP address for the first communication channel (<literal>ring0</literal>).
            By default, the script proposes the address of the first available network interface.
            This could be either an individual interface or a bonded device. Accept this address
            or enter a different one.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            If the script detects multiple network interfaces, it asks whether you want to configure
            a second communication channel (<literal>ring1</literal>). If you configured the first
            channel with a bonded device, you can decline with <literal>n</literal>. If you need to
            configure a second channel, confirm with <literal>y</literal> and enter the IP address
            of another network interface. The two interfaces must be on different subnets.
          </para>
        </step>
      </substeps>
      <para>
        The script configures the default firewall ports for &corosync; communication.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Choose whether to set up &sbd; as the node fencing mechanism:
      </para>
      <substeps>
        <step>
          <para>
            Confirm with <literal>y</literal> that you want to use &sbd;.</para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            When prompted for a path to a block device, enter <literal>none</literal> to
            configure diskless &sbd;.</para>
        </step>
      </substeps>
      <para>
        The script configures &sbd;, including the relevant timeout settings<!--and a &stonith;
        cluster resource-->. Unlike disk-based &sbd;, diskless &sbd; does not require a &stonith;
        cluster resource.
      </para>
      <para>
        If no hardware watchdog is available, the script configures the software watchdog
        <systemitem>softdog</systemitem>.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Configure a virtual IP address for cluster administration with the &hawk; Web interface:
      </para>
      <substeps>
        <step>
          <para>
            Confirm with <literal>y</literal> that you want to configure a virtual IP address.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Enter an unused IP address to use as the administration IP for &hawk;.
          </para>
        </step>
      </substeps>
      <para>
        Instead of logging in to &hawk; on an individual cluster node, you can connect to the
        virtual IP address.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Choose whether to configure &qdevice; and &qnet;:
      </para>
      <para condition="threenode">
        For the minimal setup described in this document, decline with <literal>n</literal>.
      </para>
      <substeps condition="twonode">
        <step>
          <para>
            Confirm with <literal>y</literal> that you want to configure &qdevice; and &qnet;.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Enter the IP address or host name of the &qnet; server, with or without a user name.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you include a non-&rootuser; user name, you are prompted for the password, and the
                script configures passwordless SSH authentication from the node to the &qnet; server.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                If you omit a user name, the script defaults to the &rootuser; user, so passwordless
                SSH authentication must already be configured for the node to access the &qnet; server.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
          <para>
            For the remaining fields, accept the default values<!--or change them as required-->:
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Accept the proposed port (<literal>5403</literal>) or enter a different one.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Choose the algorithm that determines how votes are assigned. The default is
            <literal>ffsplit</literal>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Choose the method to use when a tie-breaker is required. The default is
            <literal>lowest</literal>.
          </para>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Choose whether to enable TLS for client certificate checking. The default is
            <literal>on</literal> (attempt to connect with TLS, but connect without TLS
            if it is not available).
          </para>
          <!--itemizedlist> IMO only needed for the full install guide, not the quick start
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <literal>off</literal>: TLS is not required and should not be tried.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <literal>on</literal>: Attempt to connect with TLS, but connect without TLS
                if it is not available.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <literal>required</literal>: TLS is mandatory. &qdevice; will exit with an
                error if TLS is not available.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist-->
        </step>
        <step performance="optional">
          <para>
            Enter heuristics commands to affect how votes are determined. To skip this
            step, leave the field blank.
          </para>
        </step>
      </substeps>
      <para condition="twonode">
        The script configures &qdevice; and &qnet;, including SSH keys, the CA and server
        certificates, and the firewall port. It also enables the required services on the
        cluster nodes and on the &qnet; server.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
    The script starts the cluster services to bring the cluster online and enable &hawk;. The URL to
    use for &hawk; is displayed on the screen. You can also check the status of the cluster with the
    <command>crm status</command> command.
  </para>
  <important>
    <title>Secure password for <systemitem>hacluster</systemitem></title>
    <para>
      The <command>crm cluster init</command> script creates a default cluster user and password.
      Replace the default password with a secure one as soon as possible:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>sudo passwd hacluster</command></screen>
  </important>
</topic>
