<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_maintenance.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-maintenance-stopping-cluster-services-one-node"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Stopping the cluster services for one node</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Stopping the cluster services means stopping &pace; and &corosync;. When used on one node,
        the node is no longer an active member of the cluster. The node's resources either move to
        another node, or stop if constraints prevent them from moving. However, if stopping a
        resource fails or times out, the node is fenced. To avoid attempting to stop resources
        and the cluster services at the same time, we recommend using this mode in combination
        with standby mode.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <warning>
    <title>Don't stop the cluster services in single-node maintenance mode</title>
    <para>
      Stopping the cluster services while in single-node maintenance mode can lead to undesirable
      effects. Resources that were running on this node might start on another node. Caution is
      required to prevent potential concurrency violations.
    </para>
  </warning>

  <para>
    Perform this procedure on the node you want to stop.
  </para>
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
        Log in to the node either as the &rootuser; user or as a user with <command>sudo</command>
        privileges.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Check the status of the cluster:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>sudo crm status</command></screen>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the node is in <literal>maintenance</literal> mode: Don't stop the cluster services,
            as this can lead to concurrency violations. Take the node out of maintenance mode first.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the node is in <literal>standby</literal> mode: The resources have either moved to
            other nodes or stopped, so you can safely stop the cluster services.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If the node isn't in either mode: When you stop the cluster services, the resources
            attempt to move to other nodes. If they can't move, they stop. However, if any
            resources fail to stop before the cluster's shutdown timeout, the node will be fenced.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Stop the cluster services on the node:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>sudo crm cluster stop</command></screen>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Check the status of the cluster services:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>sudo crm cluster status</command></screen>
      <para>
        Both &pace; and &corosync; should be <literal>inactive</literal>.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
</topic>
