<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="klp-troubleshoot"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Troubleshooting &klp; issues</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="dpopov@suse.com" its:translate="yes"/>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="sec-klp-lifecycle">
    <title>Checking expiration date of the live patch</title>
    <para>
      Make sure that the
      <package>lifecycle-data-sle-module-live-patching</package> is installed,
      then run the <command>zypper lifecycle</command> command. You should see
      expiration dates for live patches in the <literal>Package end of support
      if different from product</literal> section of the output.
    </para>
    <para>
      Every live patch receives updates for 13 months from the release of the
      underlying kernel package. The
      <link
    xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/products/live-patching/current-patches/">Maintained
      kernels, patch updates and lifecycle</link> page allows you to check
      expiration dates based on the running kernel version without installing
      the product extension.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-klp-man-patch-check">
    <title>Checking what kernel live patch packages are installed</title>
    <para>
      The kernel is live-patched if a <package>kernel-livepatch-*</package>
      package has been installed for the running kernel. You can use the command
      <command>zypper se --details kernel-livepatch-*</command> to check what
      kernel live patch packages are installed on your system.
     </para>
     </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-klp-man-patch-prevent-reboot">
    <title>Preventing reboot</title>
    <para>
      When the <package>kernel-default</package> package is installed, the
      update manager prompts you to reboot the system. To prevent this message
      from appearing, you can filter out kernel updates from the patching
      operation. This can be done by adding package locks with Zypper.
     </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-klp-man-patch-check-status">
    <title>Check patching status</title>
    <para>
      You can check patching status using the <command>klp status</command>
      command. To examine installed patches, run the <command>klp -v
      patches</command> command.
     </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-klp-man-patch-downgrade">
    <title>Downgrading a kernel patch</title>
    <para>
      If you find the latest live patch problematic, you can downgrade the
      currently installed live patch back to its previous version. Keep in mind
      that a system with kernel warnings or kernel error traces in the system
      log may not be suitable for the patch downgrade procedure. If you are
      unsure whether the system meets the requirements for a patch downgrade,
      contact SUSE Technical Support for help.
    </para>
    <para>
      To downgrade the latest kernel live patch, use the <command>klp
      downgrade</command> command. This command automatically detects the
      version of the latest live patch and installs the preceding one.
    </para>
  </section>
</topic>
