<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="pam-config-tool"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Configuring PAM using <command>pam-config</command></title>
    <!-- can be changed via merge
      in the assembly -->
    <!-- add author's e-mail -->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
      <para>
        The topic covers the usage of the <command>pam-config</command> tool.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    The <command>pam-config</command> tool helps you configure the global PAM
    configuration files (<filename>/etc/pam.d/common-*</filename>) and several
    selected application configurations. For a list of supported modules, use
    the <command>pam-config --list-modules</command> command. Use the
    <command>pam-config</command> command to maintain your PAM configuration
    files. Add new modules to your PAM configurations, delete other modules or
    modify options to these modules. When changing global PAM configuration
    files, no manual tweaking of the PAM setup for individual applications is
    required.
  </para>
  <para>
    A simple use case for <command>pam-config</command> involves the following:
  </para>
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Auto-generate a fresh Unix-style PAM configuration.</title>
        <para>
          Let <command>pam-config</command> create the simplest possible setup
          which you can extend later on. The <command>pam-config
          --create</command> command creates a simple Unix authentication
          configuration. Pre-existing configuration files not maintained by
          <command>pam-config</command> are overwritten, but backup copies are
          kept as <literal>*.pam-config-backup</literal>.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </step>
    <step>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Add a new authentication method.</title>
        <para>
          Adding a new authentication method (for example, LDAP) to your stack
          of PAM modules comes down to a simple <command>pam-config --add
          --ldap</command> command. LDAP is added wherever appropriate across
          all <filename>common-*-pc</filename> PAM configuration files.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </step>
    <step>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Add debugging for test purposes.</title>
        <para>
          To make sure the new authentication procedure works as planned, turn
          on debugging for all PAM-related operations. The <command>pam-config
          --add --ldap-debug</command> turns on debugging for LDAP-related PAM
          operations.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </step>
    <step>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Query your setup.</title>
        <para>
          Before you finally apply your new PAM setup, check if it contains all
          the options you wanted to add. The <command>pam-config --query
          --</command><replaceable>MODULE</replaceable> command lists both the
          type and the options for the queried PAM module.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </step>
    <step>
      <formalpara>
        <title>Remove the debug options.</title>
        <para>
          Finally, remove the debug option from your setup when you are
          entirely satisfied with the performance of it. The
          <command>pam-config --delete --ldap-debug</command> command turns off
          debugging for LDAP authentication. In case you had debugging options
          added for other modules, use similar commands to turn these off.
        </para>
      </formalpara>
    </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>
    For more information on the <command>pam-config</command> command and the
    options available, refer to the manual page of
    <command>pam-config(8)</command>.
  </para>
</topic>
