<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="task-configuring-raids-using-yast"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Configuring software RAID using &yast;</title>
    <!-- add author's e-mail -->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="jsindelarova@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
  </info>
  <para>
    The &yast; software RAID configuration can be reached from the &yast;
    Expert Partitioner. This partitioning tool also enables you to edit and
    delete existing partitions and create new ones that should be used with
    software RAID. These instructions apply on setting up RAID levels 0, 1, 5,
    and 6.
    <!-- Setting
      up RAID&nbsp;10 configurations is explained in <xref linkend="cha-raid10"/>. -->
  </para>
  <!--
    1. Yast - System- Partitioner
    2. Add - RAID
    3. Select RAID type, add disks.
    4. Select chunk size
    5.
    -->
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
        Launch &yast;.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        In the <guimenu>System</guimenu> menu, select
        <guimenu>Partitioner</guimenu> on the right.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        If necessary, create partitions that should be used with your RAID
        configuration. Do not format them and set the partition type to
        <guimenu>0xFD Linux RAID</guimenu>. When using existing partitions it
        is not necessary to change their partition type&mdash;&yast; will
        automatically do so.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is strongly recommended to use partitions stored on different hard
        disks to decrease the risk of losing data if one is defective
        (RAID&nbsp;1 and 5) and to optimize the performance of RAID&nbsp;0.
      </para>
      <para>
        For RAID&nbsp;0 at least two partitions are needed. RAID 1 requires
        exactly two partitions, while at least three partitions are required
        for RAID&nbsp;5. A RAID&nbsp;6 setup requires at least four partitions.
        It is recommended to use only partitions of the same size because each
        segment can contribute only the same amount of space as the smallest
        sized partition.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        In the <guimenu>Add</guimenu> menu select <guimenu>RAID</guimenu>.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Select a <guimenu>RAID Type</guimenu> and <guimenu>Add</guimenu> an
        appropriate number of partitions from the <guimenu>Available
        Devices</guimenu> dialog.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can optionally assign a <guimenu>RAID Name</guimenu> to your RAID.
        It will make it available as
        <filename>/dev/md/<replaceable>NAME</replaceable></filename>. See
        <xref linkend="task-naming-raids"/> for more information.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="fig-yast2-raid3">
        <title>Example RAID 1 configuration</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject role="fo">
            <imagedata fileref="raid-yast-assign-disks.png" width="80%"/>
          </imageobject>
          <imageobject role="html">
            <imagedata fileref="raid-yast-assign-disks.png" width="100%"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Select the <guimenu>Chunk Size</guimenu> and, if applicable, the
        <guimenu>Parity Algorithm</guimenu>. The optimal chunk size depends on
        the type of data and the type of RAID. See
        <link xlink:href="https://raid.wiki.kernel.org/index.php/RAID_setup#Chunk_sizes"/>
        for more information. More information on parity algorithms can be
        found with <command>man 8 mdadm</command> when searching for the
        <option>--layout</option> option. If unsure, stick with the defaults.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Choose a <guimenu>Role</guimenu> for the volume. Your choice here only
        affects the default values for the upcoming dialog. They can be changed
        in the next step. If in doubt, choose <guimenu>Raw Volume
        (Unformatted)</guimenu>.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Under <guimenu>Formatting Options</guimenu>, select <guimenu>Format
        device</guimenu>, then select the <guimenu>File system</guimenu>. The
        content of the <guimenu>Options</guimenu> menu depends on the file
        system. Usually there is no need to change the defaults.
      </para>
      <para>
        Under <guimenu>Mounting Options</guimenu>, select <guimenu>Mount
        device</guimenu>, then select the mount point. Select <guimenu>Fstab
        Options</guimenu> to add special mounting options for the volume.
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Proceed with <guimenu>Next</guimenu>.
      </para>
    </step>
  </procedure>
  <important>
    <title>RAID on disks</title>
    <para>
      While the partitioner makes it possible to create a RAID on top of disks
      instead of partitions, we do not recommend this approach for a number of
      reasons. Installing a bootloader on such RAID is not supported, so you
      need to use a separate device for booting. Tools like
      <package>fdisk</package> and <package>parted</package> do not work
      properly with such RAIDs, which may lead to incorrect diagnosis and
      actions by a person who is unaware of the RAID's particular setup.
    </para>
  </important>
</topic>
