<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
     <!ENTITY snapper "entity-value">
     <!ENTITY yast "entity-value">
     <!ENTITY prompt.sudo "entity-value">
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="snapper-restore-files"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Using &snapper; to restore files</title>
   <meta name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
     <para>
     &snapper; provides the functionality to restore system files that may 
     have been accidentally deleted or modified, or to restore previous versions
     of files.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info> 
    <para>To use the restore feature, timeline snapshots for the root partition 
     must be activated. They provide a historical record of the state of the file 
     system over time. This allows you to select a specific snapshot to restore 
     from, rather than having to restore the entire file system.
     You can also find out which modifications were made at a certain point 
     in time. To do so, use &snapper;'s diff feature.</para>
    <para>
     Being able to restore files is especially interesting for data that may
     reside on subvolumes or partitions for which snapshots are not taken by
     default. For example, to restore files from home directories, you need to 
     create a separate &snapper; configuration for <filename>/home</filename>
     doing automatic timeline snapshots.
    </para>
    <warning>
     <title>Restoring files compared to rollback</title>
     <para>
      Snapshots taken from the root file system (defined by &snapper;'s root
      configuration) can be used to do a system rollback. The recommended way
      to do such a rollback is to boot from the snapshot and then perform the
      rollback.
     </para>
     <para>
      Performing a rollback would also be possible by restoring all files from a
      root file system snapshot as described below. However, this is not
      recommended. You may restore single files, for example, a configuration
      file from the <systemitem>/etc</systemitem> directory, but not the
      complete list of files from the snapshot.
     </para>
     <para>
      This restriction only affects snapshots taken from the root file system.
     </para>
    </warning>
    <procedure xml:id="proc-snapper-restore-yast">
     <title>Restoring files using the &yast; <guimenu>Snapper</guimenu> module</title>
     <para>To restore files with the &snapper; module in &yast;, follow these steps:</para>
     <step>
      <para>
       Open the <guimenu>Miscellaneous</guimenu> section in &yast; or enter the command
       <command>yast2 snapper</command> to open it, and start the <guimenu>Filesystem
       Snapshots</guimenu> module.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select the <guimenu>Current Configuration</guimenu> from which to choose
       a snapshot.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select a timeline snapshot from which to restore a file and click
       <guimenu>Show Changes</guimenu>. Timeline snapshots are of the type
       <guimenu>Single</guimenu> with a description value of
       <guimenu>timeline</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Select a file from the text box by clicking the file name. The difference
       between the snapshot version and the current system is shown. Activate
       the check box to select the file for restore. Do so for all files you
       want to restore.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Click <guimenu>Restore Selected</guimenu> and confirm the action by
       clicking <guimenu>Yes</guimenu>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure xml:id="proc-snapper-restore-cmdl">
     <title>Restoring files using the <command>snapper</command> command</title>
     <para>To restore files with the <command>snapper</command> command, perform 
      the following steps:</para> 
     <step>
      <para>
       Get a list of timeline snapshots for a specific configuration by running
       the following command:
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.sudo;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> list -t single | grep timeline</screen>
      <para>
       <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> needs to be replaced by an existing
       &snapper; configuration. Use <command>snapper list-configs</command> to
       display a list.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Get a list of changed files for a given snapshot by running the following
       command:
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.sudo;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> status <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable>..0</screen>
      <para>
       Replace <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable> with the ID for the snapshot
       from which you want to restore the files.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Optionally list the differences between the current file version and the
       one from the snapshot by running
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.sudo;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> diff <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable>..0 <replaceable>FILE NAME</replaceable></screen>
      <para>
       If you do not specify <replaceable>&lt;FILE NAME&gt;</replaceable>, the
       difference for all files is shown.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       To restore one or more files, run
      </para>
 <screen>&prompt.sudo;snapper -c <replaceable>CONFIG</replaceable> -v undochange <replaceable>SNAPSHOT_ID</replaceable>..0 <replaceable>FILENAME1</replaceable> <replaceable>FILENAME2</replaceable></screen>
      <para>
       If you do not specify file names, all changed files will be restored.
      </para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
  
  <warning>
    <title>Data consistency</title>
    <para>
     There is no mechanism to ensure data consistency when creating a snapshot.
     Whenever a file (for example, a database) is written at the same time as the
     snapshot is being created, it will result in a corrupted or partly written
     file. Restoring such a file will cause problems. Furthermore, certain system
     files, such as <filename>/etc/mtab</filename>, must never be restored.
     Therefore, we strongly recommend to <emphasis>always</emphasis> closely
     review the list of changed files and their diffs. Only restore files that
     really belong to the action you want to revert.
    </para>
   </warning>
 
</topic>
