<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="systemd-troubleshooting" xml:lang="en"
 role="task"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <title>&systemd; troubleshooting</title>
</info>
<para>You can use the following troubleshooting tips to identify and resolve issues
  with &systemd; services and ensure a smooth system operation.
  </para>

  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Check the syntax of your &systemd; unit file with the
        <command>systemd-analyze verify <replaceable>SERVICE</replaceable></command></emphasis></term>
      <listitem> <para>Before starting or enabling a &systemd; service, check the syntax of the unit file to ensure there are no errors.
        For example: </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemd-analyze verify /etc/systemd/system/my-custom-service.service</screen>
<para>The command analyzes the unit file and reports any syntax errors, missing files, or other issues.
  You must fix any reported issues before enabling and starting the service.</para>
</listitem>
       </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Check the logs for your service with the <command>
        journalctl -u <replaceable>SERVICE</replaceable></command> command</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If you experience any issue with a &systemd; service, check the service's log.
          For example:
        </para>

<screen>&prompt.sudo; journalctl -u my-custom-service.service</screen>
<para>The command displays logs for the specified service, including any error messages, warnings, or other relevant information.
  You can use these logs to identify and fix issues with the service.</para>
        </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Use the <command>systemd-analyze plot</command> command to visualize the boot process</emphasis></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          If a service is causing issues during the boot process, you can use the
          <command>systemd-analyze plot command</command> to visualize the boot process and identify issues.
          For example:
        </para>

<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemd-analyze plot > boot-plot.svg</screen>
<para>The command creates an SVG file called <filename>boot-plot.svg</filename> that contains a graphical representation of the boot process and potential issues. This includes the start and stop time of each service. You can open this file in an SVG-compatible image viewer or Web browser to analyze services that are causing issues during the boot process.</para>
        </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Troubleshoot failed services</emphasis></term>
      <listitem> <para>To find out which services have failed and to inspect the log output: </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl --state=failed</screen>
</listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis>Check the runtime status of a service</emphasis></term>
        <listitem> <para>To find out the current runtime status of a service:</para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl status <replaceable>SERVICE</replaceable></screen>
  </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
       <term><emphasis>Shutdown or reboot takes long</emphasis></term>
      <listitem> <para>If the shutdown or reboot takes long, it could be a service that is not exiting. &systemd;
        waits for some time for each service to exit before trying to terminate it.
        A common issue is a suspended service or a stalled shutdown. To find out, use the following:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl poweroff
  Failed to power off system via logind: There's already a shutdown or sleep operation in progress
</screen>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl list-jobs</screen>
<para>You can cancel the running and waiting jobs, and again shut down or reboot: </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl cancel</screen>
 <screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl stop systemd-suspend.service</screen>
</listitem>
       </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</topic>