<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="systemd-convert-sysv" xml:lang="en"
 role="task"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <title>Converting SysV init to &systemd; </title>
</info>
<para>
SysV init is the traditional initialization system used by older Linux distributions.
It is often referred to as init. &systemd; is now the default initialization system for <phrase os="sles">
&productname; 16</phrase> <phrase os="sle4sap"></phrase>.
</para>
<section xml:id="systemd-convert-benefits">
  <title>Benefits of converting SysV init to &systemd;</title>
    <para></para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><emphasis>Faster boot time:</emphasis> &systemd; utilizes parallel service startup and socket activation
 drastically reducing the boot time compared to SysV init's sequential execution model.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para> <emphasis>Improved dependency management:</emphasis> &systemd; uses clear, declarative unit files to define dependencies, ensuring services start in the correct order reliably
 unlike the complex and error-prone shell scripts of SysV init.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>Reliable process tracking:</emphasis> &systemd; uses Linux Control Groups (Cgroups) for definitive process tracking, guaranteeing that all associated processes for a service are stopped or managed correctly.
</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><emphasis>Simplified and Unified Configuration:</emphasis>With &systemd;, configuration is moved from complex, distribution-specific shell scripts to standardized, easy-to-read unit files
  , simplifying administration and maintenance across different Linux systems.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para><emphasis>More feature availability:</emphasis> &systemd; offers a unified suite of tools like Journald,timer units (replacing cron) and on-demand service activation.
  This integrates core system management functions that previously required separate, disparate tools.
</para></listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="systemd-convert-steps">
  <title></title>
  <procedure>
<step><para></para></step>
</procedure>
</section>
</topic>