<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="terminal-signals-systemd"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Sending termination signals to &systemd; services</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com"/>
  </info>

    <para>
      Each service in &systemd; is categorized into a control group which makes it easy to identify
      all parent and child processes of a service. This enables you to send a signal to each of these processes.
      You can send a signal to a &systemd; service or to the individual processes that belong to a service.
    </para>
    <para>You can identify and stop processes in &systemd; services with the <command>systemd-cgls</command> command.
    The <command>systemd-cgls</command> command displays all processes that belong to a &systemd; service.
    </para>
    It's a bit hard to read. In my opinion, an admonition should be easy to see and read.
Maybe move all the bad things that can happen into a list?

Suggested change
    <important><para>The D-Bus service is the message bus for communication between &systemd; clients and the &systemd; manager that is running as pid 1.
      D-Bus is a stand-alone daemon and an integral part of the init infrastructure. Terminating D-Bus or restarting it in the running system is similar to an attempt to terminate or restart pid 1.
      It breaks the &systemd; client and server communication and make most &systemd; functions unusable.
      Terminating or restarting D-Bus is neither recommended nor supported.
      Updating D-Bus or D-Bus-related packages requires a reboot.
      You can run <command>sudo zypper ps -s</command> to check if a reboot is required.
      If D-Bus appears among the listed services, you need to reboot the system.
     Note that D-Bus is updated even when automatic updates are configured to skip the packages that require reboot.</para></important>
    <important>
     <para>The D-Bus service is the message bus for communication between &systemd; clients and the &systemd; manager that is running as pid 1.</para>
     <para>
      D-Bus is a stand-alone daemon and an integral part of the init infrastructure.
      Keep in mind the following properties:
      </para>

      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      Terminating D-Bus or restarting it in the running system is similar to an attempt to terminate or restart pid 1.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      It breaks the &systemd; client and server communication and make most &systemd; functions unusable.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      Terminating or restarting D-Bus is neither recommended nor supported.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>
      Updating D-Bus or D-Bus-related packages requires a reboot.
      You can run <command>sudo zypper ps -s</command> to check if a reboot is required. If D-Bus appears among the listed services, you need to reboot the system.
      </para>
      </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
          <para>
     Note that D-Bus is updated even when automatic updates are configured to skip the packages that require reboot.</para>
     </important>

    <procedure><step><para>List all control groups and their processes:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>systemd-cgls</command></screen></step>
    <step><para> Display all processes that belong to a particular service, for example,:
      the <literal>libvirtd.service</literal> service:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.user;<command>systemd-cgls -u libvirtd.service</command></screen></step>
    <step><para>Send a termination signal to the service.
      <systemitem>SIGTERM</systemitem> (15) is the default:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>systemctl kill <replaceable>SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></command></screen></step>
    <step><para>Send a different signal to a service with the <option>-s</option>
      option, such as <systemitem>SIGKILL</systemitem> (9):
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>systemctl kill -s <replaceable>9</replaceable> <replaceable>SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></command></screen></step>
    <step><para>By default the <command>kill</command> command sends the signal to
      <option>all</option> processes of the specified control group.
      You can restrict it to the <option>control</option> or the
      <option>main</option> process.
      The latter is, for example, useful to force a service to reload its
      configuration by sending <systemitem>SIGHUP</systemitem>:
    </para>
    <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>systemctl kill -s SIGHUP --kill-who=main <replaceable>SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></command></screen></step>
  </procedure>
 </topic>