<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="systemd-timer-mailto"
       role="task" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <title>Getting notified by email if a timer fails</title>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Cron comes with the MAILTO feature, where you only have to specify an email address with
        MAILTO to get an email notification with the output of the respective script(s). systemd
        does not offer such functionality out of the box. The following procedure describes a
        workaround to get email notifications when a timer fails.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    You need to
  </para>
  <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        create a script that sends an e-mail.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        create systemd service file running the email script.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        test the service file.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        call this service file via <literal>OnFailure</literal> within the service that is run by
        the timer.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
  <procedure>
    <step>
      <para>
        Create the script <filename class="directory">/usr/local/bin/send_systemd_email</filename>.
        In the following example we are using the <command>mailx</command> command from package
        <package>mailx</package>. Note that the script requires two parameters:
        <literal>$1</literal>, the email address, and <literal>$2</literal>, the name of the unit
        file used by the timer. Both parameters will be provided by the unit file running the mail
        script.
      </para>
      <screen>#!/bin/sh
systemctl status --full "$2" | mailx -S sendwait\
 -s "Timer failure for $2" -r root@$HOSTNAME $1
</screen>
      <para>
        Make sure the scrtipt you just created is executable:
      </para>
      <screen>sudo chmod 755 /usr/local/bin/send_systemd_email</screen>
      <note>
        <title>Requires Postfix</title>
        <para>
          Note that in order to send emails you need to install and configure the email server
          Postfix on your system. The latter can be done via <menuchoice><guimenu>&yast;</guimenu>
           <guimenu>Network Services</guimenu> <guimenu>Mail Server</guimenu></menuchoice>.
        </para>
      </note>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        Create the file
        <filename>/etc/systemd/system/send_email_to_<replaceable>user</replaceable>@.service</filename>.
        Note that you need to replace <replaceable>user</replaceable> in the file name with the
        login of the user that should receive the email.
      </para>
      <screen>[Unit]
Description=Send systemd status information by email for %i to <replaceable>user</replaceable>

[Service]
Type=oneshot
ExecStart=/usr/local/bin/send_systemd_email <replaceable>e-mail_address</replaceable> %i
User=root
Group=systemd-journal
</screen>
      <para>
        Note that you need to replace <replaceable>user</replaceable> and
        <replaceable>e-mail_address</replaceable> in the file with the login and the e-mail address
        of the user that should receive the email. <literal>%i</literal> is the name of the service
        that has failed (it will be passed on to the e-mail service (by the <literal>%n</literal>
        parameter).
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        To make sure the service file works correctly, verify it and fix any errors that may be
        reported:
      </para>
      <screen>systemd-analyze verify /etc/systemd/system/send_email_to_<replaceable>user</replaceable>@.service</screen>
      <para>
        If the command returns no output, the file has passed the verification successfully.
      </para>
      <para>
        Now start the service using the <literal>dbus</literal> instance for testing (you may use
        any other service that is currently running. We are using dbus here, because this service
        is guaranteed to run on any installation).
      </para>
      <screen>sudo systemctl start send_email_to_<replaceable>user</replaceable>@dbus.service</screen>
      <para>
        If successful, <replaceable>e-mail_address</replaceable> will receive an e-mail with the
        subject <literal>Timer failure for dbus</literal> containing dbus status messages in the
        body. (Note that this is just a test, there is no problem with the dbus service. You can
        safely delete the mail, no action is required).
      </para>
      <para>
        If the test e-mail has been successfully send, proceed by integrating it into your timer
        file(s).
      </para>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        To add e-mail notification to your timer, add an <literal>OnFailure</literal> option to the
        <literal>Unit</literal> section of the <emphasis>service</emphasis> file that is started by
        the timer:
      </para>
      <screen>[Unit]
Description="Hello World script"
OnFailure<co xml:id="systemd-timer-mailto-onfailure"/>=send_email_to_<replaceable>user</replaceable><co xml:id="systemd-timer-mailto-user"/>@%n<co xml:id="systemd-timer-mailto-name"/>.service

[Service]
ExecStart=/usr/local/bin/helloworld.sh
</screen>
      <calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="systemd-timer-mailto-onfailure">
          <para>
            The <literal>OnFailure</literal> option takes a service as a argument.
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="systemd-timer-mailto-user">
          <para>
            Replace with the login name part of the service unit's file name.
          </para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="systemd-timer-mailto-name">
          <para>
            Provides the name of the service (<literal>helloworld</literal> in this example). This
            name is available in the e-mail service file as %i.
          </para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>
    </step>
    <step>
      <para>
        You successfully set up failure notification for systemd services.
      </para>
      <tip>
        <title>Scope of usage</title>
        <para>
          Using the e-mail for systemd service failure notification is not restricted to systemd
          timers. It can be used with any systemd service. The e-mailing service created above can
          be also used with multiple service files simultaneously.
        </para>
      </tip>
      <tip>
        <title>Sending e-mail notifications to multiple users</title>
        <para>
          While the e-mail script is generic, the email service file has the recipient's e-mail
          address hard-coded. In order to send notification emails to a different user, copy the
          e-mail service file and replace the user login in the file name and the e-mail address
          within the copy.
        </para>
        <para>
          To send a failure notification to several people at the same time, add the respective
          service files space-separated to the service file:
        </para>
        <screen>OnFailure=send_email_to_&exampleuser_plain;@%n.service send_email_to_&exampleuserII_plain;@%n.service</screen>
      </tip>
    </step>
  </procedure>
</topic>
