<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="tr-up-rollback"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Performing system rollback</title><!-- can be changed via merge
in the assembly -->
    <!-- add author's e-mail -->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="jsindelarova@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract><!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
      <para>
      GRUB 2 enables booting from btrfs snapshots and thus allows you to use
      any older functional snapshot in case the new snapshot does not work
      correctly.
    </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
      When booting a snapshot, the parts of the file system included in the
      snapshot are mounted read-only; all other file systems and parts that are
      excluded from snapshots are mounted read-write and can be modified.
    </para>
    <tip>
      <title>Rolling back to a specific installation state</title>
      <para>
        An initial bootable snapshot is created at the end of the initial
        system installation. You can go back to that state at any time by
        booting this snapshot. The snapshot can be identified by the
        description <literal>after installation</literal>.
      </para>
    </tip>
    <para>
      There are two methods to perform a system rollback.
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          From a running system, you can set the default snapshot, see more in
          <xref linkend="proc-running-snapshot"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Especially in cases where the current snapshot is broken, you can
          boot into the new snapshot and set it to default. For details, refer
          to <xref linkend="proc-boot-snapshot"/>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      If your current snapshot is functional, you can use the following
      procedure for a system rollback.
    </para>
    <procedure xml:id="proc-running-snapshot">
      <title>Rollback from a running system</title>
      <step>
        <para>
          Choose the snapshot that should be set as default and run:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;snapper list</screen>
        <para>
          to get a list of snapshots. Note the number of the snapshot
          to be set as default.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Set the snapshot as default by running:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;transactional-update rollback <replaceable>snapshot_number</replaceable></screen>
        <para>
          If you omit the <replaceable>snapshot number</replaceable>, the
          current snapshot will be set as default.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Reboot your system to boot into the new default snapshot.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    <para>
      The following procedure is used in case the current snapshot is broken
      and you cannot boot into it.
    </para>
    <procedure xml:id="proc-boot-snapshot">
      <title>Rollback to a working snapshot</title>
      <step>
        <para>
          Reboot your system and select <literal>Start bootloader from a
          read-only snapshot</literal>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Choose a snapshot to boot. The snapshots are sorted according to the
          date of creation, with the latest one at the top.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Log in to your system and check whether everything works as expected.
          The data written to directories excluded from the snapshots will stay
          untouched.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          If the snapshot you booted into is not suitable for the rollback,
          reboot your system and choose another one.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the snapshot works as expected, you can perform the rollback by
          running the following command:
        </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update rollback</command></screen>
        <para>
          And reboot afterwards.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
</topic>
