<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="transactional-update-no-reboot"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Applying multiple changes using &tr-up; without rebooting</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        The &tr-up; command applies changes to the root file system on a
        transactional system.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    The default &tr-up; behavior is to create a new snapshot from the current
    root file system after each change. To apply the changes, you need to reboot
    the host. You cannot run the &tr-up; command multiple times without
    rebooting to add more changes to the snapshot, because this creates
    separate independent snapshots that do not include changes from the
    previous snapshots.
  </para>
  <para>
    To make multiple changes to the root file system, you have several options, which are
    described in the following sections:
  </para>
  <section xml:id="transactional-update-continue-option">
    <title>The &tr-up; <option>--continue</option> option</title>
    <para>
      Use the &tr-up; command together with the <option>--continue</option>
      option to make multiple changes without rebooting. A separate snapshot is
      created on each run that contains all changes from the previous snapshot,
      plus your new changes. The final snapshot includes all changes. To apply
      them, reboot the system and your final snapshot becomes the new root file
      system.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="transactional-update-run">
    <title>The &tr-up-run; command</title>
    <para>
      The &tr-up; <command>run</command> command normally runs only a single
      command. However, you can use it to run multiple commands in one
      transactional session by concatenating them within a command shell such as
      <command>bash</command>, for example:
    </para>
<screen>&prompt.root;<command>transactional-update run bash -c 'ls &amp;&amp; date; if [ true ]; then echo -n "Hello "; echo '\''world'\''; fi'</command></screen>
    <note>
      <para>
        The &tr-up-run; command has the same limitations as the &tr-up-shell;
        command described in <xref linkend="transactional-update-shell"/>
        except that the entered commands are logged in the
        <filename>/var/log/transactional-update.log</filename> file.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="transactional-update-shell">
    <title>The &tr-up; shell</title>
    <para>
      The &tr-up-shell; command opens a shell in the transactional-update
      environment. In the shell, you can enter almost any Linux command to make
      changes to the file system, for example, install multiple packages with
      the <command>zypper</command> command or perform changes to files that
      are part of the read-only file system. You can also verify that the
      changes you previously made with the &tr-up; command are correct.
    </para>
    <important>
      <para>
        The transactional shell has several limitations. For example, you
        cannot operate start or stop services using &systemd; commands, or
        modify the <filename>/var</filename> partition because it is not
        mounted. Also, commands entered during a shell session are not logged
        in the <filename>/transactional-update.log</filename> file.
      </para>
    </important>
    <para>
      All changes that you make to the file system are part of a single
      snapshot. After you finish making changes to the file system and leave
      the shell with the <command>exit</command> command, you need to reboot
      the host to apply the changes.
    </para>    
  </section>
</topic>
