<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="troubleshoot-iscsi"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Troubleshooting iSCSI</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
Effectively troubleshooting an iSCSI environment begins with recognizing that most disruptions stem from a handful of common known issues, ranging from basic network reachability and firewall blockages on port 3260 to more nuanced configuration errors like IQN mismatches, incorrect CHAP authentication credentials, and MTU inconsistencies that trigger intermittent packet loss.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
    <para>
The following are some known issues and possible solutions for iSCSI target and iSCSI initiator:
 </para>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Portal error when setting up target LUNs on an iSCSI LIO target server</term>
<listitem>
  <para>
    When adding or editing an iSCSI LIO target group, you get an error:
   </para>
<screen>Problem setting network portal <replaceable>IP_ADDRESS</replaceable>:3260</screen>
   <para>
    The <filename>/var/log/YasT2/y2log</filename> log file contains the
    following error:
   </para>
<screen>find: `/sys/kernel/config/target/iscsi': No such file or directory</screen>
   <para>
    This problem occurs if the iSCSI LIO Target Server software is not
    currently running. To resolve this issue, exit &yast;, manually start iSCSI
    LIO at the command line with <command>systemctl start targetcli</command>,
    then try again.
   </para>
   <para>
    You can also enter the following to check if <command>configfs</command>,
    <command>iscsi_target_mod</command>, and <command>target_core_mod</command>
    are loaded. A sample response is shown.
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;lsmod | grep iscsi
iscsi_target_mod      295015  0
target_core_mod       346745  4
iscsi_target_mod,target_core_pscsi,target_core_iblock,target_core_file
configfs               35817  3 iscsi_target_mod,target_core_mod
scsi_mod              231620  16
iscsi_target_mod,target_core_pscsi,target_core_mod,sg,sr_mod,mptctl,sd_mod,
scsi_dh_rdac,scsi_dh_emc,scsi_dh_alua,scsi_dh_hp_sw,scsi_dh,libata,mptspi,
mptscsih,scsi_transport_spi</screen>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>iSCSI LIO targets are not visible from other systems</term>
  <listitem><para>If you use a firewall on the target server, you must open the iSCSI port
    that you are using to allow other systems to see the iSCSI LIO targets.
   TCP port 3260 is the port number for the iSCSI protocol, as defined by IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers Authority).
  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
  <varlistentry><term>Data packets dropped for iSCSI traffic</term>
    <listitem><para> A firewall might drop packets if it gets too busy. The default for the SUSE
      Firewall is to drop packets after three minutes. If you find that iSCSI
      traffic packets are being dropped, consider configuring the SUSE Firewall
      to queue packets instead of dropping them when it gets too busy.
    </para></listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term>Using iSCSI volumes with LVM</term>
      <listitem><para>Use the troubleshooting tips in this section when using LVM on iSCSI
        targets.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
        <varlistentry><term>Check if the iSCSI initiator discovery occurs at boot</term>
          <listitem><para>When you set up the iSCSI Initiator, ensure that you enable discovery at
            boot time so that udev can discover the iSCSI devices at boot time and set
            up the devices to be used by LVM.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
            <varlistentry><term>Check that iSCSI target discovery occurs at boot</term>
              <listitem><para>Remember that <filename>udev</filename> provides the default setup for
                devices. Ensure that all of the applications that create devices are
                started at boot time so that <command>udev</command> can recognize and
                assign devices for them at system start-up. If the application or service
                is not started until later, <command>udev</command> does not create the
                device automatically as it would at boot time.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
                <varlistentry><term>iSCSI targets are mounted when the configuration file is set to manual</term>
                  <listitem><para> When Open-iSCSI starts, it can mount the targets even if the
                    <literal>node.startup</literal> option is set to manual in the
                    <filename>/etc/iscsi/iscsid.conf</filename> file if you manually modified
                    the configuration file.
                   </para>
                   <para>
                    Check the
                    <filename>/etc/iscsi/nodes/<replaceable>TARGET_NAME</replaceable>/<replaceable>IP_ADDRESS</replaceable>,<replaceable>PORT</replaceable>/default</filename>
                    file. It contains a <literal>node.startup</literal> setting that overrides
                    the <filename>/etc/iscsi/iscsid.conf</filename> file. Setting the mount
                    option to manual by using the &yast; interface also sets
                    <literal>node.startup = manual</literal> in the
                    <filename>/etc/iscsi/nodes/<replaceable>TARGET_NAME</replaceable>/<replaceable>IP_ADDRESS</replaceable>,<replaceable>PORT</replaceable>/default
                    </filename>files.
                  </para></listitem></varlistentry>
              </variablelist>
</topic>