<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/adm_sudo.xml -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="troubleshoot-kdump"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <title>How to troubleshoot common &kdump; issues</title>
    <abstract>
<para>
Troubleshooting &kdump; is a critical process to ensure that your system can successfully capture a vmcore file during a kernel crash, which is often the only way to diagnose system crashes.
When troubleshooting &kdump;, the process usually fails at one of three stages: during boot (memory reservation), during the crash when the dump does not start, or during the save process when the file is not written.
</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
    <section xml:id="troubleshooting-kdump">
    <title>Crash kernel memory reserved is insufficient</title>
    <para>One of the most common reasons &kdump; fails is that the amount of crash kernel
      memory reserved is insufficient. Different system configurations may require
      more memory than estimated by <command>kdumptool calibrate</command> and set up automatically in
      the boot loader config by the <literal>kdump-commandline.service</literal>.</para>
      <para>During &kdump;, if you see error messages mentioning low memory and invoking the
Out of Memory (OOM) killer, this is the likely cause. If you don't see such messages, trying with increased crash kernel reservation is a good
first step.</para>
<procedure>
<step><para>Find the size of the current automatically configured crash kernel reservation
  by checking the kernel command line:</para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo; cat /proc/cmdline</screen>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><literal>crashkernel=X M</literal></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><literal>crashkernel=Y M,low</literal></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><literal>crashkernel=Z M,high</literal></para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>
  Add up the values of <replaceable>X</replaceable>, <replaceable>Y</replaceable>,
  and <replaceable>Z</replaceable> to determine the total size of the current
  reservation in MiB (<replaceable>current</replaceable>).
</para>
</step>
<step><para>Manually set the new reservation by editing the <filename>/etc/sysconfig/kdump</filename>
  file. Locate and change the value of the <varname>KDUMP_CRASHKERNEL</varname>
  variable to double the current size:</para>
<screen>KDUMP_CRASHKERNEL="crashkernel=&lt;2 * current&gt;M"</screen>
</step>
<step>
  <para>
      Reboot the system to apply the new memory parameters:
  </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo; reboot</screen>
</step>
<step>
  <para>
      Repeat this process a few times until Kdump successfully executes without errors.
  </para>
  <note>
      <para>
          Fine-tuning crash kernel memory involves finding the smallest RAM reservation
          that successfully captures a crash dump without triggering OOM errors in the
          capture kernel. Fine-tune your final setting using the range between your
          last working and non-working values to avoid wasting system memory.
      </para>
  </note>
</step>
</procedure>
<section xml:id="related-termination-signals-systemd">
  <title>Other troubleshooting issues</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>Issues with switching to a text virtual terminal</term>
<listitem><para>Check the &kdump; boot messages for errors. If the screen is blank, the system is likely failing to switch to the text virtual terminal. To fix this, configure a serial console to capture the output; you cannot troubleshoot the issue without these messages.</para>
  <para>Once you get some output, you can increase &kdump; verbosity. Setting
  <literal>KDUMP_VERBOSE</literal> to 11 turns on debugging output during all stages of the &kdump;
   process and results in the following behavior:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>Removes the quiet option from the capture kernel command line.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Runs the <literal>kdump-save</literal> script with -x.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Runs <literal>makedumpfile </literal> with debugging.</para></listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
</varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
    <term> <literal>makedumpfile</literal> or network config errors </term>
    <listitem><para> During the capture kernel boot, if you see problems with
     <literal>makedumpfile</literal>, network config, etc., set <literal>KDUMP_CONTINUE_ON_ERROR=false</literal>
      or <literal>KDUMP_IMMEDIATE_REBOOT=false</literal>. This opens up an interactive shell when
      an error occurs or when <literal>makedumpfile</literal> finishes, enabling you to manually debug problems
      from within the capture system.
    </para></listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Dracut errors</term>
      <listitem><para>If you see dracut errors during the boot of the capture system, add
        dracut debugging options to <literal> KDUMP_COMMANDLINE_APPEND</literal>.
      </para></listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term> <literal>kdump initramfs</literal> does not generate correctly</term>
        <listitem><para>If <literal>kdump initramfs</literal> does not generate correctly, turn on debugging when generating it;
<command>mkdumprd -fd</command>. You can also unpack and inspect the generated initramfs image with the <command>lsinitrd --unpack /var/lib/kdump/initrd
</command> command. </para></listitem>
        </varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
 </section>
      </topic>