<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="yama-troubleshooting" xml:lang="en"
 role="task"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <info>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <title>Troubleshooting Yama</title>
</info>
<para>
  Troubleshooting Yama is essential because an overly restrictive <literal>ptrace_scope</literal> can silently break critical system operations, such as debugging with GDB or generating crash reports, directly impacting a developer's ability to diagnose software failures.
  </para>
<para> Common troubleshooting scenarios include:</para>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><emphasis>Debuggers (GDB) Cannot Attach to processes</emphasis></term>
      <listitem> <para>This is the most common issue. You try to debug a running process with GDB or strace and you get an <literal>Operation not permitted</literal> error, even if you own the process.
   To resolve issues where a restrictive YAMA <literal>ptrace_scope</literal> (typically levels 1 or 2) prevents a debugger from attaching to a process, lower the kernel's security constraints. By checking the current status via <command>cat /proc/sys/kernel/yama/ptrace_scope</command> and subsequently updating it to 0 using the command <command>echo 0 | sudo tee /proc/sys/kernel/yama/ptrace_scope</command> , you temporarily grant permissions for a user to debug their own non-privileged processes.
   This adjustment effectively relaxes the system's <literal>ptrace</literal> restrictions, enabling standard debugging tools to function without being blocked by the Linux security module.
   </para>
</listitem>
 </varlistentry>
 <varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis>Permissions reverting After reboot</emphasis></term>
  <listitem> <para>You manually set <literal>ptrace_scope</literal>  to 0 to allow development work, but every time the machine reboots, it switches back to 1, breaking your workflow.
 Because the <literal>/proc</literal> file system is volatile, any manual changes to the YAMA <literal>ptrace_scope</literal> are lost upon reboot, as security-oriented distributions reset this value via default configuration files.
 To make a permanent adjustment, modify the persistent configuration located at <literal>/etc/sysctl.d/10-ptrace.conf</literal> or a similar path by changing the value of <literal>kernel.yama.ptrace_scope </literal> from 1 to 0.
 Save the file and apply the changes with <command>sudo sysctl -p</command>. This ensures that the relaxed debugging permissions remain active across system restarts.
  </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
  <term><emphasis>Admin only debugging (scope 2)</emphasis></term>
  <listitem> <para>You are a developer with &sudo; access, but you still cannot attach to a process you started, even after trying to use <command>sudo gdb</command>.
 When the YAMA <literal>ptrace_scope</literal>  is set to level 2 (Admin-only attach), the system enforces a strict security policy that prevents users and sometimes even root users from attaching to a process that is already running unless they possess specific capabilities like <literal>CAP_SYS_PTRACE</literal> .
To bypass this restriction without lowering the system's global security level, initiate the process directly through the debugger rather than attempting to hook into a pre-existing PID.
With the command <command>sudo gdb --args ./my_program</command>, the debugger acts as the parent process, establishing a legitimate relationship that permits full debugging control even under restrictive YAMA settings.
  </para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
</topic>