<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<topic xml:id="cpu-check-temperature-troubleshoot"
 role="reference" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
   <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This part describes potential problems when monitoring CPU temperatures and their solutions.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="no-sensors-detected">
    <title>No sensors were detected</title>
    <para>
      On laptops, the <command>sensors-detect</command> command may provide the following output:
    </para>
<screen>
Sorry, no sensors were detected.
This is relatively common on laptops, where thermal management is
handled by ACPI rather than the OS.</screen>
    <para>
        This message is displayed when <command>sensors-detect</command> cannot find any hardware 
        sensors on your laptop because most laptops handle thermal management through ACPI 
        (Advanced Configuration and Power Interface), not the operating system.</para> 
    <note>
            <title>The <command>sensors</command> command</title>
            <para>
            Despite the message about the failure to detects sensors, the <command>sensors</command> 
            command may still work and provide expected results.</para>
    </note>                
    <para>You can check the CPU temperature using the tools that read from the ACPI interface.</para>
    <procedure xml:id="monitor-temp-acpi">
        <step>
         <para>
         Check if the <package>acpi</package> package is installed. This package provides an interface for the 
         hardware's embedded controller via ACPI, allowing you to check battery status, 
         thermal zone temperature, and more. To install, run the command:
        </para>
        <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>zypper install acpi</command></screen>
        </step>
        <step>
         <para>
         Check the CPU temperature directly from the <filename>/sys</filename> file system. 
         The CPU temperature is located in <filename>/sys/class/thermal/thermal_zone*/temp</filename>. 
         Below is an example of the command with its output:</para>
<screen>
&prompt.user;cat /sys/class/thermal/thermal_zone*/temp
41000</screen>
        <para>
        The temperature is displayed in milliCelsius. To get the temperature in Celsius, 
        divide the output by 1000 to get, in our example, 41°C.
        </para>
        </step>
       </procedure>
<para>For more information about ACPI, refer to
   <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/html/SLES-all/cha-power-mgmt.html#sec-power-mgmt-acpi"/>.</para>
   <note>
    <title>ACPI may not be available on mainframes</title>
    <para>
      Mainframes do not have the same power management needs as desktops, laptops and servers,
      and so they do not typically use ACPI. Instead, mainframes use different architectures
      and technologies for their configuration and management.
    </para>
</note> 
       </section>
      
<section xml:id="unrealistic-temperatures-shown">
    <title>The displayed temperatures are unrealistic</title>
    <para>
        If you suspect that the displayed temperature is too low or too high, you can try the following:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
         <para>Check whether the sensors are detected correctly: Rerun the <command>sensors-detect</command> 
          command to redetect the sensors.</para>
         <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>sensors-detect</command></screen>
         <para>Then, run the <command>sensors</command> command again to see if the temperature readings
          are more realistic.</para>
        </listitem>
<listitem>
<para>Check the raw thermal data in the <filename>/sys/class/thermal/</filename> directory. 
  See whether the raw data matches the output of the <command>sensors</command> command.</para>
  <screen>&prompt.user;cat /sys/class/thermal/thermal_zone*/temp</screen>
</listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>Use a different tool to read the CPU temperature, for example, Hardinfo, which is a system 
        profiler and benchmark tool. It can gather information about your system's hardware and operating 
        system, perform benchmarks, and generate printable reports. It can also show CPU temperature. 
        To install Hardinfo, use the following commands:</para>
        <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>zypper install hardinfo</command></screen>
    <para>Then, you can launch Hardinfo from the app menu.</para>
     </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
  <para>If none of these recommendations solves the issue, the problem might be due to unsupported or 
  faulty hardware. In this case, you need to seek help from your hardware manufacturer.</para>
</section>

<section xml:id="troubleshoot-wrong-temperature">
  <title>The displayed temperature is too high</title>
  <para>
    If the CPU temperature is too high, here are actions you can take:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>Verify that the CPU cooling system, such as the fan or heat sink, is working correctly.
        Ensure that the fan is spinning properly and that the heat sink is making proper contact with the CPU.
        If necessary, you may need to replace the thermal paste between the CPU and the heat sink to improve heat transfer.</para>
      </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>Adjust the power settings on your system to reduce heat generation. Lowering the CPU
        frequency or enabling power-saving features can help keep the temperature in check. 
        For more information about lowering CPU frequency, see
        <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sbp/all/single-html/SBP-performance-tuning/index.html#sec-cpupower-tool"/>.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>Monitor the system load and CPU usage. High CPU usage for extended periods can
    lead to increased temperatures. Identify any resource-intensive processes and consider optimizing
    or limiting their usage. For more information, refer to <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/kb/doc/?id=000016916"/>.</para>
    </listitem>      
    </itemizedlist>
</section>
</topic>
