<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="cpu-troubleshoot"
 role="reference" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
   <title>Troubleshooting</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This part describes potential problems when monitoring CPU temperatures and their solutions.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="no-sensors-detected">
    <title>No sensors were detected</title>
    <para>
      On laptops, the <command>sensors-detect</command> commands may provide the following output:
    </para>
    <screen>Sorry, no sensors were detected.
        This is relatively common on laptops, where thermal management is
        handled by ACPI rather than the OS.</screen>
    <para>
        This message is displayed when <command>sensors-detect</command> cannot find any hardware 
        sensors on your laptop because most laptops handle thermal management through ACPI 
        (Advanced Configuration and Power Interface), not the operating system.</para> 
    <note>
            <title>The <command>sensors</command> command</title>
            <para>
            Despite the message about the failure to detects sensors, the <command>sensors</command> 
            command may still work and provide expected results.</para>
    </note>                
    <para>However, you can still check the CPU temperature using the tools that read 
            from the ACPI interface.</para>
    <procedure xml:id="monitor-temp-acpi">
        <step>
         <para>
         Check if the <package>acpi</package> package is installed. This package provides an interface for the 
         hardware's embedded controller via ACPI, allowing you to check battery status, 
         thermal zone temperature, and more. To install, run the command:
        </para>
        <screen>&prompt.sudo;<command>zypper install acpi</command></screen>
        </step>
        <step>
         <para>
         Check the CPU temperature directly from the <filename>/sys</filename> file system. 
         The CPU temperature is located in <filename>/sys/class/thermal/thermal_zone*/temp</filename>. 
         For example:</para>
         <screen>cat /sys/class/thermal/thermal_zone*/temp</screen>
         <note>
        <title>Temperature units</title>
        <para>
        The temperature is displayed in milliCelsius, for example, 41000. To see the temperature in Celsius, 
        divide the output by 1000 to get, in our example, 41°C.
        </para>
        </note>
        </step>
       </procedure>
       </section>
      
<section xml:id="unrealistic-temperatures-shown">
    <title>The displayed temperatures are unrealistic</title>
    <para>
        what to do with the received information, i.e. if the temperature is too high???
        Maybe not all your sensors are properly supported (because) the temperatures shown are strange and why?
    </para>
</section>

</topic>
