<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="iscsi-terminology"
 role="reference" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>iSCSI terminology</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        The following lists essential terminology for the iSCSI LIO target server and the initiator client.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>ACL (Access Control List)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
  A security list on the Target that specifies which Initiator IQNs are allowed to connect. </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>backstore</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A physical storage object that provides the actual storage underlying an
       iSCSI endpoint. In LIO:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">iblocks:</emphasis>A raw block device like <filename>/dev/sdb</filename> .</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">fileio:</emphasis>A file on a regular filesystem used as a virtual disk.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">pscsi:</emphasis>Direct pass-through to a physical SCSI device.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>CDB (command descriptor block)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
 A CDB is the fundamental data structure used by the SCSI protocol to tell a storage device what to do. Since iSCSI is SCSI over IP, the iSCSI initiator wraps these CDBs inside TCP/IP packets to send them to the LIO Target.
CDBs are commonly 6, 10, or 12 bytes long, though they can be 16 bytes or of variable length.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>CHAP (challenge handshake authentication protocol)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A point-to-point protocol (PPP) authentication method used to confirm the
       identity of one computer to another. After the Link Control Protocol
       (LCP) connects the two computers, and the CHAP method is negotiated, the
       authenticator sends a random Challenge to the peer. The peer issues a
       cryptographically hashed Response that depends upon the Challenge and a
       secret key. The authenticator verifies the hashed Response against its
       own calculation of the expected hash value, and either acknowledges the
       authentication or terminates the connection. CHAP is defined in the RFC
       1994.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>CID (connection identifier)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A 16‐bit number, generated by the initiator, that uniquely identifies a
       connection between two iSCSI devices. This number is presented during the
       login phase.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Discovery</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
  The process where the Initiator queries a target portal to see what IQNs are available to it.  </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>endpoint</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The combination of an iSCSI Target Name with an iSCSI TPG (IQN + Tag).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>EUI (extended unique identifier)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A 64‐bit number that uniquely identifies every device in the world. The
       format consists of 24 bits that are unique to a given company, and 40
       bits assigned by the company to each device it builds.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>initiator</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The originating end of an SCSI session. Typically a controlling device
        such as a computer.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>IPS (Internet protocol storage)</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        The class of protocols or devices that use the IP protocol to move data
        in a storage network. FCIP (Fibre Channel over Internet Protocol), iFCP
        (Internet Fibre Channel Protocol), and iSCSI (Internet SCSI) are all
        examples of IPS protocols.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>IQN (iSCSI qualified name)</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        A name format for iSCSI that uniquely identifies every device in the
        world (for example:
        <filename>iqn.5886.com.acme.tapedrive.sn‐a12345678</filename>).
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>ISID (initiator session identifier)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          A 48‐bit number, generated by the initiator, that uniquely identifies a
          session between the initiator and the target. This value is created
          during the login process, and is sent to the target with a Login PDU.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Initiatorname</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The unique IQN assigned to the client. This must be registered in the Target's ACL for a connection to be successful.
           </para>
          </listitem>
         </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>MCS (multiple connections per session)</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          A part of the iSCSI specification that allows multiple TCP/IP connections
          between an initiator and a target.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Login</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The process of authenticating and establishing a session between the initiator and the target.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>MPIO (multipath I/O)</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          A method by which data can take multiple redundant paths between a server
          and storage.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>network portal</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The combination of an iSCSI endpoint with an IP address plus a TCP
          (Transmission Control Protocol) port. TCP port 3260 is the port number
          for the iSCSI protocol, as defined by IANA (Internet Assigned Numbers
          Authority).
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Node</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          In the context of initiator software like <literal>iscsiadm</literal>, a node represents a specific target that has been discovered and recorded in the local database. </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>SAM (SCSI architectural model)</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          A document that describes the behavior of SCSI in general terms, allowing
          for different types of devices communicating over various media.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>Session</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The active TCP connection or group of connections between an initiator and a target.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>target</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The receiving end of an SCSI session, typically a device such as a disk
          drive, tape drive, or scanner.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>targetcli</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          The shell-like interface used to configure LIO on Linux.
         </para>
        </listitem>
       </varlistentry>
       <varlistentry>
        <term>target group (TG)</term>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          A list of SCSI target ports that are all treated the same when creating
          views. Creating a view can help simplify LUN (logical unit number)
          mapping. Each view entry specifies a target group, host group, and a LUN.
         </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>target port</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         The combination of an iSCSI endpoint with one or more LUNs.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>target port group (TPG)</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A list of IP addresses and TCP port numbers that determines which
         interfaces a specific iSCSI target will listen to.
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>target session identifier (TSID)</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>
         A 16‐bit number, generated by the target, that uniquely identifies a
         session between the initiator and the target. This value is created
         during the login process, and is sent to the initiator with a Login
         Response PDU (protocol data units).
        </para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
</topic>