<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="manage-vm-on-commandline-tools"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Command-line tools</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>libvirt includes several command line utilities to manage virtual machines.</para></abstract>
  </info>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>virsh</literal> (Package: libvirt-client)</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>A command line tool to manage VM Guests with similar functionality as the Virtual Machine Manager. Allows you to change a VM Guest's status (start, stop, pause, etc.), to set up new guests and devices, or to edit existing configurations. virsh is also useful to script VM Guest management operations.</para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><literal>virt-install</literal> (Package: virt-install)</term>
    <listitem> <para>A command line tool for creating new VM Guests using the libvirt library. It supports graphical installations via VNC or SPICE protocols. Given suitable command line arguments, virt-install can run completely unattended. This allows for easy automation of guest installs. virt-install is the default installation tool used by the Virtual Machine Manager.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><literal>remote-viewer</literal> (Package: virt-viewer)</term><listitem><para>A simple viewer of a remote desktop. It supports SPICE and VNC protocols.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
    <varlistentry><term><literal>virt-clone</literal> (Package: virt-install)</term><listitem><para>A tool for cloning existing virtual machine images using the libvirt hypervisor management library.</para></listitem></varlistentry> 
    <varlistentry><term><literal>virt-host-validate</literal> (Package: libvirt-client)</term><listitem><para>A tool that validates whether the host is configured in a suitable way to run libvirt hypervisor drivers.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
     </topic>
