<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="terminal-signals-systemd"
 role="task" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Sending termination signals to &systemd; services</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com"/>
  </info>
    <para>
      Each service in &systemd; is categorized into a control group which makes it easy to identify
      all parent and child processes of a service. This enables you to send a signal to each of these processes.
      You can send a signal to a &systemd; service or to the individual processes that belong to a service.
    </para>

    <warning>
      <title>Do not cancel the D-Bus service in a running system</title>
      <para>The D-Bus service is the message bus for communication between &systemd; clients and the &systemd; manager that is running as PID 1.
       D-Bus is a stand-alone daemon and an integral part of the init infrastructure.</para>

     <para>
      Terminating or restarting the D-Bus service is neither recommended nor supported. This breaks the &systemd; client
      and server communication and makes most of the &systemd; functions unusable.</para>
          </warning>
          <para>The <command>systemd-cgls</command> command displays all processes that belong to a &systemd; service.
              It recursively shows the contents of the specific Linux control group hierarchy in a tree.
              </para>
            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term>Lists all control groups and their processes:</term>
                <listitem><screen>&prompt.user;systemd-cgls</screen></listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                <term>Displays all processes that belong to a particular service, for example,:
                  the <literal>libvirtd.service</literal> service:</term>
                <listitem><screen>&prompt.user;systemd-cgls -u libvirtd.service</screen></listitem>
                </varlistentry>
                <varlistentry>
                  <term>Sends a termination signal to the service.</term>
                  <listitem><screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl kill <replaceable>SERVICE</replaceable></screen></listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>By default the <command>kill</command> command sends the signal to
                      <option>all</option> processes of the specified control group.
                      You can restrict it to the <option>control</option> or the
                      <option>main</option> process.
                      The latter is, for example, useful to force a service to reload its
                      configuration by sending <systemitem>SIGHUP</systemitem>:</term>
                    <listitem><screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl kill -s SIGHUP --kill-who=main SERVICE_NAME</screen></listitem>
                    </varlistentry>
                    <varlistentry>
                      <term>Sends a different signal to a service with the <option>-s</option>
                        option, such as <systemitem>SIGKILL</systemitem> (9):</term>
                      <listitem><screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl kill -s 9 SERVICE_NAME</screen></listitem>
                      </varlistentry>
              </variablelist>
 </topic>