<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="systemd-coredump-configuration"
 role="reference" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Configuration of <literal>systemd-coredump</literal></title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para><literal>systemd-coredump</literal> provides a centralized, automated framework for capturing and managing process crashes by intercepting kernel signals to store compressed memory images and metadata, which are then easily analyzed through the <literal>coredumpctl</literal> utility.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para><literal>systemd-coredump</literal> is enabled by default. The primary configuration file is located at <filename>/etc/systemd/coredump.conf</filename>.</para>
<screen>[Coredump]
#Storage=external
#Compress=yes
#ProcessSizeMax=2G
#ExternalSizeMax=2G
#JournalSizeMax=767M
#MaxUse=
#KeepFree=</screen>
<para>The following parameters in <filename>[Coredump]</filename> define how dumps are handled:</para>
<variablelist><varlistentry>
  <term>Storage</term>
  <listitem><para>Defines where to store dumps such as <literal>none</literal>, <literal>external</literal>, <literal>journal</literal>. The default is <literal>external</literal>.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Compress</term>
  <listitem><para>Enables/disables compression for the stored core dump. By default, this is enabled.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>ProcessSizeMax</term>
<listitem><para>The maximum size of a core dump to be processed. The default size is <literal>2G</literal></para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>ExternalSizeMax</term><listitem><para>The maximum size for a dump stored on disk. The default size is <literal>2G</literal></para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>JournalSizeMax</term><listitem><para>The maximum size of core dumps that can be stored directly within the system journal (when Storage=journal is used). If a core dump exceeds this value, it will be ignored or handled according to other storage settings.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>MaxUse</term><listitem><para>The maximum amount of disk space the coredump storage (typically /var/lib/systemd/coredump/) is allowed to occupy. Once this limit is reached, older core dumps are automatically deleted to make room for new ones.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>KeepFree</term><listitem><para>The minimum amount of free disk space that must be maintained on the filesystem where core dumps are stored. <literal>systemd-coredump</literal> will stop saving new dumps if doing so would cause the available disk space to fall below this threshold.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
<para>Size units are <literal>B</literal>, <literal>K</literal>, <literal>M</literal>, <literal>G</literal>, <literal>T</literal>, <literal>P</literal>, and <literal>E</literal>. The <literal>ExternalSizeMax</literal> also supports a value of infinity. </para>
<note><para>A new instance of <literal>systemd-coredump</literal> is invoked for every crash. Configuration changes are applied immediately to the next crash; you do not need to restart any services.</para></note>
<section><title>Managing Core Dump Storage</title>
    <para>To minimize the storage of sensitive information, you can disable disk storage and log only to the journal by modifying <filename>/etc/systemd/coredump.conf</filename>. In systemd configuration, if a field is explicitly set to nothing or if the feature is disabled via none, the system defaults to <literal>external</literal>, logging only the basic event details to systemd-journald. You can control this behavior in <filename>/etc/systemd/coredump.conf</filename> with the Storage option:</para>
    <itemizedlist><listitem><para><literal>Storage=none</literal> Dumps are logged in the journal but the memory image is not saved to disk.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><literal>Storage=journal</literal> Cores are stored directly within the systemd journal.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<para>Depending on the storage configuration, core dumps may not be preserved after a system restart (for example, if stored in volatile journal memory or a temporary directory). To ensure a core dump is saved to a permanent file for later analysis:</para>
<screen>coredumpctl -o my_app.dump dump &gt;PID&lt;</screen>
<para>For more information, see <code>man systemd-coredump, man coredumpctl, man core, and man coredump.conf</code> for complete command and option listing.</para>
</section>
</topic>