<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="virtualization-scenarios"
 role="reference" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Virtualization scenarios</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Virtualization is a technology that provides a way for a machine (&vmhost;) to run another
        operating system (&vmguest;) on top of the host operating system. Virtualization can
        provide the following capabilities:
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Server consolidation</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Many servers can be replaced by one physical server, so that hardware is consolidated,
          and guest operating systems are converted to virtual machines. This also supports running
          legacy software on new hardware.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Better use of not fully utilized resources.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Fewer server locations needed.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              More efficient use of computer resources with multiple workloads on the same server.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Simplifies data center infrastructure.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Simplifies moving workloads to other hosts, avoiding service downtime.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Faster and more agile virtual machine provisioning.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Multiple guest operating systems can run on a single host.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Isolation</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Guest operating systems are fully isolated from the host running them. Therefore, if
          there are problems inside virtual machines, the host is not harmed. Also, problems inside
          one VM do not affect other VMs. No data is shared between VMs.
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Secure Boot can be used for VMs.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              KSM should be avoided.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Individual CPU cores can be assigned to VMs.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Hyper-threading (HT) should be disabled to avoid potential security issues.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              VMs should not share networks, storage, or network hardware.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Using advanced hypervisor features, such as PCI pass-through or NUMA, adversely
              affects VM migration capabilities.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Using paravirtualization and <literal>virtio</literal> drivers generally improves VM
              performance and efficiency.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>
          AMD provides specific features regarding the security of virtualization.
<!-- link to the SEV doc? -->
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Disaster recovery</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          The hypervisor can make snapshots of VMs, enabling restoration to a known good state, or
          to any desired earlier state. Since virtualized operating systems are less dependent on
          hardware configuration than those running directly on bare metal, these snapshots can be
          restored onto different server hardware so long as it is running the same hypervisor.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term>Dynamic load balancing</term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Live migration can be used to load balance your services across your infrastructure by
          moving VMs from busy hosts to those with spare capacity, on demand.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
</topic>
