<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xml:id="concept-bci-variants" xml:lang="en"
 role="concept"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>BCI-Base, BCI-Minimal, BCI-Micro, and BCI-BusyBox</title>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
    <dm:component>Smart Docs</dm:component>
    <dm:product>Documentation</dm:product>
    <dm:assignee>assignee@suse.com</dm:assignee>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <section xml:id="environment-bci-variants">
  <title>Environment</title>
  <para>
   This document applies to the following products and product versions:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &sles;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP4
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="decision-card-bci">
  <title>Decision card</title>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>WHAT</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      An overview of differences between BCI-Base, BCI-Minimal, BCI-Micro, and
      BCI-BusyBox.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>WHY</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Because you'd want to use the right &bci; for the project at hand.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>WHERE</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <link xlink:href="https://registry.suse.com/">registry.suse.com</link>
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>EFFORT</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      It only takes 10 minutes of reading time.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>GOAL</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Understand the differences and pick the right &bci; for your projects.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="bci-variants-intro">
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
   &suse; offers several general-purpose &bci;s that are intended as deployment
   targets or as foundations for creating customized images: BCI-Base,
   BCI-Minimal, BCI-Micro, and BCI-BusyBox. These images share the common
   &slsa; base, and none of them ship with a specific language or an
   application stack. All images feature the RPM database (even if the specific
   image does not include the RPM package manager) that can be used to verify
   the provenance of every file in the image. Each image includes the &slsa;
   certificate bundle, which allows the deployed applications to use the
   system's certificates to verify TLS connections.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="bci-variants-table">
  <title>Quick overview</title>
  <para>
   The table below provides a quick overview of the differences between
   BCI-Base, BCI-Minimal, BCI-Micro, and BCI-BusyBox.
  </para>
  <informalfigure>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="fo">
     <imagedata fileref="bci-variants.png" width="80%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
     <imagedata fileref="bci-variants.png" width="100%"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </informalfigure>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="bci-variants-base">
  <title>BCI-Base: When you need flexibility</title>
  <para>
   This &bci; comes with the &zypper; package manager and a free SLE-BCI
   repository. This allows you to install software available in the repository
   and customize the image during the build. The downside is the size of the
   image. It is the largest of the general-purpose &bci;s, so it is not always
   the best choice for a deployment image.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="bci-variants-minimal">
  <title>BCI-Minimal: When you do not need &zypper;</title>
  <para>
   This is a stripped-down version of the BCI-Base image. BCI-Minimal comes
   without &zypper;, but it does have the RPM package
   manager installed. This significantly reduces the size of the image.
   However, while RPM can install and remove packages,
   it lacks support for repositories and automated dependency resolution. The
   BCI-Minimal image is therefore intended for creating deployment containers,
   and then installing the desired RPM packages inside the containers. Although
   you can install the required dependencies, you need to download and resolve
   them manually. However, this approach is not recommended as it is prone to
   errors.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="bci-variants-micro">
  <title>BCI-Micro: When you need to deploy static binaries</title>
  <para>
   This image is similar to BCI-Minimal but without the
   RPM package manager. The primary use case for the
   image is deploying static binaries produced externally or during multi-stage
   builds. As there is no straightforward way to install additional
   dependencies inside the container image, we recommend deploying a project
   using the BCI-Minimal image only when the final build artifact bundles all
   dependencies and has no external runtime requirements (like Python or Ruby).
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="bci-variants-busybox">
  <title>BCI-BusyBox: When you need the smallest and GPLv3-free image</title>
  <para>
   Similar to BCI-Micro, the BCI-BusyBox image comes with the most basic tools
   only. However, these tools are provided by the BusyBox project. This has the
   benefit of further size reduction. Furthermore, the image contains no GPLv3
   licensed software. When using the image, keep in mind that there are certain
   differences between the BusyBox tools and the GNU Coreutils. So scripts
   written for a system that uses GNU Coreutils may require modification to
   work with BusyBox.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section xml:id="bci-variants-size">
  <title>Approximate sizes</title>
  <para>
   For your reference, the list below provides an approximate size of each
   &bci;. Keep in mind that the provided numbers are rough estimations.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>BCI-Base</literal> ~94MB
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>BCI-Minimal</literal> ~42MB
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>BCI-Micro</literal> ~26MB
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <literal>BCI-BusyBox</literal> ~14MB
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</article>
