<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xml:id="concept-time-synchronization-ntp" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>Synchronizing time with NTP</title>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
    <dm:component>Documentation</dm:component>
    <dm:product>Product Name</dm:product>
    <dm:assignee>assignee@suse.com</dm:assignee>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>
 <section>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para>
   Maintaining an exact and synchronized time in an operating system is
   important. For example, planning and calendaring applications rely on it to
   track time correctly and notify users about appointments on time. For
   clustered applications, individual host machines often require synchronized
   system time for mutual communication.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Implementation</title>
  <para>
   The built-in hardware clock is not a reliable time source and manual
   correction of the system time may cause malfunction of critical
   applications. That is why the Network Time Protocol (NTP) is designed to
   synchronize the system time over the network. Its goal is to maintain the
   absolute time, and use it to synchronize the system time of all machines
   within a network.
  </para>
  <para>
   Since &sls; 15, &chrony; is the default implementation of NTP. &chrony;
   includes two parts; &chronyd; is a daemon that can be started at boot time
   and &chronyc; is a command line interface program to monitor the performance
   of &chronyd;, and to change various operating parameters at runtime.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>How it works</title>
  <para>
   Depending on its configuration, &chronyd; can maintain the exact time on a
   single machine, or additionally act as a time server for other machines
   within a network.
  </para>
  <section xml:id="maintain-exact-time">
   <title>Maintaining the exact system time on a machine</title>
   <para>
    This case is very common on desktop computers where you only need to keep
    the system time exact. The NTP service continuously queries and adjusts the
    system time with reliable time servers in the network.
   </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="provide-exact-time">
   <title>Providing the exact time to multiple machines</title>
   <para>
    If you need to maintain the exact system time on multiple machines within a
    network, we recommend configuring at least one of the machines as a local
    time server. The local time server will maintain the exact time from a
    reliable (external) time server and provide the time information at the
    same time so that other machines can synchronize with it.
   </para>
   <para>
    This approach is better than letting all the machines within a network
    synchronize their system time with an external time server. It saves the
    network bandwidth and allows for more secure setup where time server
    clients do not have access to the external network.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Benefits</title>
  <para>
   A paragraph of text.
  </para>
 </section>
 <section>
  <title>Related topics</title>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     An
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Unordered
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     List
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</article>
