<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<article xml:id="concept-systemd" xml:lang="en"
 role="concept"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

 <info>
   <title>Basic &systemd; concepts</title>
   <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
    <dm:bugtracker>
     <dm:url>https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
     <dm:component>Smart Docs</dm:component>
     <dm:product>Documentation</dm:product>
     <dm:assignee>carla.schroder@suse.com</dm:assignee>
    </dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
   </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

 <section xml:id="environment-concept-systemd">
  <title>Environment</title>
  <para>This document applies to the following products and product versions:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>&sles;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP5,15&nbsp;SP4, 15&nbsp;SP3, 15&nbsp;SP2, 15&nbsp;SP1, 15&nbsp;GA, 12&nbsp;SP5, 12&nbsp;SP4, 12&nbsp;SP3</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>&sles4sap;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP5,15&nbsp;SP4, 15&nbsp;SP3, 15&nbsp;SP2, 15&nbsp;SP1, 15&nbsp;GA, 12&nbsp;SP5, 12&nbsp;SP4, 12&nbsp;SP3</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>&sleha;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP5,15&nbsp;SP4, 15&nbsp;SP3, 15&nbsp;SP2, 15&nbsp;SP1, 15&nbsp;GA, 12&nbsp;SP5, 12&nbsp;SP4, 12&nbsp;SP3</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>&slehpc;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP5,15&nbsp;SP4, 15&nbsp;SP3, 15&nbsp;SP2, 15&nbsp;SP1, 15&nbsp;GA</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>&sled;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP5,15&nbsp;SP4, 15&nbsp;SP3, 15&nbsp;SP2, 15&nbsp;SP1, 15&nbsp;GA, 12&nbsp;SP5, 12&nbsp;SP4, 12&nbsp;SP3</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>&slert;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP5,15&nbsp;SP4, 15&nbsp;SP3, 15&nbsp;SP2, 15&nbsp;SP1, 15&nbsp;GA, 12&nbsp;SP5, 12&nbsp;SP4, 12&nbsp;SP3</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="what-is-systemd">
  <title>What is &systemd;?</title>
  <para>
   &systemd; is the modern replacement for the legacy Linux initialization
   systems, System V (SysV) and Linux Standard Base init (LSB init).
   &systemd; owns PID 1, and is started directly by the kernel. All other
   processes are either started directly by &systemd;, or by one of its child
   processes. &systemd; is designed to manage the complex demands of modern
   Linux systems, by dynamically managing all processes from system boot to
   shutdown.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="how-it-works-systemd">
  <title>How does &systemd; work?</title>
  <para>
   &systemd; uses unit files to control related processes. A unit
   configuration file contains all the elements necessary to operate a
   service: a listening socket, device, mount point, automount point, swap
   file or partition, startup target, watched file system path, timers,
   temporary system state snapshot, resource management slice, or a group of
   externally created processes. This simplifies system administration, as
   &systemd; tracks and manages all the elements necessary for a particular
   service, and the administrator has only a single service unit file to
   manage for any service.
  </para>
  <para>
    Unit files are customizable, and simpler and easier to understand
    than SysV and LSB init scripts.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="benefits-systemd">
  <title>Benefits of &systemd;</title>
  <para>
   &systemd; provides a number of benefits. It is a single daemon
   that performs complete process management, from startup to shutdown.
   It speeds up boot times by parallelizing service starts. It conserves
   system resources by starting services on demand, and puts them to sleep
   when there is no demand. &systemd; reduces complexity and
   increases efficiency by opening listening sockets, which are then
   available when services start, and the administrator does not have to
   worry about starting them in the correct order.
  </para>
  <para>
   In contrast, SysV and LSB init only start services at boot, then exit.
   The SysV and LSB init administrator must configure services
   carefully to start in the correct order, for example networking must start
   before network services, and the administrator must remember to configure
   all necessary services to start at boot.
  </para>
  <para>
    &systemd; is written in C, in contrast to the large assortment of shell
    scripts that comprise SysV and LSB init. The compiled single &systemd;
    binary is faster and more efficient than masses of scripts.
  </para>
  <para>
    &systemd; provides unified logging for all processes with the
    &systemd; journal, which is viewed with the <command>journalctl</command>
    command.
  </para>
  <para>
    &systemd; organizes processes with Kernel Control Groups (cgroups).
    cgroups are inbuilt in the Linux kernel. This provides an extremely
    efficient way to organize all related processes for a service, and to
    quickly find which process belongs to which service.
    cgroups also provide resource management, such as CPU, memory, I/O, and
    device groups.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <command>systemctl</command> command is the &systemd; and service
    manager.
  </para>
  <para>
    <command>journalctl</command> and <command>systemctl</command> replace a
    host of legacy commands and scripts.
  </para>
  <para>
    &systemd; is backwards-compatible with SysV and LSB init.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="related-systemd">
  <title>Related topics</title>
  <para>
    Because &systemd; is a complete process manager, from startup to
    shutdown, it controls all operations on a Linux system. Consult the
    following resources to learn more.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      freedesktop is the home of &systemd;:
      <link xlink:href="https://www.freedesktop.org/wiki/Software/systemd/"/>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
      Run <command>man -k systemd</command> to see all man pages for
      &systemd;. The following man pages are the most relevant for daily
      administration tasks:
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <command>man 1 systemd</command>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <command>man 1 systemctl</command>
    </para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <command>man 1 journalctl</command>
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</article>
