<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->

<topic xml:id="software-raids"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
<info>
 <title>Software RAIDs</title>
 <abstract>
 </abstract>
</info>

  <para>
  The purpose of RAID (redundant array of independent disks) is to combine
  several hard disk partitions into one large virtual hard disk to optimize
  performance, data security, or both. Most RAID controllers use the SCSI
  protocol, because it can address a larger number of hard disks in a more
  effective way than the IDE protocol and is more suitable for parallel
  processing of commands. There are some RAID controllers that support IDE or
  SATA hard disks. 
 </para>

 

 <section xml:id="software-raid-levels">
  <title>RAID levels</title>
  <para>
   This section describes common RAID levels and also nested RAID
   levels.
  </para>


  <section xml:id="software-raid-levels-0">
    <title>RAID&nbsp;0</title>
    <para>
           RAID&nbsp;0 has the data split evenly to two or more disks. Such a solution
           provides higher performance because you can read data from several
           disks simultaneously, but does not provide any fault tolerance. You
           need to have at least two disks.
        </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="software-raid-levels-1">
    <title>RAID&nbsp;1</title>
    <para>
    This level provides adequate security for your data, because the data is
    copied to another hard disk 1:1. This is known as <emphasis>hard disk
    mirroring</emphasis>. If a disk is destroyed, a copy of its contents is
    available on another mirrored disk. All disks except one could be damaged
    without endangering your data. However, if damage is not detected, damaged
    data might be mirrored to the correct disk and the data is corrupted that
    way. The writing performance suffers a little in the copying process
    compared to when using single disk access, but
    read access is significantly faster in comparison to a single
    physical hard disks, because the data is duplicated so can be scanned in
    parallel. RAID 1 generally provides nearly twice the read transaction rate
    of single disks and almost the same write transaction rate as single disks.
   </para>
   <para>
    This RAID level requires at least two disks.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="software-raid-levels-4">
    <title>RAID&nbsp;4</title>
    <para>
    Level&nbsp;4 provides block-level striping like Level&nbsp;0 combined with
    a dedicated parity disk. If a data disk fails, the parity data is used to
    create a replacement disk. However, the parity disk might create a
    bottleneck for write access. 
   </para>
   <para>
    You need to have
           at least 3 disks.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="software-raid-levels-5">
   <title>RAID&nbsp;5</title>
   <para>
    RAID&nbsp;5 is an optimized compromise between Level&nbsp;0 and
    Level&nbsp;1 in terms of performance and redundancy. The hard disk space
    equals the number of disks used minus one. The data is distributed over the
    hard disks as with RAID&nbsp;0. <emphasis>Parity blocks</emphasis>, created
    on one of the partitions, are there for security reasons. They are linked
    to each other with XOR, enabling the contents to be reconstructed by the
    corresponding parity block in case of system failure. With RAID&nbsp;5, no
    more than one hard disk can fail at the same time. If one hard disk fails,
    it must be replaced when possible to avoid the risk of losing data.
   </para>
   <para>
    The minimum number of disks is 3.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="software-raid-levels-6">
   <title>RAID&nbsp;6</title>
   <para>
    RAID&nbsp;6 is an extension of RAID&nbsp;5 that allows for additional fault
    tolerance by using a second independent distributed parity scheme (dual
    parity). Even if two of the hard disks fail during the data recovery
    process, the system continues to be operational, with no data loss.
   </para>
   <para>
    RAID&nbsp;6 provides for extremely high data fault tolerance by sustaining
    multiple simultaneous drive failures. It handles the loss of any two
    devices without data loss. Accordingly, it requires N+2 drives to store N
    drives worth of data. It requires a minimum of four devices.
   </para>
   <para>
    The performance for RAID&nbsp;6 is slightly lower but comparable to
    RAID&nbsp;5 in normal mode and single disk failure mode. It is very slow in
    dual disk failure mode. A RAID&nbsp;6 configuration needs a considerable
    amount of CPU time and memory for write operations.
   </para>
   <para>
    The minimum number of disks is 4.
   </para>
 </section>
 </section>
</topic>
