<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<?xml-stylesheet href="urn:x-suse:xslt:profiling:docbook51-profile.xsl"
 type="text/xml"
 title="Profiling step"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<article xml:id="concept-basic-networking" xml:lang="en"
 role="concept"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.1"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
 <info>
  <title>Basic networking concept</title>
  <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager">
   <dm:bugtracker>
    <dm:url>https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
    <dm:component>Smart Docs</dm:component>
    <dm:product>Documentation</dm:product>
    <dm:assignee>jhalackova@suse.com</dm:assignee>
   </dm:bugtracker>
   <dm:translation>no</dm:translation>
  </dm:docmanager>
 </info>

<section xml:id="environment-networking">
  <!--to create unique section IDs, amend the TOPIC-ID (without prefix)-->
  <!--example: environment-time-synchronization-ntp-->
  <title>Environment</title>
  <para>
   This document applies to the following products and product versions:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     &sles;&nbsp;15&nbsp;SP3, 15&nbsp;SP2, 15&nbsp;SP1, 15&nbsp;GA,
     12&nbsp;SP5, 12&nbsp;SP4, 12&nbsp;SP3
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="networking-in-linux">
  <title>Networking in Linux</title>
  <para>
  Linux and other Unix operating systems use the TCP/IP protocol. It is not a
  single network protocol, but a family of network protocols that offer various
  services. The protocols listed in <xref linkend="tab-net-basic-tcpproto"/>,
  are provided for exchanging data between two machines via TCP/IP. Networks
  combined by TCP/IP, comprising a worldwide network, are also called
  <quote>the Internet.</quote>
 </para>
 <para>
  RFC stands for <emphasis>Request for Comments</emphasis>. RFCs are documents
  that describe various Internet protocols and implementation procedures for
  the operating system and its applications. The RFC documents describe the
  setup of Internet protocols. For more information about RFCs, see
  <link xlink:href="https://datatracker.ietf.org/"/>.
 </para>
 <variablelist xml:id="tab-net-basic-tcpproto">
  <title>Several Protocols in the TCP/IP Protocol Family</title>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>TCP</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Transmission Control Protocol: a connection-oriented secure protocol. The
     data to transmit is first sent by the application as a stream of data and
     converted into the appropriate format by the operating system. The data
     arrives at the respective application on the destination host in the
     original data stream format it was initially sent. TCP determines whether
     any data has been lost or jumbled during the transmission. TCP is
     implemented wherever the data sequence matters.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>UDP</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     User Datagram Protocol: a connectionless, insecure protocol. The data to
     transmit is sent in the form of packets generated by the application. The
     order in which the data arrives at the recipient is not guaranteed and
     data loss is possible. UDP is suitable for record-oriented applications.
     It features a smaller latency period than TCP.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>ICMP</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Internet Control Message Protocol: This is not a protocol for
     the end user, but a special control protocol that issues error reports and
     can control the behavior of machines participating in TCP/IP data
     transfer. In addition, it provides a special echo mode that can be viewed
     using the program ping.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
  <varlistentry>
   <term>IGMP</term>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Internet Group Management Protocol: This protocol controls machine
     behavior when implementing IP multicast.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </varlistentry>
 </variablelist>
 <para>
  As shown in <xref linkend="fig-net-basic-OSI"/>, data exchange takes place in
  different layers. The actual network layer is the insecure data transfer via
  IP (Internet protocol). On top of IP, TCP (transmission control protocol)
  guarantees, to a certain extent, security of the data transfer. The IP layer
  is supported by the underlying hardware-dependent protocol, such as Ethernet.
 </para>
 <figure xml:id="fig-net-basic-OSI">
  <title>Simplified Layer Model for TCP/IP</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata width="100%" fileref="net_basic_osi.svg" format="SVG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata width="75%" fileref="net_basic_osi.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  The diagram provides one or two examples for each layer. The layers are
  ordered according to <emphasis>abstraction levels</emphasis>. The lowest
  layer is very close to the hardware. The uppermost layer, however, is almost
  a complete abstraction from the hardware. Every layer has its own special
  function. The special functions of each layer are mostly implicit in their
  description. The data link and physical layers represent the physical network
  used, such as Ethernet.
 </para>
 <para>
  Almost all hardware protocols work on a packet-oriented basis. The data to
  transmit is collected into <emphasis>packets</emphasis> (it cannot be sent
  all at once). The maximum size of a TCP/IP packet is approximately 64 KB.
  Packets are normally quite smaller, as the network hardware can be a limiting
  factor. The maximum size of a data packet on an Ethernet is about fifteen
  hundred bytes. The size of a TCP/IP packet is limited to this amount when the
  data is sent over an Ethernet. If more data is transferred, more data packets
  need to be sent by the operating system.
 </para>
 <para>
  For the layers to serve their designated functions, additional information
  regarding each layer must be saved in the data packet. This takes place in
  the <emphasis>header</emphasis> of the packet. Every layer attaches a small
  block of data, called the protocol header, to the front of each emerging
  packet. A sample TCP/IP data packet traveling over an Ethernet cable is
  illustrated in <xref linkend="fig-net-basic-TCPPaket"/>. The proof sum is
  located at the end of the packet, not at the beginning. This simplifies
  things for the network hardware.
 </para>
 <figure xml:id="fig-net-basic-TCPPaket">
  <title>TCP/IP Ethernet Packet</title>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject role="fo">
    <imagedata width="80%" fileref="net_basic_tcppacket.svg" format="SVG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <imageobject role="html">
    <imagedata width="75%" fileref="net_basic_tcppacket.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>
 <para>
  When an application sends data over the network, the data passes through each
  layer, all implemented in the Linux kernel except the physical layer. Each
  layer is responsible for preparing the data so it can be passed to the next
  layer. The lowest layer is ultimately responsible for sending the data. The
  entire procedure is reversed when data is received. Like the layers of an
  onion, in each layer the protocol headers are removed from the transported
  data. Finally, the transport layer is responsible for making the data
  available for use by the applications at the destination. In this manner, one
  layer only communicates with the layer directly above or below it. For
  applications, it is irrelevant whether data is transmitted via a 100 Mbit/s
  FDDI network or via a 56-Kbit/s modem line. Likewise, it is irrelevant for
  the data line which kind of data is transmitted, as long as packets are in
  the correct format.
 </para>
 </section>


 <section xml:id="related-basic-networking">
  <title>Related topics</title>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        IPv4 networking
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        IPv6 networking
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
</section>

</article>