<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2" xml:id="snapper-basic-concepts" xml:lang="en">
  <info>
      <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its">The Basic Concepts of Snapper</title>

      
      <revhistory xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xml:id="rh-snapper-basic-concepts">
        <revision><date>2025-11-04</date>
          <revdescription>
            <para>
             Initial version
            </para>
          </revdescription>
        </revision>
        </revhistory>
       
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>

      
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="architecture" its:translate="no">
        <phrase>AMD64/Intel&#xA0;64</phrase>
        <phrase>AArch64</phrase>
        <phrase>POWER</phrase>
        <phrase>IBM&#xA0;Z</phrase>
      </meta>

      
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="productname" its:translate="no">
        
        <productname version="6.2" os="slmicro"><phrase><phrase os="slmicro">SUSE Linux Micro</phrase></phrase></productname>        
      </meta>

      
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="title" its:translate="yes">The Basic Concepts of Snapper</meta>
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="description" its:translate="yes">A basic overview of Snapper: interfaces, default settings</meta>

      
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Snapper basic overview: interfaces, default settings</meta>
      
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="task" its:translate="no">
        <phrase>Backup &amp; Recovery</phrase>
        <phrase>Administration</phrase>
      </meta>

      
      <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="series" its:translate="no">Products &amp; Solutions</meta>

      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          <dm:url>https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
          <dm:component>Documentation</dm:component>          
          <dm:product os="slmicro">SUSE Linux Micro 6.2</dm:product>
                    
          <dm:assignee>daria.vladykina@suse.com</dm:assignee>
        </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>
      <abstract xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its">
      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>WHAT?</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This article describes the basic concepts of the Snapper
              tool that is used to create and manage Btrfs file system snapshots.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>WHY?</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              This article provides a basic overview of Snapper,
              its supported interfaces and main purposes. It also informs about
              default settings for snapshots on <phrase><phrase os="slmicro">SUSE Linux Micro</phrase></phrase>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>EFFORT</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
              It takes up to 20 minutes to understand Snapper and its default setup.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>REQUIREMENTS</term>
            <listitem>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    <systemitem class="username">root</systemitem> or <command>sudo</command> privileges
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    Snapper needs to be installed. It is available on <phrase><phrase os="slmicro">SUSE Linux Micro</phrase></phrase> by default.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    A root partition (<filename>/</filename>) size of at least 16&#xA0;GB. The size
                    of the root partition depends on the product. We strongly recommend 50&#xA0;GB or more.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
        <note>
          <para>This article is the first installment of the series of articles
            about Snapper. In the subsequent articles, we cover common use cases such
            as undoing changes, rolling back the system, manually creating and managing
            snapshots, automatic snapshot cleanup, and more. Each article builds upon the
            knowledge gained from the previous ones, providing a progressively
            enhanced understanding of the Snapper tool.</para>
        </note>
      </abstract>
    </info>
  <section role="concept" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="snapper-about-snapshots"><info>
    <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">Essential concepts of Btrfs subvolumes and snapshots</title>
    
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
  </info>
  
  <para>Btrfs subvolumes are separately mountable file systems within a physical 
    partition. The Btrfs file system is set up with subvolumes by default. 
    Snapshots in Btrfs are a type of subvolume that shares data with another 
    subvolume. They are created using the copy-on-write capabilities of Btrfs, 
    which allows them to be quickly created with minimal disk space usage. 
    Snapshots can be used to capture the state of a file system at a particular 
    point in time and to roll back to a previous state if needed.   
  </para>
  <para>A Btrfs subvolume has its own independent file and directory hierarchy.
    Unlike LVM logical volumes, which operate at the block level, Btrfs 
    subvolumes are file extent-based. A snapshot is also considered a subvolume,
    carrying the initial content of the original subvolume. Subvolumes appear 
    as directories and can be manipulated like any other directory, including 
    being renamed or moved.</para>
  <para>
    One of the primary purposes of subvolumes is to be explicitly included or 
    excluded from snapshots. When using a snapshot to roll back the system, we 
    need to ensure that data such as users' home directories, Web and FTP 
    server contents or log files do not get lost or overwritten during a rollback. 
    This is achieved by excluding certain Btrfs subvolumes from snapshots. 
    Find more information and the list of excluded subvolumes in 
    <xref linkend="snapper-subvolumes"/>.
  </para>
</section>
  <section role="concept" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="snapper-basic-concept"><info>
  <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">What is Snapper?</title>    
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
  </info>
  
  <para>Snapper is a tool that helps create and manage file system snapshots.
    File system snapshots allow keeping a copy of the state of a file system
    at a certain point of time. Snapper can create and compare snapshots, revert
    between snapshots, and supports automatic snapshot timelines. Snapper never
    modifies the content of snapshots.</para>
    <para>The standard setup of Snapper is designed to allow rolling back system
    changes. However, you can also use it to create on-disk backups of user data.
    As the basis for this functionality, Snapper uses two types of file systems:</para>
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Btrfs, a copy-on-write file system for Linux that natively supports
        file system snapshots of subvolumes.
       </para>
       </listitem>
      <listitem>
       <para>
        Thinly provisioned LVM volumes formatted with XFS and ext4.
       </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <note>
      <para>
        You can also boot from <literal>Btrfs</literal> snapshots. 
       </para>
      </note>

  <section xml:id="snapper-basic-tasks">
    <title>What can Snapper do?</title>
    <para>Snapper has a command-line interface that allows you to create,
     delete and compare snapshots, as well as undo changes made between snapshots.</para>
    <para>
      Using Snapper, you can perform the following tasks:</para>
      <itemizedlist mark="bullet" spacing="normal">
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Undo system changes made by <command>zypper</command>. 
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Restore files from previous snapshots. 
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Do a system rollback by booting from a snapshot. 
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
         <para>
          Manually create and manage snapshots, within the running system. 
         </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          Perform automatic snapshot cleanup.  
          </para>
         </listitem>
       </itemizedlist>   
</section>



<section xml:id="snapper-snapshot-creation"> 
  <title>Snapshot creation</title>
   <para>
   When a snapshot is created, both the snapshot and the original point to the
   same blocks in the file system. So, initially a snapshot does not occupy
   additional disk space. If data in the original file system is modified,
   changed data blocks are copied while the old data blocks are kept for the
   snapshot. Therefore, a snapshot occupies the same amount of space as the
   data modified. So, over time, the amount of space a snapshot allocates
   constantly grows. As a consequence, deleting files from a
   <literal>Btrfs</literal> file system containing snapshots may
   <emphasis>not</emphasis> free disk space!</para>
   <note>
     <title>Snapshot location</title>
     <para>
      Snapshots always reside on the same partition or subvolume on which the
      snapshot has been taken. It is not possible to store snapshots on a
      different file system.
     </para>
    </note>
    <para>
     As a result, partitions containing snapshots need to be larger than
     partitions not containing snapshots. The exact amount depends strongly on the
     number of snapshots you keep and the amount of data modifications. As a rule
     of thumb, give partitions twice as much space as you normally would.
     To prevent disks from running out of space, old snapshots are automatically
     cleaned up.
    </para>  
 </section>
</section>
  <section role="concept" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="snapper-default-setup"><info>
  <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">Snapper default setup</title>    
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
       <para>
        Learn about the default setup of Snapper and its default settings.
       </para>
     </abstract>
  </info>
 
  <para>Snapper is set up as an undo and recovery tool for system
    changes. By default, the root partition (<filename>/</filename>) of 
    <phrase><phrase os="slmicro">SUSE Linux Micro</phrase></phrase> is formatted with <literal>Btrfs</literal>. Taking snapshots
    is automatically enabled if the root partition (<filename>/</filename>) 
    is big enough (more than approximately 16&#xA0;GB). 
    By default, snapshots are disabled on partitions other than <filename>/</filename>.</para>
    <important>
      <para>We do not recommend activating snapshots manually after the system 
        has been installed with snapshots. Enabling Snapper after the installation 
        results in a different setup compared to what is described here.</para>
    </important>
<tip>
  <title>Checking root partition size</title>
  <para>The size of the root partition is product-specific. To find out the disk 
    space that the root partition occupies, run:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>df -h</command></screen>
</tip>

    <section xml:id="snapper-default-settings">
    <title>Snapper default settings</title>
      
 
 <para>Snapshots are created for the root partition only, and certain 
  directories are excluded by means of subvolumes. For the list of excluded subvolumes, 
  see <xref linkend="snapper-subvolumes"/>.</para>
 <para>Snapper provides automatic snapshot cleanup algorithms to prevent running 
        out of space on the root partition. These algorithms differentiate 
        between timeline snapshots and <emphasis>numbered</emphasis> snapshots 
        (administration plus installation snapshot pairs). The cleanup behavior can 
        be configured based on the following criteria:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Number limit: The system can be set to automatically delete old snapshots 
        when a certain count of snapshots is reached.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Age limit: Old snapshots can be deleted if they exceed a certain age, while 
        still preserving a number of snapshots for each time period (hourly, daily, monthly, yearly).</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><literal>Pre</literal> and <literal>post</literal> snapshot pairs: 
          <literal>pre</literal> and <literal>post</literal> snapshot pairs that do not 
          differ can be automatically deleted.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For numbered snapshots, which include administration and installation snapshot 
          pairs, the cleanup is controlled by parameters such as <literal>NUMBER_CLEANUP</literal>,
        <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal>, <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>, and <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>. 
          The default values are 2&#x2013;10 for <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> and 4&#x2013;10 for
          <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>, meaning that only the youngest snapshots are kept.</para>
          <para>For timeline snapshots, the cleanup is based on the number of snapshots to keep for 
          each type (hourly, daily, weekly, monthly, yearly). For example, the last 24 hourly
          snapshots, the first daily snapshot from the last seven days, the first snapshot 
          made on the last day of the month for the last twelve months, and so forth. The parameters 
          include <literal>TIMELINE_CLEANUP</literal>, <literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal> and 
          interval parameters such as <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY</literal>, 
          <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_HOURLY</literal> and so on.</para>
      <para>You can roll back to an existing snapshot at any time by booting from 
        the respective snapshot and making it active afterwards.</para> 
        <note>
          <title>Disabling Snapper automatically and manually</title>
          <para>If your root partition is smaller than 16&#xA0;GB, the automatic creation 
          of snapshots as described above is disabled by default. In this case, 
          you can manually create snapshots. Keep an 
          eye on the available disk space.</para>
          <para>To disable automatic snapshots even if your root partition is sufficiently 
          sized, disable snapshots manually during the installation in the partition setup 
          step.</para>
        </note>
</section>

<section xml:id="snapper-on-root">
        <title>Snapper on root</title> 
         <para>When Snapper is configured to operate on root, every Btrfs subvolume is
         excluded by default.</para>
        <para>The default behavior of Snapper is defined in a configuration file that 
         is specific for each partition or Btrfs subvolume. These configuration files reside
         under <filename>/etc/snapper/configs/</filename>.</para>
         
</section>

<section xml:id="snapper-subvolumes">
        <title>Subvolumes excluded from snapshots</title>
         <para>The primary use case for snapshots is to roll back the system 
          to a previous state. Therefore, there are certain subvolumes (directories)
          for which snapshotting is disabled.</para>
          <para>The following list contains directories that are excluded from snapshots. 
            Depending on your product and architecture, not all of them may be available
            on your system.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/boot/grub2/i386-pc</filename>,
             <filename>/boot/grub2/x86_64-efi</filename>,
             <filename>/boot/grub2/powerpc-ieee1275</filename>,
             <filename>/boot/grub2/s390x-emu</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              A rollback of the boot loader configuration is not supported. The
              directories listed above are architecture-specific. The first two
              directories are present on AMD64/Intel 64 machines, the latter two are
              on IBM POWER and on IBM&#xA0;Z, respectively.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/home</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              If <filename>/home</filename> does not reside on a separate partition, it
              is excluded to avoid the loss of user-created data on rollbacks.
             </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
           <term><filename>/opt</filename>, <filename>/usr/local</filename>
           </term>
           <listitem>
            <para>
              These directories are used when manually installing third-party products.
              They are excluded to avoid uninstalling these installations on rollbacks.
            </para>
           </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/srv</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              Contains data for Web and FTP servers. It is excluded to avoid data loss on
              rollbacks.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/tmp</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              All directories containing temporary files and caches are excluded from
              snapshots.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>           
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/var</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              This directory contains many variable files, including logs, temporary
              caches, third-party products in <filename>/var/opt</filename>, and is the
              default location for virtual machine images and databases. Therefore, this
              subvolume is created to exclude all of this variable data from snapshots
              and has copy-on-write disabled.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/run</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              This directory contains application runtime data and is excluded from
              snapshots to reduce the size of the snapshot and to avoid including 
              potentially sensitive information.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
         <tip>
            <para>
              The list of subvolumes is product-specific. To see what subvolumes 
              are created under <filename>/</filename> and 
              therefore see which directories are excluded from the 
              default snapshots behavior, run:</para>
            <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> btrfs subvolume list /</screen>
         </tip>  
      <note><title>Why is there a space limit?</title>
      <para>
        When creating a snapshot, no physical data copies are created. A snapshot only consists of 
        pointers to the respective data blocks. As long as the snapshot remains consistent with 
        the current system, it occupies almost no additional disk space (apart from the metadata 
        it contains). However, if a file is modified on the system, the original data is recorded
        in the snapshot. Over time, as more changes accumulate and the snapshot diverges from 
        the live system, the snapshot's size increases accordingly.</para>
        <para>To prevent disks from running full (and the system becoming inoperable as a result), we 
        recommend having a minimal root file system size. The required size depends on system usage:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>The frequency of snapshot creation</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>The duration for which snapshots are retained</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>The rate of changes to the system</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
        <para>In general, the more snapshots you have, the longer they are kept, and the more 
          frequently the system changes, the larger the root partition needs to be.</para>
      </note>
  </section>
    </section>
  <section role="glue" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="snapper-basic-concepts-more-info"><info>
    <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">For more information</title>
    
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    
    
  </info>
  
  <para>
  For more information on the Btrfs file system, refer 
  to <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP5/html/SLES-all/cha-filesystems.html#sec-filesystems-major-btrfs"/>
  and <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/btrfs"/>.
  </para>
  <para>For more information on LVM volumes, refer to 
  <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sles/15-SP5/html/SLES-all/part-lvm.html"/>.</para>
</section>
  <section version="5.2" xml:id="legal-disclaimer"><info>
    <title xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Legal Notice</title>
  </info>
  
  <para> Copyright&#xA9; 2006&#x2013;<?dbtimestamp format="Y"?>
 SUSE LLC and contributors.
  All rights reserved. </para>
  <para>
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the
    GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant
    Section being this copyright notice and license. A copy of the license version 1.2 is included
    in the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation License</quote>.
  </para>
  <para>
    For SUSE trademarks, see <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>. All other
    third-party trademarks are the property of their respective owners. Trademark symbols (&#xAE;, &#x2122;
    etc.) denote trademarks of SUSE and its affiliates. Asterisks (*) denote third-party
    trademarks.
  </para>
  <para>
    All information found in this book has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However,
    this does not guarantee complete accuracy.  Neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, nor
    the translators shall be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof.
  </para>
</section>
  <appendix xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" version="5.2" role="legal" its:translate="no" xml:id="doc-gfdl-license"><info>
   <title xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GNU Free Documentation License</title>
 </info>

 

 <para>
  Copyright (C) 2000, 2001, 2002 Free Software Foundation, Inc. 51 Franklin St,
  Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA. Everyone is permitted to copy and
  distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but changing it is not
  allowed.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    0. PREAMBLE
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other
  functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to assure
  everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or without
  modifying it, either commercially or non-commercially. Secondarily, this
  License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit for their
  work, while not being considered responsible for modifications made by
  others.
 </para>

 <para>
  This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative works of
  the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It complements the
  GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license designed for free
  software.
 </para>

 <para>
  We have designed this License to use it for manuals for free software,
  because free software needs free documentation: a free program should come
  with manuals providing the same freedoms that the software does. But this
  License is not limited to software manuals; it can be used for any textual
  work, regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a printed
  book. We recommend this License principally for works whose purpose is
  instruction or reference.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium, that
  contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be distributed
  under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a world-wide,
  royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work under the
  conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers to any such manual or
  work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you". You
  accept the license if you copy, modify or distribute the work in a way
  requiring permission under copyright law.
 </para>

 <para>
  A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the Document
  or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with modifications and/or
  translated into another language.
 </para>

 <para>
  A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section of the
  Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the publishers or
  authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related
  matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within that overall
  subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a
  Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.) The relationship could be
  a matter of historical connection with the subject or with related matters,
  or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position
  regarding them.
 </para>

 <para>
  The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles are
  designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice that says
  that the Document is released under this License. If a section does not fit
  the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as
  Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections. If the Document
  does not identify any Invariant Sections then there are none.
 </para>

 <para>
  The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are listed, as
  Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that the
  Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may be at most 5
  words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.
 </para>

 <para>
  A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy,
  represented in a format whose specification is available to the general
  public, that is suitable for revising the document straightforwardly with
  generic text editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint
  programs or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that is
  suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a
  variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters. A copy made in an
  otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of markup, has
  been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent modification by readers is
  not Transparent. An image format is not Transparent if used for any
  substantial amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called
  "Opaque".
 </para>

 <para>
  Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain ASCII
  without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or XML using a
  publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML, PostScript or
  PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent image formats
  include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary formats that can
  be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which
  the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally available, and the
  machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors
  for output purposes only.
 </para>

 <para>
  The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself, plus such
  following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material this License
  requires to appear in the title page. For works in formats which do not have
  any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent
  appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the
  text.
 </para>

 <para>
  A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose title
  either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following text that
  translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands for a specific section
  name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements", "Dedications",
  "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of such a section when
  you modify the Document means that it remains a section "Entitled XYZ"
  according to this definition.
 </para>

 <para>
  The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice which states
  that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty Disclaimers are
  considered to be included by reference in this License, but only as regards
  disclaiming warranties: any other implication that these Warranty Disclaimers
  may have is void and has no effect on the meaning of this License.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    2. VERBATIM COPYING
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either commercially
  or non-commercially, provided that this License, the copyright notices, and
  the license notice saying this License applies to the Document are reproduced
  in all copies, and that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of
  this License. You may not use technical measures to obstruct or control the
  reading or further copying of the copies you make or distribute. However, you
  may accept compensation in exchange for copies. If you distribute a large
  enough number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section 3.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above, and you may
  publicly display copies.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    3. COPYING IN QUANTITY
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have printed
  covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the Document's license
  notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the copies in covers that
  carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the
  front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover. Both covers must also
  clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these copies. The front
  cover must present the full title with all words of the title equally
  prominent and visible. You may add other material on the covers in addition.
  Copying with changes limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the
  title of the Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as
  verbatim copying in other respects.
 </para>

 <para>
  If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit legibly, you
  should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably) on the actual
  cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.
 </para>

 <para>
  If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering more
  than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent copy along
  with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a
  computer-network location from which the general network-using public has
  access to download using public-standard network protocols a complete
  Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material. If you use the
  latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you begin
  distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent
  copy will remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one
  year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through
  your agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.
 </para>

 <para>
  It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of the
  Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to give them
  a chance to provide you with an updated version of the Document.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    4. MODIFICATIONS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under the
  conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release the Modified
  Version under precisely this License, with the Modified Version filling the
  role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the
  Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do
  these things in the Modified Version:
 </para>

 <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from
    that of the Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if
    there were any, be listed in the History section of the Document). You may
    use the same title as a previous version if the original publisher of that
    version gives permission.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities
    responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version,
    together with at least five of the principal authors of the Document (all
    of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five), unless they release
    you from this requirement.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the Modified Version,
    as the publisher.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the
    other copyright notices.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license notice giving
    the public permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this
    License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and
    required Cover Texts given in the Document's license notice.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Include an unaltered copy of this License.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title, and add to it
    an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the
    Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If there is no section
    Entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating the title, year,
    authors, and publisher of the Document as given on its Title Page, then add
    an item describing the Modified Version as stated in the previous sentence.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for public
    access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network
    locations given in the Document for previous versions it was based on.
    These may be placed in the "History" section. You may omit a network
    location for a work that was published at least four years before the
    Document itself, or if the original publisher of the version it refers to
    gives permission.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", Preserve the
    Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the substance and
    tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications given
    therein.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their
    text and in their titles. Section numbers or the equivalent are not
    considered part of the section titles.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section may not be
    included in the Modified Version.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled "Endorsements" or to
    conflict in title with any Invariant Section.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>

 <para>
  If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or appendices that
  qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material copied from the
  Document, you may at your option designate some or all of these sections as
  invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in
  the Modified Version's license notice. These titles must be distinct from any
  other section titles.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains nothing
  but endorsements of your Modified Version by various parties--for example,
  statements of peer review or that the text has been approved by an
  organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a
  passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list of
  Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of Front-Cover Text and
  one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements made by) any
  one entity. If the Document already includes a cover text for the same cover,
  previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity you are
  acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may replace the old
  one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher that added the old
  one.
 </para>

 <para>
  The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License give
  permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or imply
  endorsement of any Modified Version.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may combine the Document with other documents released under this
  License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified versions,
  provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant Sections of
  all of the original documents, unmodified, and list them all as Invariant
  Sections of your combined work in its license notice, and that you preserve
  all their Warranty Disclaimers.
 </para>

 <para>
  The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and multiple
  identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy. If there are
  multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different contents, make
  the title of each such section unique by adding at the end of it, in
  parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of that section if
  known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment to the section
  titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the
  combined work.
 </para>

 <para>
  In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History" in the
  various original documents, forming one section Entitled "History"; likewise
  combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled
  "Dedications". You must delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents
  released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this
  License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in the
  collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for verbatim
  copying of each of the documents in all other respects.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may extract a single document from such a collection, and distribute it
  individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this License
  into the extracted document, and follow this License in all other respects
  regarding verbatim copying of that document.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate and
  independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or
  distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright resulting from
  the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of the compilation's
  users beyond what the individual works permit. When the Document is included
  in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the other works in the
  aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of the Document.
 </para>

 <para>
  If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these copies of
  the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the entire
  aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers that bracket
  the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of covers if
  the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear on printed
  covers that bracket the whole aggregate.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    8. TRANSLATION
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may distribute
  translations of the Document under the terms of section 4. Replacing
  Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission from their
  copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or all Invariant
  Sections in addition to the original versions of these Invariant Sections.
  You may include a translation of this License, and all the license notices in
  the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include
  the original English version of this License and the original versions of
  those notices and disclaimers. In case of a disagreement between the
  translation and the original version of this License or a notice or
  disclaimer, the original version will prevail.
 </para>

 <para>
  If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements", "Dedications",
  or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its Title (section 1)
  will typically require changing the actual title.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    9. TERMINATION
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except as
  expressly provided for under this License. Any other attempt to copy, modify,
  sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will automatically
  terminate your rights under this License. However, parties who have received
  copies, or rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
  terminated so long as such parties remain in full compliance.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of the GNU
  Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions will be
  similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail to address
  new problems or concerns. See
  <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/"/>.
 </para>

 <para>
  Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number. If the
  Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this License "or any
  later version" applies to it, you have the option of following the terms and
  conditions either of that specified version or of any later version that has
  been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If the
  Document does not specify a version number of this License, you may choose
  any version ever published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents
  </bridgehead>

<screen>Copyright (c) YEAR YOUR NAME.
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
A copy of the license is included in the section entitled &#x201C;GNU
Free Documentation License&#x201D;.</screen>

 <para>
  If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover Texts,
  replace the &#x201C;with...Texts.&#x201D; line with this:
 </para>

<screen>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.</screen>

 <para>
  If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other combination
  of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the situation.
 </para>

 <para>
  If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we recommend
  releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free software
  license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their use in free
  software.
</para>
</appendix>
</article>
