<?xml version="1.0"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2" xml:id="Intro-firewalld" xml:lang="en">
  <info>
      <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its">Introduction to <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem></title>
      
      <revhistory xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xml:id="rh-intro-firewalld">
        <revision><date>2025-11-04</date>
          <revdescription>
            <para>Initial version</para>
          </revdescription>
        </revision>
       </revhistory>

       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>

       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="productname" its:translate="no">
         
         <productname os="sles;sles4sap" version="16.0"><phrase><phrase os="sles">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server</phrase></phrase></productname>        
         
       </meta>

       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="architecture" its:translate="no">
        <phrase>AMD64/Intel&#xA0;64</phrase>
        <phrase>POWER</phrase>
        <phrase>IBM&#xA0;Z</phrase>
        <phrase>AArch64</phrase>
       </meta>

       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="title" its:translate="yes">Introduction to <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem></meta>
       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="description" its:translate="yes">Learn about <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem>, the default network defense on modern Linux, and master dynamic, zone-based management to secure your server</meta>
       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="social-descr" its:translate="yes">Fundamentals of <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> for network security</meta>


       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="task" its:translate="no">
         <phrase>Authentication</phrase>
         <phrase>Security</phrase>
        </meta>

       <meta xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" name="series" its:translate="no">Products &amp; Solutions</meta>

      
      <dm:docmanager xmlns:dm="urn:x-suse:ns:docmanager" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its">
        <dm:bugtracker>
          <dm:url>https://bugzilla.suse.com/enter_bug.cgi</dm:url>
          <dm:component>Documentation</dm:component>
          
          <dm:product os="sles">SUSE Linux Enterprise Server 16.0</dm:product>
                    
          <dm:assignee>amrita.sakthivel@suse.com</dm:assignee>
        </dm:bugtracker>
        <dm:translation>yes</dm:translation>
      </dm:docmanager>

      <abstract xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its">
        <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>WHAT?</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
            Learn about <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> an important tool for securing Linux servers and services. It is the default and primary network
            defense mechanism on many modern distributions. The intuitive zone-based management and dynamic configuration capabilities allow for
            precise control over network traffic without service interruption.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>WHY?</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> is essential because it provides a modern, dynamic and user-friendly way to manage network security on Linux systems by
              abstracting complex firewall rules into intuitive zones and services.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>EFFORT</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                It takes you up to 30 minutes to read through this article.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>GOAL</term>
            <listitem>
              <para>
               To effectively manage and enhance the security of a Linux system.
              </para>
            </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>REQUIREMENTS</term>
            <listitem>
              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                  <literal>sudo</literal> or <literal>root</literal> privileges, because <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> commands, especially those that make
                    permanent changes to the firewall rules, require elevated privileges.
                  </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                <para>
                 <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> is the default firewall on many modern Linux distributions, if it is not preinstalled on your system,
                 you need to install the <literal>firewalld</literal> package.
               </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                  <para>
                    A basic understanding of the Linux terminal is essential.
                 </para>
                  </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </abstract>
    </info>
  <section role="concept" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="about-firewalld"><info>
    <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">About <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem></title>
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
      <para>
<systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> is a dynamic firewall management service that provides a flexible and efficient way to control network traffic on Linux systems.
It allows modifications without interrupting existing connections. The benefits of using <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> are:
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
   <emphasis>Dynamic configuration:</emphasis> Apply changes instantly without breaking existing connections.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
    <emphasis>User-friendly interface:</emphasis> Zones and services simplify complex firewall rules.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
    <emphasis>Abstraction:</emphasis> There is no need to directly manipulate <literal>nftables</literal> rules for common scenarios.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
    <emphasis>Persistent configuration:</emphasis> Easy management of rules that survive reboots.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    <para>
    <emphasis>Persistent configuration:</emphasis> By default, <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> operates on a <literal>deny-all</literal> principle
    by blocking all incoming traffic unless explicitly allowed.</para>
     </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<section xml:id="firewall-zones">
<title><systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zones</title>
<para>
  A firewall zone is a predefined set of rules that dictate how incoming and outgoing network traffic is handled for a specific network interface or source IP address.
  Each zone represents a different level of trust for the network it is associated with. You can apply different security policies based on where the network connection originates.
   </para>
  <para>
  Zones are like security profiles. For example, you would want to apply different firewall rules for a public Wi-Fi connection and your secure home network.
  <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zones allow you to define these distinct sets of rules and apply them accordingly.
  A network connection is subject to the rules of only one <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zone. A <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zone can have many network interfaces or source IP addresses.
   </para>
   <para>The <filename>/usr/lib/firewalld/zones/ </filename> directory stores the predefined zones. For example:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt> /usr/lib/firewalld/zones ls
block.xml  dmz.xml  docker.xml  drop.xml  external.xml  home.xml  internal.xml  nm-shared.xml  public.xml  trusted.xml  work.xml
</screen>
   <para>Some of the default settings of the predefined zones are as follows:</para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>drop</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> Completely untrusted.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis> All incoming network packets are dropped without any reply. Only outgoing connections initiated from the system are allowed.
                This provides a <quote>stealth</quote> mode where the system appears nonexistent to external attackers.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use Case:</emphasis> Used for maximum stealth and security, completely ignoring unwanted traffic.
               Suitable as a strict default for a server that should never accept incoming connections.
             </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>block</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> Very low.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis> All incoming network connections are rejected with an <literal>icmp-host-prohibited</literal> message for IPv4 and <literal>cmp6-adm-prohibited</literal>i for IPv6.
               This informs the sender that their connection was explicitly rejected. Only outgoing connections initiated from the system are possible.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use Case:</emphasis> Applied when you want to explicitly signal to senders that their connection attempts are being blocked.
             </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>public</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> Untrusted or public.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis> Represents public, untrusted networks where you do not trust other systems.
               Only selected incoming connections are accepted by default for example, SSH, DHCPv6 client, etc.
               </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use Case:</emphasis> Common default zone for interfaces connected directly to the Internet, such as your router's WAN interface. Also includes
              being connected to a network where you have no control over other devices.
             </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>external</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> External with masquerading.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis> Intended for external networks when the firewall acts as a gateway or router.
               Usually, NAT masquerading is enabled by default.Only selected incoming connections are accepted, under the assumption that you do not trust other systems on this network.
               </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use Case:</emphasis> Used when your Linux machine acts as a router, connecting an internal private network to the public Internet.
               The external interface is placed in this zone to hide internal network topology while allowing internal clients to access external resources such as the Internet.
             </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>dmz (Demilitarized Zone)</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> Limited public access.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis> For systems in a DMZ zone that are publicly accessible but with limited access to the internal network.
               Only selected incoming connections are accepted. The default usually includes SSH and other services you expose.
               </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use Case:</emphasis> Suitable for public-facing servers such as Web, mail and DNS servers. These servers are intentionally exposed to the Internet but are isolated from your internal, more trusted networks.
               Useful when you want to host services that need to be Internet-accessible while minimizing the risk to your core internal infrastructure.
             </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>work</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> Mostly trusted (work environment).
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis> In a work environment, you usually trust other computers on the network.
               Allows selected incoming connections that are common in a work environment, such as SSH and DHCPv6 client.
               </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use Case:</emphasis> Suitable for office networks and systems on a corporate LAN.
               </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>home</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> Mostly trusted (home environment).
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis> In a home environment, you mostly trust the other systems on the network.
               Allows more services than public or external zones, often including common home network services like file sharing, media servers, and printers, along with SSH and DHCPv6 client.
               </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use case:</emphasis> Best for home networks and small home office setups.
               </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
       <term><literal>trusted</literal></term>
       <listitem>
         <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Trust level:</emphasis> Highest.
             </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Behavior:</emphasis>  All network connections are accepted without any filtering.
               Firewalling is not implemented for connections assigned to this zone.
               </para>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
             <para>
               <emphasis>Use Case:</emphasis> Reserved for highly trusted connections.
               </para>
           </listitem>
         </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
</section>
<section xml:id="firewall-policies-rules">
 <title><systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> policies and rules </title>
  <para>
  <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> policies provide a more advanced and flexible way to manage network traffic compared to traditional zones.
  They allow you to define rich rules that specify the source and destination of traffic, services, ports and actions such as accept, reject and drop.
  These policies are useful for setting up complex routing, port forwarding or creating isolated network segments within a single host.
  </para>
<para>
<systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> policies leverage zones to define rule sets. They apply rules statefully and in one direction, which means you define traffic flow in one direction,
and <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> implicitly permits the return path. These policies link an ingress zone (where traffic enters) with an egress zone (where traffic exits).
This defines the specific path and direction a policy's rules apply to. You can view the policies, for example:
</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt> /usr/lib/firewalld/policies ls
allow-host-ipv6.xml
</screen>
<para>Firewall rules let you precisely control network traffic, allowing or blocking it to protect your system from security threats.
Firewall rules define certain criteria based on various attributes such as, source and destination IP addresses, ports and network interfaces.
<systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> segregates firewall rules into zones and policies. Each zone in <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> has a unique set of rules that dictates the traffic permissions for its associated network interfaces.
</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="services-and-ports">
  <title>Services and ports </title>
  <para>
    Services are recommended when a predefined service is available. For example, instead of remembering that
    HTTP uses TCP port 80, you can simply add the <literal>http</literal> service. This is less error-prone and easier to manage.
    Use ports when a service is not predefined or when you are using a custom port for a service. You can view the active
    services and ports for the default zones with the following: </para>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command>  <command>firewall-cmd --list-services</command></screen>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command>  <command>firewall-cmd --list-ports</command></screen>
 </section>
</section>
  <section role="glue" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="firewalld-managing-zones-glue"><info>
    <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">Managing firewall rules and zones</title>
    
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    
    
  </info>
  
  
 <para>
  You can configure <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zones and their rules with the graphical Web interface Cockpit or the <command>firewall-cmd</command>utility for command-line control.
 </para>
<section role="task" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="firewalld-adding-zones-cli"><info>
    <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">Managing firewall rules and zones using the <command>firewalld-cmd</command> utility</title>
    
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
      <para>
       You can use the CLI interface to manage <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zones.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  
  <section xml:id="firewalld-adding-zones-cli-new-zone">
    <title>Adding <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zones</title>
    <para>
      To add a new <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zone:
    </para>
    <procedure>
      <step>
        <para>
          Create a new zone, for example:
        </para>
        <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --permanent --new-zone=<replaceable>test</replaceable></command></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
         Set the trust level of the zone that defines the default behavior:
        </para>
        <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --permanent --zone=example --set-target=<replaceable>trusted</replaceable></command></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Reload the <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> service to apply the new configuration:
        </para>
        <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --reload</command></screen>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="firewalld-adding-zones-cli-add-service">
    <title>Adding a service to a zone</title>
<para>To add a service to a zone:</para>
<procedure>
  <step>
    <para>
      List all services to check if your service is already predefined:
    </para>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --get-services</command>
      0-AD RH-Satellite-6 RH-Satellite-6-capsule afp alvr amanda-client amanda-k5-client amqp amqps anno-1602
      anno-1800 apcupsd audit ausweisapp2 bacula bacula-client bareos-director bareos-filedaemon bareos-storage bb bgp bitcoin bitcoin-rpc bitcoin-testnet bitcoin-testnet-rpc bittorrent-lsd ceph ceph-exporter ceph-mon cfengine checkmk-agent civilization-iv civilization-v cockpit collectd condor-collector cratedb ctdb dds dds-multicast dds-unicast dhcp dhcpv6 dhcpv6-client distcc dns dns-over-quic dns-over-tls docker-registry docker-swarm dropbox-lansync elasticsearch etcd-client etcd-server factorio finger foreman foreman-proxy freeipa-4 freeipa-ldap freeipa-ldaps freeipa-replication freeipa-trust ftp galera
      ganglia-client ganglia-master git gpsd grafana gre http http3 https ident imap imaps ipfs ipp ipp-client ipsec irc ircs
      [...]
    </screen>
  </step>
  <step>
    <para>
     You can add a service either temporarily for the runtime session or permanently, for example:
    </para>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command> firewall-cmd --zone=public --add-service=http</command></screen>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command> firewall-cmd --zone=public --permanent --add-service=http</command></screen>
  <para>The <literal>--permanent</literal> flag ensures the change persists across all reboots. </para>
  </step>
  <step>
    <para>
      Reload the <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> service to apply the new configuration:
    </para>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --reload</command></screen>
  </step>
  <step>
    <para>
     Verify the results:
    </para>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --zone=public --list-services</command></screen>
  </step>
</procedure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="firewalld-adding-zones-cli-add-port">
    <title>Adding a port to a zone</title>
<para>If your application does not have a predefined service, you can open a specific port or a range of ports.</para>
<procedure>
   <step>
    <para>
     You can either add a port temporarily for the runtime session or permanently, for example:
    </para>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command> firewall-cmd --zone=public --add-port=8080/tcp</command></screen>
    <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command> firewall-cmd --zone=public --permanent --add-port=8080/tcp</command></screen>
  <para>The <literal>--permanent</literal>flag ensures the change persists across all reboots. </para>
  </step><step>
        <para>
          Reload the <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> service to apply the new configuration:
        </para>
        <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --reload</command></screen>
      </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Verify the results:
      </para>
      <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --zone=public --list-ports</command></screen>
    </step>
 </procedure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="firewalld-deleting-zones-cli">
    <title>Deleting <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> zones</title>
    <para>
     To delete a zone:
    </para>
    <procedure>
      <step>
       <para>
        Verify the zone is not the default or in use:
       </para>
       <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command> firewall-cmd --get-default-zone</command></screen>
       <para>If the zone is in use or default, set a different zone, for example: </para>
       <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command> firewall-cmd --set-default-zone=<replaceable>NEW_DEFAULT_ZONE</replaceable></command></screen>
      </step>
      <step>
         <para>
          Check if any network interfaces are bound to the zone:
         </para>
         <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --zone=<replaceable>ZONE_TO_BE_DELETED</replaceable> --list-all</command></screen>
        </step>
        <step><para>The <literal>interfaces</literal> field in the output lists all the interfaces. Theses interfaces need to be
          reassigned to another zone. For example:</para>
        <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --zone=public --permanent --change-interface=<replaceable>ITERFACE_NAME</replaceable></command></screen>
        </step>
        <step><para>Delete the zone:</para>
        <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --permanent --delete-zone=<replaceable>ZONE_TO_BE_DELETED</replaceable></command></screen>
        </step>
        <step>
          <para>
            Reload the <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> service to apply the new configuration:
          </para>
          <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --reload</command></screen>
        </step>
       </procedure>
  </section>
</section><section role="task" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="task-managing-firewall-cockpit"><info>
          <title xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its">Managing firewall rules and zones with Cockpit</title>
           <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="jsindelarova@suse.com" its:translate="no"/><abstract xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
      <para>
        Cockpit enables you to create new zones or update the existing ones.
        In the firewall settings, you can add services to a zone or allow access
        to ports.
      </para>
    </abstract></info>
  
  <note>
    <title>Cockpit service is mandatory</title>
    <para>
      Do not remove the Cockpit service from the default firewall zone as
      the Cockpit service may get blocked, and you may get disconnected
      from the server.
    </para>
  </note>
  <section xml:id="cockpit-adding-firewall-zones">
    <title>Adding firewall zones</title>
    <para>
      The <guimenu>public zone</guimenu> is the default firewall zone. To add a
      new zone, proceed as follows:
    </para>
    <procedure>
      <title>Adding new firewall zones</title>
      <step>
        <para>
          Navigate to the <guimenu>Networking</guimenu> page.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click <guimenu>Edit rules and zones</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click <guimenu>Add new zone</guimenu>.
        </para>
        
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Select <guimenu>Trust level</guimenu>. Each trust level of network
          connections has a predefined set of included services (the Cockpit
          service is included in all trust levels). The description for each trust level appears in the <guimenu>Description</guimenu> section.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Define allowed addresses within the zone. Select one of the values:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guimenu>Entire subnet</guimenu> to allow all addresses in the
              subnet.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              <guimenu>Range</guimenu>&#x2014;a comma-separated list of IP
              addresses with the routing prefix, for example, 192.0.2.0/24,
              2001:db8::/32.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click <guimenu>Add zone</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="cockpit-adding-firewall-services">
    <title>Adding allowed services and ports to a zone</title>
    <para>
      You can add services to an existing firewall zone as described below:
    </para>
    <procedure>
      <title>Adding services to a firewall zone</title>
      <step>
        <para>
          Navigate to the <guimenu>Networking</guimenu> page.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click <guimenu>Edit rules and zones</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Click <guimenu>Add services</guimenu>.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          To add a service, select <guimenu>Services</guimenu> and choose the
          services from the list.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          To allow custom ports, select <guimenu>Custom ports</guimenu> and
          specify the port value for UDP and/or TCP. You can assign an
          identifier to this port.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          To confirm the changes, click <guimenu>Add services</guimenu> or
          <guimenu>Add ports</guimenu>, respectively.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
</section></section>
  <section role="concept" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="common-firewalld-commands"><info>
    <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">Common <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> commands</title>
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
      <para>
   The <command>firewall-cmd</command> command-line tool is used to configure and manage the <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> daemon.
   It is a powerful, dynamic utility that allows for the creation, modification, and deletion of firewall rules without
   requiring a full service restart, which prevents interruption of active network connections.
   </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  
    <para>
Some common <command>firewall-cmd</command> command examples include:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
            <para>
              Checking if <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> is running. The outputs are <literal>running</literal>, <literal>not running</literal> or
              <literal>RUNNING_BUT_FAILED</literal>. For example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --state</command>
running
</screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Listing all available zones, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --get-zones</command>
 block dmz docker drop external home internal nm-shared public trusted work
</screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Viewing the default zone, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --get-default-zone</command>
public
</screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
           Viewing the active zones and the assigned, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --get-active-zones</command>
docker
interfaces: docker0
public (default)
interfaces: lo enp1s0
</screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
          Viewing all rules for the default zone, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --list-all</command>
public (default, active)
target: default
ingress-priority: 0
egress-priority: 0
icmp-block-inversion: no
interfaces: enp1s0 lo
sources:
services: cockpit dhcpv6-client ssh
ports:
protocols:
forward: yes
masquerade: no
forward-ports:
source-ports:
icmp-blocks:
rich rules:
rule family="ipv4" source address="192.168.1.100" service name="ssh" accept
</screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
          Viewing all rules for a specific zone, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --zone=public --list-all</command>
public (default, active)
target: default
ingress-priority: 0
egress-priority: 0
icmp-block-inversion: no
interfaces: enp1s0 lo
sources:
services: cockpit dhcpv6-client ssh
ports:
protocols:
forward: yes
masquerade: no
forward-ports:
source-ports:
icmp-blocks:
rich rules:
rule family="ipv4" source address="192.168.1.100" service name="ssh" accept
</screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
           Listing all available predefined services, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --get-services</command>
  0-AD RH-Satellite-6 RH-Satellite-6-capsule afp alvr amanda-client amanda-k5-client amqp amqps anno-1602 anno-1800
  apcupsd audit ausweisapp2 bacula bacula-client bareos-director bareos-filedaemon bareos-storage bb bgp bitcoin bitcoin-rpc
  bitcoin-testnet bitcoin-testnet-rpc bittorrent-lsd ceph ceph-exporter ceph-mon cfengine checkmk-agent civilization-iv civilization-v
  cockpit collectd condor-collector cratedb ctdb dds dds-multicast dds-unicast dhcp dhcpv6 dhcpv6-client distcc dns dns-over-quic dns-over-tls
  docker-registry docker-swarm dropbox-lansync elasticsearch etcd-client etcd-server factorio finger foreman foreman-proxy freeipa-4 freeipa-ldap
  freeipa-ldaps freeipa-replication freeipa-trust ftp galera ganglia-client ganglia-master git gpsd grafana gre http http3 https ident imap imaps
  ipfs ipp ipp-client ipsec irc ircs iscsi-target isns jenkins kadmin kdeconnect kerberos kibana klogin kpasswd kprop kshell kube-api kube-apiserver
  kube-control-plane kube-control-plane-secure kube-controller-manager kube-controller-manager-secure kube-nodeport-services kube-scheduler kube-scheduler-secure
  [...] </screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
          Listing the services currently allowed in the default zone, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --list-services</command>
cockpit dhcpv6-client ssh
</screen>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
Adding a service to the default zone permanently, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command>  <command>firewall-cmd --permanent --add-service=http</command>
success
</screen>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para>
Removing a service permanently, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --permanent --remove-service=http</command>
success
</screen>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para>
          Listing the ports currently open in the default zone, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --list-ports</command>
22/tcp
</screen>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para>
           Opening a specific TCP port temporarily, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --add-port=8080/tcp</command>
success
</screen>
           </listitem>
           <listitem>
            <para>
           Removing an open port permanently, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --permanent --remove-port=8080/tcp</command>
success
</screen>
           </listitem>
            <listitem>
            <para>
          Adding an interface to a specific zone temporarily, for example:
        </para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --zone=trusted --add-interface=eth1</command> f
success
</screen>
           </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>

</section>
  <section role="concept" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="firewalld-troubleshooting"><info>
    <title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion"><systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> troubleshooting</title>
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
      <para>
       Troubleshooting <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> involves checking its status, verifying rules, and restarting or reloading the service.
       If you encounter issues, you can enable debugging, examine logs and adjust firewall rules as needed.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  

  <section xml:id="check-firewall-status">
<title>Check <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> status</title>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Use the <command>systemctl status</command> command, for example:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>systemctl status  firewalld.service</command>
&#x25CF; firewalld.service - firewalld - dynamic firewall daemon
Loaded: loaded (/usr/lib/systemd/system/firewalld.service; enabled; preset: enabled)
Active: active (running) since Thu 2025-07-17 09:47:36 CEST; 5min ago
Invocation: a7ea482f16d2431fa92d6204c297ebd9
Docs: man:firewalld(1)
Main PID: 921 (firewalld)
Tasks: 2
CPU: 262ms
CGroup: /system.slice/firewalld.service
        &#x2514;&#x2500;921 /usr/bin/python3.13 /usr/sbin/firewalld --nofork --nopid</screen>
     </listitem>
     <listitem><para>The <command>firewall-cmd --state</command> command gives a quick status check with <literal>running</literal>,
      <literal>not running</literal> or <literal>RUNNING_BUT_FAILED</literal> outputs. For example:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --state</command>
running </screen>
      </listitem>
      <listitem><para>If <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> is not running, use the <command>systemctl start firewalld</command> command.</para>
      <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command>  systemctl start firewalld </screen>
        </listitem>
        <listitem><para>If the <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> service is masked, unmask it first, then enable and start it, for example:</para>
         <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>systemctl unmask --now firewalld</command></screen>
         <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>systemctl enable firewalld</command> </screen>
         <screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>systemctl start firewalld</command> </screen>
            </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="verify-firewall-rules">
      <title>Check <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> rules </title>
      <itemizedlist><listitem><para> The <command>firewall-cmd --list-all-zones</command> command displays all zones and their rules, for example:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --list-all-zones</command>
        block
          target: %%REJECT%%
          ingress-priority: 0
          egress-priority: 0
          icmp-block-inversion: no
          interfaces:
          sources:
          services:
          ports:
          protocols:
          forward: yes
          masquerade: no
          forward-ports:
          source-ports:
          icmp-blocks:
          rich rules:

        dmz
          target: default
          ingress-priority: 0
          egress-priority: 0
          icmp-block-inversion: no
          interfaces:
          sources:
          services: ssh
          ports:
          protocols:
          forward: yes
          masquerade: no
          forward-ports:
          source-ports:
          icmp-blocks:
          rich rules:

        docker (active)
          target: ACCEPT
          ingress-priority: 0
          egress-priority: 0
          icmp-block-inversion: no
          [...]
        </screen>
           </listitem>
           <listitem><para>The <command>firewall-cmd --list-ports</command> command shows open ports,for example:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --list-ports</command>
22/tcp
</screen>
            </listitem>
            <listitem><para>The <command>firewall-cmd --zone=<replaceable>YOUR_ZONE</replaceable> --list-all.
            </command> command lists ports for specific zones, for example:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewall-cmd --zone=dmz --list-all</command>
                dmz
                  target: default
                  ingress-priority: 0
                  egress-priority: 0
                  icmp-block-inversion: no
                  interfaces:
                  sources:
                  services: ssh
                  ports:
                  protocols:
                  forward: yes
                  masquerade: no
                  forward-ports:
                  source-ports:
                  icmp-blocks:
                  rich rules:
                                </screen>
                </listitem>
                    </itemizedlist>
          </section>
          <section xml:id="debug-firewall">
            <title>Debugging <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> </title>
            <itemizedlist><listitem><para> Enable debugging in <filename>/etc/sysconfig/firewalld</filename> by adding <literal>--debug=[level]</literal>
              to <literal>FIREWALLD_ARGS</literal>, for example:</para>
<screen>
<prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command>  vi /etc/sysconfig/firewalld
# firewalld command line args
# possible values: --debug
FIREWALLD_ARGS=--debug=[level]
              </screen>
                 </listitem>
                 <listitem><para>Start <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem> with the <literal>--debug</literal>option, for example:</para>
<screen><prompt>&gt; </prompt><command>sudo</command> <command>firewalld --nofork --debug</command>
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: start()
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: Loading firewalld config file '/etc/firewalld/firewalld.conf'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: CleanupOnExit is set to 'True'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: CleanupModulesOnExit is set to 'False'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: IPv6 rpfilter is enabled
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: LogDenied is set to 'off'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: FirewallBackend is set to 'nftables'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: FlushAllOnReload is set to 'False'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: RFC3964_IPv4 is set to 'True'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: NftablesFlowtable is set to 'off'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: NftablesCounters is set to 'False'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: Loading lockdown whitelist
2025-07-23 11:10:05 ipset not usable, disabling ipset usage in firewall. Other set backends (nftables) remain usable.
2025-07-23 11:10:05 iptables-restore and iptables are missing, IPv4 direct rules won't be usable.
2025-07-23 11:10:05 ip6tables-restore and ip6tables are missing, IPv6 direct rules won't be usable.
2025-07-23 11:10:05 ebtables-restore and ebtables are missing, eb direct rules won't be usable.
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: Loading icmptype file '/usr/lib/firewalld/icmptypes/address-unreachable.xml'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: Loading icmptype file '/usr/lib/firewalld/icmptypes/bad-header.xml'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: Loading icmptype file '/usr/lib/firewalld/icmptypes/beyond-scope.xml'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: Loading icmptype file '/usr/lib/firewalld/icmptypes/communication-prohibited.xml'
2025-07-23 11:10:05 DEBUG1: Loading icmptype file '/usr/lib/firewalld/icmptypes/destination-unreachable.xml'
[...]
</screen>
                <para>All log files are available at <filename>/var/log/firewalld</filename>.</para>
                  </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </section>

  </section>
  <section role="glue" xml:lang="en" version="5.2" xml:id="firewalld-more-info"><info><title xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">More information</title>
    <meta xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion" name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
      <para>
        To learn more about <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem>, refer to the following resources:
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  
  
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://firewalld.org/documentation/">The official source for concepts, architecture,
          how-to and links to all man pages.
        </link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://firewalld.org/documentation/man-pages/firewall-cmd.html">Man page essential for understanding
          command-line interaction with <systemitem class="daemon">firewalld</systemitem>
        </link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://wiki.archlinux.org/title/Firewalld">A comprehensive resource with
          excellent explanations and practical examples that also cover <literal>nftables</literal>.
        </link>
      </para>
    </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
</section>
  <section version="5.2" xml:id="legal-disclaimer"><info>
    <title xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Legal Notice</title>
  </info>
  
  <para> Copyright&#xA9; 2006&#x2013;<?dbtimestamp format="Y"?>
 SUSE LLC and contributors.
  All rights reserved. </para>
  <para>
    Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the terms of the
    GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2 or (at your option) version 1.3; with the Invariant
    Section being this copyright notice and license. A copy of the license version 1.2 is included
    in the section entitled <quote>GNU Free Documentation License</quote>.
  </para>
  <para>
    For SUSE trademarks, see <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/company/legal/"/>. All other
    third-party trademarks are the property of their respective owners. Trademark symbols (&#xAE;, &#x2122;
    etc.) denote trademarks of SUSE and its affiliates. Asterisks (*) denote third-party
    trademarks.
  </para>
  <para>
    All information found in this book has been compiled with utmost attention to detail. However,
    this does not guarantee complete accuracy.  Neither SUSE LLC, its affiliates, the authors, nor
    the translators shall be held liable for possible errors or the consequences thereof.
  </para>
</section>
  <appendix xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its" version="5.2" role="legal" its:translate="no" xml:id="doc-gfdl-license"><info>
   <title xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GNU Free Documentation License</title>
 </info>

 

 <para>
  Copyright (C) 2000, 2001, 2002 Free Software Foundation, Inc. 51 Franklin St,
  Fifth Floor, Boston, MA 02110-1301 USA. Everyone is permitted to copy and
  distribute verbatim copies of this license document, but changing it is not
  allowed.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    0. PREAMBLE
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  The purpose of this License is to make a manual, textbook, or other
  functional and useful document "free" in the sense of freedom: to assure
  everyone the effective freedom to copy and redistribute it, with or without
  modifying it, either commercially or non-commercially. Secondarily, this
  License preserves for the author and publisher a way to get credit for their
  work, while not being considered responsible for modifications made by
  others.
 </para>

 <para>
  This License is a kind of "copyleft", which means that derivative works of
  the document must themselves be free in the same sense. It complements the
  GNU General Public License, which is a copyleft license designed for free
  software.
 </para>

 <para>
  We have designed this License to use it for manuals for free software,
  because free software needs free documentation: a free program should come
  with manuals providing the same freedoms that the software does. But this
  License is not limited to software manuals; it can be used for any textual
  work, regardless of subject matter or whether it is published as a printed
  book. We recommend this License principally for works whose purpose is
  instruction or reference.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    1. APPLICABILITY AND DEFINITIONS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  This License applies to any manual or other work, in any medium, that
  contains a notice placed by the copyright holder saying it can be distributed
  under the terms of this License. Such a notice grants a world-wide,
  royalty-free license, unlimited in duration, to use that work under the
  conditions stated herein. The "Document", below, refers to any such manual or
  work. Any member of the public is a licensee, and is addressed as "you". You
  accept the license if you copy, modify or distribute the work in a way
  requiring permission under copyright law.
 </para>

 <para>
  A "Modified Version" of the Document means any work containing the Document
  or a portion of it, either copied verbatim, or with modifications and/or
  translated into another language.
 </para>

 <para>
  A "Secondary Section" is a named appendix or a front-matter section of the
  Document that deals exclusively with the relationship of the publishers or
  authors of the Document to the Document's overall subject (or to related
  matters) and contains nothing that could fall directly within that overall
  subject. (Thus, if the Document is in part a textbook of mathematics, a
  Secondary Section may not explain any mathematics.) The relationship could be
  a matter of historical connection with the subject or with related matters,
  or of legal, commercial, philosophical, ethical or political position
  regarding them.
 </para>

 <para>
  The "Invariant Sections" are certain Secondary Sections whose titles are
  designated, as being those of Invariant Sections, in the notice that says
  that the Document is released under this License. If a section does not fit
  the above definition of Secondary then it is not allowed to be designated as
  Invariant. The Document may contain zero Invariant Sections. If the Document
  does not identify any Invariant Sections then there are none.
 </para>

 <para>
  The "Cover Texts" are certain short passages of text that are listed, as
  Front-Cover Texts or Back-Cover Texts, in the notice that says that the
  Document is released under this License. A Front-Cover Text may be at most 5
  words, and a Back-Cover Text may be at most 25 words.
 </para>

 <para>
  A "Transparent" copy of the Document means a machine-readable copy,
  represented in a format whose specification is available to the general
  public, that is suitable for revising the document straightforwardly with
  generic text editors or (for images composed of pixels) generic paint
  programs or (for drawings) some widely available drawing editor, and that is
  suitable for input to text formatters or for automatic translation to a
  variety of formats suitable for input to text formatters. A copy made in an
  otherwise Transparent file format whose markup, or absence of markup, has
  been arranged to thwart or discourage subsequent modification by readers is
  not Transparent. An image format is not Transparent if used for any
  substantial amount of text. A copy that is not "Transparent" is called
  "Opaque".
 </para>

 <para>
  Examples of suitable formats for Transparent copies include plain ASCII
  without markup, Texinfo input format, LaTeX input format, SGML or XML using a
  publicly available DTD, and standard-conforming simple HTML, PostScript or
  PDF designed for human modification. Examples of transparent image formats
  include PNG, XCF and JPG. Opaque formats include proprietary formats that can
  be read and edited only by proprietary word processors, SGML or XML for which
  the DTD and/or processing tools are not generally available, and the
  machine-generated HTML, PostScript or PDF produced by some word processors
  for output purposes only.
 </para>

 <para>
  The "Title Page" means, for a printed book, the title page itself, plus such
  following pages as are needed to hold, legibly, the material this License
  requires to appear in the title page. For works in formats which do not have
  any title page as such, "Title Page" means the text near the most prominent
  appearance of the work's title, preceding the beginning of the body of the
  text.
 </para>

 <para>
  A section "Entitled XYZ" means a named subunit of the Document whose title
  either is precisely XYZ or contains XYZ in parentheses following text that
  translates XYZ in another language. (Here XYZ stands for a specific section
  name mentioned below, such as "Acknowledgements", "Dedications",
  "Endorsements", or "History".) To "Preserve the Title" of such a section when
  you modify the Document means that it remains a section "Entitled XYZ"
  according to this definition.
 </para>

 <para>
  The Document may include Warranty Disclaimers next to the notice which states
  that this License applies to the Document. These Warranty Disclaimers are
  considered to be included by reference in this License, but only as regards
  disclaiming warranties: any other implication that these Warranty Disclaimers
  may have is void and has no effect on the meaning of this License.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    2. VERBATIM COPYING
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may copy and distribute the Document in any medium, either commercially
  or non-commercially, provided that this License, the copyright notices, and
  the license notice saying this License applies to the Document are reproduced
  in all copies, and that you add no other conditions whatsoever to those of
  this License. You may not use technical measures to obstruct or control the
  reading or further copying of the copies you make or distribute. However, you
  may accept compensation in exchange for copies. If you distribute a large
  enough number of copies you must also follow the conditions in section 3.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may also lend copies, under the same conditions stated above, and you may
  publicly display copies.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    3. COPYING IN QUANTITY
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  If you publish printed copies (or copies in media that commonly have printed
  covers) of the Document, numbering more than 100, and the Document's license
  notice requires Cover Texts, you must enclose the copies in covers that
  carry, clearly and legibly, all these Cover Texts: Front-Cover Texts on the
  front cover, and Back-Cover Texts on the back cover. Both covers must also
  clearly and legibly identify you as the publisher of these copies. The front
  cover must present the full title with all words of the title equally
  prominent and visible. You may add other material on the covers in addition.
  Copying with changes limited to the covers, as long as they preserve the
  title of the Document and satisfy these conditions, can be treated as
  verbatim copying in other respects.
 </para>

 <para>
  If the required texts for either cover are too voluminous to fit legibly, you
  should put the first ones listed (as many as fit reasonably) on the actual
  cover, and continue the rest onto adjacent pages.
 </para>

 <para>
  If you publish or distribute Opaque copies of the Document numbering more
  than 100, you must either include a machine-readable Transparent copy along
  with each Opaque copy, or state in or with each Opaque copy a
  computer-network location from which the general network-using public has
  access to download using public-standard network protocols a complete
  Transparent copy of the Document, free of added material. If you use the
  latter option, you must take reasonably prudent steps, when you begin
  distribution of Opaque copies in quantity, to ensure that this Transparent
  copy will remain thus accessible at the stated location until at least one
  year after the last time you distribute an Opaque copy (directly or through
  your agents or retailers) of that edition to the public.
 </para>

 <para>
  It is requested, but not required, that you contact the authors of the
  Document well before redistributing any large number of copies, to give them
  a chance to provide you with an updated version of the Document.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    4. MODIFICATIONS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may copy and distribute a Modified Version of the Document under the
  conditions of sections 2 and 3 above, provided that you release the Modified
  Version under precisely this License, with the Modified Version filling the
  role of the Document, thus licensing distribution and modification of the
  Modified Version to whoever possesses a copy of it. In addition, you must do
  these things in the Modified Version:
 </para>

 <orderedlist numeration="upperalpha" spacing="normal">
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Use in the Title Page (and on the covers, if any) a title distinct from
    that of the Document, and from those of previous versions (which should, if
    there were any, be listed in the History section of the Document). You may
    use the same title as a previous version if the original publisher of that
    version gives permission.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    List on the Title Page, as authors, one or more persons or entities
    responsible for authorship of the modifications in the Modified Version,
    together with at least five of the principal authors of the Document (all
    of its principal authors, if it has fewer than five), unless they release
    you from this requirement.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    State on the Title page the name of the publisher of the Modified Version,
    as the publisher.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve all the copyright notices of the Document.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Add an appropriate copyright notice for your modifications adjacent to the
    other copyright notices.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Include, immediately after the copyright notices, a license notice giving
    the public permission to use the Modified Version under the terms of this
    License, in the form shown in the Addendum below.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve in that license notice the full lists of Invariant Sections and
    required Cover Texts given in the Document's license notice.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Include an unaltered copy of this License.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve the section Entitled "History", Preserve its Title, and add to it
    an item stating at least the title, year, new authors, and publisher of the
    Modified Version as given on the Title Page. If there is no section
    Entitled "History" in the Document, create one stating the title, year,
    authors, and publisher of the Document as given on its Title Page, then add
    an item describing the Modified Version as stated in the previous sentence.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve the network location, if any, given in the Document for public
    access to a Transparent copy of the Document, and likewise the network
    locations given in the Document for previous versions it was based on.
    These may be placed in the "History" section. You may omit a network
    location for a work that was published at least four years before the
    Document itself, or if the original publisher of the version it refers to
    gives permission.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    For any section Entitled "Acknowledgements" or "Dedications", Preserve the
    Title of the section, and preserve in the section all the substance and
    tone of each of the contributor acknowledgements and/or dedications given
    therein.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve all the Invariant Sections of the Document, unaltered in their
    text and in their titles. Section numbers or the equivalent are not
    considered part of the section titles.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Delete any section Entitled "Endorsements". Such a section may not be
    included in the Modified Version.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Do not retitle any existing section to be Entitled "Endorsements" or to
    conflict in title with any Invariant Section.
   </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>
    Preserve any Warranty Disclaimers.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>

 <para>
  If the Modified Version includes new front-matter sections or appendices that
  qualify as Secondary Sections and contain no material copied from the
  Document, you may at your option designate some or all of these sections as
  invariant. To do this, add their titles to the list of Invariant Sections in
  the Modified Version's license notice. These titles must be distinct from any
  other section titles.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may add a section Entitled "Endorsements", provided it contains nothing
  but endorsements of your Modified Version by various parties--for example,
  statements of peer review or that the text has been approved by an
  organization as the authoritative definition of a standard.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may add a passage of up to five words as a Front-Cover Text, and a
  passage of up to 25 words as a Back-Cover Text, to the end of the list of
  Cover Texts in the Modified Version. Only one passage of Front-Cover Text and
  one of Back-Cover Text may be added by (or through arrangements made by) any
  one entity. If the Document already includes a cover text for the same cover,
  previously added by you or by arrangement made by the same entity you are
  acting on behalf of, you may not add another; but you may replace the old
  one, on explicit permission from the previous publisher that added the old
  one.
 </para>

 <para>
  The author(s) and publisher(s) of the Document do not by this License give
  permission to use their names for publicity for or to assert or imply
  endorsement of any Modified Version.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    5. COMBINING DOCUMENTS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may combine the Document with other documents released under this
  License, under the terms defined in section 4 above for modified versions,
  provided that you include in the combination all of the Invariant Sections of
  all of the original documents, unmodified, and list them all as Invariant
  Sections of your combined work in its license notice, and that you preserve
  all their Warranty Disclaimers.
 </para>

 <para>
  The combined work need only contain one copy of this License, and multiple
  identical Invariant Sections may be replaced with a single copy. If there are
  multiple Invariant Sections with the same name but different contents, make
  the title of each such section unique by adding at the end of it, in
  parentheses, the name of the original author or publisher of that section if
  known, or else a unique number. Make the same adjustment to the section
  titles in the list of Invariant Sections in the license notice of the
  combined work.
 </para>

 <para>
  In the combination, you must combine any sections Entitled "History" in the
  various original documents, forming one section Entitled "History"; likewise
  combine any sections Entitled "Acknowledgements", and any sections Entitled
  "Dedications". You must delete all sections Entitled "Endorsements".
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    6. COLLECTIONS OF DOCUMENTS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may make a collection consisting of the Document and other documents
  released under this License, and replace the individual copies of this
  License in the various documents with a single copy that is included in the
  collection, provided that you follow the rules of this License for verbatim
  copying of each of the documents in all other respects.
 </para>

 <para>
  You may extract a single document from such a collection, and distribute it
  individually under this License, provided you insert a copy of this License
  into the extracted document, and follow this License in all other respects
  regarding verbatim copying of that document.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    7. AGGREGATION WITH INDEPENDENT WORKS
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  A compilation of the Document or its derivatives with other separate and
  independent documents or works, in or on a volume of a storage or
  distribution medium, is called an "aggregate" if the copyright resulting from
  the compilation is not used to limit the legal rights of the compilation's
  users beyond what the individual works permit. When the Document is included
  in an aggregate, this License does not apply to the other works in the
  aggregate which are not themselves derivative works of the Document.
 </para>

 <para>
  If the Cover Text requirement of section 3 is applicable to these copies of
  the Document, then if the Document is less than one half of the entire
  aggregate, the Document's Cover Texts may be placed on covers that bracket
  the Document within the aggregate, or the electronic equivalent of covers if
  the Document is in electronic form. Otherwise they must appear on printed
  covers that bracket the whole aggregate.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    8. TRANSLATION
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  Translation is considered a kind of modification, so you may distribute
  translations of the Document under the terms of section 4. Replacing
  Invariant Sections with translations requires special permission from their
  copyright holders, but you may include translations of some or all Invariant
  Sections in addition to the original versions of these Invariant Sections.
  You may include a translation of this License, and all the license notices in
  the Document, and any Warranty Disclaimers, provided that you also include
  the original English version of this License and the original versions of
  those notices and disclaimers. In case of a disagreement between the
  translation and the original version of this License or a notice or
  disclaimer, the original version will prevail.
 </para>

 <para>
  If a section in the Document is Entitled "Acknowledgements", "Dedications",
  or "History", the requirement (section 4) to Preserve its Title (section 1)
  will typically require changing the actual title.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    9. TERMINATION
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  You may not copy, modify, sublicense, or distribute the Document except as
  expressly provided for under this License. Any other attempt to copy, modify,
  sublicense or distribute the Document is void, and will automatically
  terminate your rights under this License. However, parties who have received
  copies, or rights, from you under this License will not have their licenses
  terminated so long as such parties remain in full compliance.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    10. FUTURE REVISIONS OF THIS LICENSE
  </bridgehead>

 <para>
  The Free Software Foundation may publish new, revised versions of the GNU
  Free Documentation License from time to time. Such new versions will be
  similar in spirit to the present version, but may differ in detail to address
  new problems or concerns. See
  <link xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xlink:href="https://www.gnu.org/copyleft/"/>.
 </para>

 <para>
  Each version of the License is given a distinguishing version number. If the
  Document specifies that a particular numbered version of this License "or any
  later version" applies to it, you have the option of following the terms and
  conditions either of that specified version or of any later version that has
  been published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation. If the
  Document does not specify a version number of this License, you may choose
  any version ever published (not as a draft) by the Free Software Foundation.
 </para>

 <bridgehead renderas="sect4">
    ADDENDUM: How to use this License for your documents
  </bridgehead>

<screen>Copyright (c) YEAR YOUR NAME.
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document
under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.2
or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation;
with no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts.
A copy of the license is included in the section entitled &#x201C;GNU
Free Documentation License&#x201D;.</screen>

 <para>
  If you have Invariant Sections, Front-Cover Texts and Back-Cover Texts,
  replace the &#x201C;with...Texts.&#x201D; line with this:
 </para>

<screen>with the Invariant Sections being LIST THEIR TITLES, with the
Front-Cover Texts being LIST, and with the Back-Cover Texts being LIST.</screen>

 <para>
  If you have Invariant Sections without Cover Texts, or some other combination
  of the three, merge those two alternatives to suit the situation.
 </para>

 <para>
  If your document contains nontrivial examples of program code, we recommend
  releasing these examples in parallel under your choice of free software
  license, such as the GNU General Public License, to permit their use in free
  software.
</para>
</appendix>
</article>
