<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="about-fqdn"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>About the FQDN</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
FQDN stands for Fully Qualified Domain Name. A FQDN is a domain name that specifies its exact location in the tree hierarchy of the DNS (Domain Name System).
It is absolute which means it provides every label from the specific host up to the DNS root zone.
</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
<para>An FQDN consists of two main parts; the hostname and the domain name. It is structured from the most specific label,on the left, to the most general which in on the right.</para>
<para>For example, <literal>mail.google.com.</literal>:</para>
<itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Hostname:</emphasis><literal>mail</literal>identifies a specific server or service, in this case, it is the server handling email.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Subdomain:</emphasis><literal>google</literal>is the specific organization or network.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Top-Level Domain:</emphasis><literal>com</literal>is the general category (commercial).</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Trailing Dot:</emphasis><literal>.</literal>is the root zone. While we usually leave it off when typing in a browser, a true FQDN technically ends with a dot. This signals that the name is absolute and not relative to another domain.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>A hostname and FQDN are distinctly different because they serve different functions in a networked environment.
A hostname is a simple human readable label assigned to a device on a local network. It is relative because it only identifies the machine within its immediate sub-network.
A FQDN is the absolute and unambiguous address of that host on the internet. It combines the hostname with the full domain hierarchy.
</para>
<section xml:id="imp-fqdn">
<title>Importance of FQDNs</title>
<para>FQDNs serve a number of important functions:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para>By mapping a distinct hostname to its full parent domain hierarchy, FQDNs eliminate the ambiguity inherent in local naming conventions, ensuring that every asset can be precisely located and accessed across the global Internet.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>In an email address, the portion following the <literal>@</literal> symbol represents the FQDN (or a domain that resolves to one) of the destination mail server.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>In web hosting, FQDNs serve as the definitive addresses that map user requests to specific web servers, enabling browsers to locate and retrieve precise web pages within the global DNS structure.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>DNS serves as the internet's directory by translating human-readable names into machine-accessible IP addresses to facilitate cross-network communication. FQDNs are the essential components of this process, providing the absolute, unambiguous paths required for DNS queries and responses to accurately resolve hostnames to their specific numerical destinations.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
<section xml:id="usage-fqdn">
  <title>Why you need FQDNs?</title>
  <para>Some of the use case scenarios include:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para>To make a device accessible over the internet, a FQDN is required. You have to use the FQDN to configure your DNS records, which maps the domain name to the device's static IP address. </para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>An FQDN is also a prerequisite for SSL certification. To meet current web security standards, you must use a verified domain name to issue and manage your site’s encryption certificates. </para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>In large-scale networking, FQDNs are indispensable for segmenting and managing complex environments.They provide a hierarchical structure that allows administrators to organize traffic into distinct and secure zones.
  By using specific host names within a structured domain hierarchy, organizations can implement granular access controls and streamline service discovery, ensuring that data flows efficiently and remains isolated within its intended network segment. </para></listitem>
 <listitem><para>Whether you are establishing a connection for FTP file transfers or configuring email services for specific applications, a FQDN or IP address is required to properly route and authenticate the traffic.</para></listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="certs-fqdn">
    <title>About FQDNs and SSL/TLS certificates</title>
    <para>A FQDN is a fundamental requirement for obtaining SSL/TLS certificates, which safeguard online communications by encrypting data transmitted between servers and clients.
      By providing a specific FQDN to a Certificate Authority (CA), you ensure the resulting certificate is mathematically bound to your exact domain, authenticating your site's identity and preventing unauthorized third parties from intercepting or spoofing your traffic.</para>
<para>Without a valid FQDN, browsers cannot validate the site’s security credentials, making it impossible to establish the trusted, encrypted tunnel necessary for modern web safety and data privacy.</para>
    </section>
</topic>