<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="concept-about-system-tuning"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>System tuning concepts and tools</title><!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
    <!--add author's email address-->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract><!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
      <para>
      System tuning is the process of monitoring, analyzing and adjusting operating system parameters to optimize hardware resource allocation for specific application workloads. By leveraging tools like <command>tuned</command> and <command>cpupower</command>, administrators can balance throughput, latency and power consumption to ensure the infrastructure operates at maximum efficiency.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    System tuning is optimizing operating system parameters and hardware configurations to achieve peak performance for specific workloads. It involves a systematic approach of monitoring resource utilization—such as CPU, memory, I/O, and network bandwidth—identifying bottlenecks, and adjusting kernel variables or service settings. Rather than a one-time setup, tuning is an iterative lifecycle of benchmarking and refinement, ensuring that the infrastructure provides the highest possible throughput and lowest latency for the applications it hosts.
    </para>
    <para>System tuning is managed through the <command>tuned</command> daemon and the <command>cpupower</command> infrastructure. &productnameshort; provides a variety of pre-defined tuning profiles designed for common scenarios, such as <literal>throughput-performance</literal> for heavy computation or <literal>latency-performance</literal> for real-time responsiveness. Administrators can use the <command>tuned-adm</command> tool to switch between these profiles dynamically, allowing the system to adapt its power management and kernel scheduling policies without requiring a manual reboot or deep expertise in <filename>/proc</filename> and <filename>/sys</filename> file system internals.</para>
</topic>