<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="ansible-intro"
 role="reference" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to Ansible core</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Ansible is an open-source IT automation engine that automates provisioning, configuration management, application deployment and other IT processes.
        It is simple and has agent less architecture, which means it does not require any special software installed on the machines it manages.
      It operates on the following concepts: </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Control node:</emphasis> The machine where Ansible is installed and executed. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Managed Nodes:</emphasis> The target servers or devices that Ansible manages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Inventory:</emphasis> A file that defines and groups your managed nodes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Modules:</emphasis> The code or binaries that Ansible copies to and executes on each managed node to accomplish the action defined in each task.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Tasks:</emphasis> A single execution of an Ansible module on a managed node.
           </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Playbooks:</emphasis> YAML files that contain an ordered list of tasks and define the desired state of your systems.
       </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
             <emphasis>Collections:</emphasis> Organized into a specific directory structure and includes roles, modules, playbooks,
             and plugins.</para>
            </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Roles:</emphasis> Structured ways to organize playbooks and other related files for reusability.
           </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <important><para>
  <emphasis role="bold">Core</emphasis> refers to the fundamental engine and capabilities like the Ansible parser and execution environment required to perform basic tasks.
  <emphasis role="bold">Automation built on top of core</emphasis> utilizes these fundamental capabilities such as Ansible Modules
  and structures them into linear and repeatable sequences of tasks, often within a single system or domain, for example a playbook to deploy a web server.
  <emphasis role="bold">Orchestration</emphasis> is the highest level, acting as a conductor that coordinates multiple, independent automation sequences and systems
  (like Ansible Playbooks, cloud APIs, and monitoring tools) with complex, cross-domain dependencies, conditional logic and state management to achieve a large, end-to-end business workflow.
  An example is deploying a complete multi-tier application across hybrid infrastructure.
      </para></important>
     </topic>
