<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="ansible-intro"
 role="reference" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to Ansible core</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Ansible is an open-source IT automation engine that automates provisioning, configuration management, application deployment and other IT processes.
        It is simple and has agent less architecture, which means no dedicated connection software is required on the managed nodes.
      It operates on the following concepts: </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <emphasis>Control node:</emphasis> The machine where Ansible is installed and executed. </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Managed Nodes:</emphasis> The target servers or devices that Ansible manages.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Inventory:</emphasis> A file that defines and groups your managed nodes.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Module:</emphasis> A small program that performs actions on a managed node.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Task:</emphasis> A single execution of an Ansible module on a managed node.
           </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Playbooks:</emphasis> Ansible Playbooks provide a repeatable, reusable, simple configuration management and multi-machine deployment system.
       </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
             <emphasis>Collection:</emphasis> A Collection of Ansible roles or modules focusing on a specific area.</para>
            </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
           <emphasis>Role:</emphasis> A standard, self-contained and portable unit of automation that organizes related tasks, variables and files into a predictable directory structure for easy reuse.
           </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <important>
        <itemizedlist>
     <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Ansible Core</emphasis> is the foundational software package that includes command-line tools like <literal>ansible</literal> and <literal>ansible-playbook</literal> and the execution engine.
  It provides the essential libraries and basic modules needed to connect to managed nodes and execute tasks. </para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Ansible automation components</emphasis> are the content that defines the logic, packaged into playbooks, roles and collections.
  These assets provide the instructions for the core engine, with collections serving as a distribution format that bundles reusable roles, modules and plugins. </para></listitem>
 <listitem><para> <emphasis role="bold">Ansible Orchestration</emphasis> is handled by higher-level tools that provide a UI, API and workflow engine to centrally manage and visually chain multiple automation playbooks together for complex multi-system processes.</para>
   </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </important>
     </topic>
