<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="concept-about-cgroups"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>About Kernel Control groups</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>Kernel control groups provide a hierarchical framework for organizing processes to strictly monitor, isolate, and limit their consumption of system resources like CPU, memory, and I/O.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
   Every process is assigned to exactly one administrative control group (cgroup). These cgroups are organized into a unified hierarchical tree structure, allowing you to manage resource allocation for individual processes or entire branches of the hierarchy simultaneously. You can define specific limitations for system resources, including CPU, Memory, Disk I/O, and Network Bandwidth.</para>
  <para>
   On &productnameshort;, &systemd; serves as the primary manager for cgroups, organizing all processes into logical units called slices. This integration provides a consistent interface for monitoring and setting resource properties across the OS.</para>
 <para>To visualize your current system organization, use the <literal>systemd-cgls</literal> command to display the hierarchy tree.</para>
<section><title>The Modern Unified Hierarchy (cgroup v2)</title>
  <para>The Linux kernel previously supported two API variants (v1 and v2). &productnameshort; exclusively utilizes the unified (v2) hierarchy as the default and recommended mode.</para>
  <variablelist><varlistentry><term>Unified (v2)</term>
  <listitem><para>A single hierarchy where all resource controllers are managed under a unified structure, providing better consistency and easier resource accounting.</para></listitem>
  </varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Hybrid/Legacy (v1)</term>
<listitem><para>In this mode controllers are spread across multiple v1 hierarchies—is considered legacy in &productnameshort; .</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>
<section><title>Legacy cgroup Support</title>
<para><literal>cgroup v1</literal> is functionally obsolete in SLES 16.0. Many modern system features and container runtimes now require the unified v2 hierarchy to operate correctly. Use of the legacy mode should be restricted to environments with strict requirements for aging, incompatible applications.</para>
<para>To force the system into the legacy hybrid hierarchy, you must append systemd.unified_cgroup_hierarchy=0 as a kernel command-line parameter in the GRUB 2 boot loader. For detailed instructions on modifying boot parameters, refer to the &productnameshort; Administration Guide.</para>
</section>
</topic>
