<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="concept-about-cgroups"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to Control Groups</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>Kernel control groups provide a hierarchical framework for organizing processes to monitor, isolate, and limit their consumption of system resources like CPU, memory, and I/O.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
   Every process is assigned to exactly one administrative control group (cgroup). These cgroups
   are organized into a unified hierarchical tree structure, allowing you to manage resource
   allocation for individual processes or entire branches of the hierarchy simultaneously. You can
   define specific limitations for system resources.</para>
   <section xml:id="systemd-slices">
    <title>The role of &systemd; slices</title>
    <para>
   On &productname;, &systemd; serves as the primary manager for cgroups. Instead of requiring
   administrators to interact with the raw cgroup file system manually, &systemd; abstracts this
   management by organizing all processes into logical units called slices
   (<literal>.slice</literal> units).</para>
   <para>
    This integration bridges the gap between &systemd; service management and the kernel's resource tracking through several key mechanisms:
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Direct hierarchical mapping</emphasis>: Slices represent inner nodes in a tree that maps directly onto the kernel’s cgroup directory structure</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Built-in partitioning</emphasis>: By default, systemd
      automatically organizes the operating system into distinct root slices to prevent workloads
      from interfering with each other. &systemd; uses these root slices:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>system.slice</literal> for services
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>user.slice</literal> for user sessions
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>machine.slice</literal> for managing resources of virtual machines 
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            <literal>init.scope</literal> to host the PID1 process itself
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </listitem>    
   </itemizedlist>
 <para>To visualize your current system organization, use the <literal>systemd-cgls</literal> command to display the hierarchy tree.</para>
   </section>
  
<section><title>The unified hierarchy (cgroup v2)</title>
  <para>The Linux kernel previously supported two API variants (v1 and v2). &productnameshort; exclusively utilizes the unified (v2) hierarchy as the default and recommended mode.</para>
  <variablelist><varlistentry><term>Unified hierarchy (cgroup v2)</term>
  <listitem><para>A single hierarchy where all resource controllers are managed under a unified structure, providing better consistency and easier resource accounting.</para></listitem>
  </varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Hybrid/Legacy cgroup support (v1)</term>
<listitem><para><literal>cgroup v1</literal> is functionally obsolete and unsupported in
&productname; &productnumber;. If cgroup v1 needs to be used, switch to older &productnameshort; releases.</para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</section>

</topic>
