<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="concept-cockpit-applications"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
 <info> <title>Managing applications in &cockpit;</title> <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/> <abstract> <para>The &cockpit; Web interface supports modularity through plug-in applications. This section describes how to view, navigate and remove these applications using the <guilabel>Applications</guilabel> page. </para> </abstract> </info>
<para>&cockpit; applications (or modules) extend the functionality of the Web interface. Adding an application creates a new entry in the sidebar, allowing you to manage complex system services—such as firewalls, virtual machines or SELinux—through a visual interface rather than the command line.</para>
  <para>Commonly installed modules include: <guimenu>Networking</guimenu>, <guimenu>Software Updates (Packages)</guimenu>, <guimenu>Repositories</guimenu> and <guimenu>SELinux</guimenu>.</para>
<section><title>Viewing and navigating applications</title>
<para>You can access your installed modules by clicking the <guimenu>Applications</guimenu> tab in the left-hand navigation pane and clicking the application's name to switch to its dedicated management tab. To uninstall a module, locate the application in the list and click the <guimenu>Remove</guimenu> button.</para>
</section>
<section><title>Troubleshooting missing applications</title>
<para>If the <guilabel>Applications</guilabel> page is empty, or if a newly installed module does not appear in the list, you may need to refresh the &cockpit; service.</para>
<para>Restart the socket: Run the following command in your terminal: </para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo; systemctl restart cockpit.socket</screen>
<para>Check for service failures: If a specific service fails to start, the <guilabel>Applications</guilabel> page will display the relevant systemd error logs directly on the screen to assist with debugging.</para>
</section></topic>
