<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="concept-cockpit-packages"
role="concept" xml:lang="en"
xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
<info>
<title>Managing packages using &cockpit;</title>
<meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
<abstract>
<para>
&cockpit; enables you to view the list of packages available to install, reinstall, and uninstall in a single web interface.
</para>
</abstract>
</info>
<para>The <guilabel>Packages</guilabel> tab communicates with the <filename>PackageKit</filename> to install, uninstall, or search for packages, and integrate logs.</para>
<note><para>The <guilabel>Packages</guilabel> plugin is not available for the transactional system.</para></note>
<para>The list of available packages appear in the <guilabel>Packages</guilabel> tab and you can reinstall or uninstall the packages. You can view the package name, package version number, and a short description of the package in this tab. If an update fails due to a conflict, the <guilabel>Packages</guilabel> tab shows the technical details in web interface so that you need not manually verify the <filename>/var/log/zypp/history</filename>.</para>
<itemizedlist>
    <listitem><para>To install a package by initiating zypper in the background and downloading the required packages, click the <guilabel>Install</guilabel> toggle button.</para>
    <para>Specify the package name in the <guilabel>Find by name</guilabel> search box. The list of packages matching the search appears.</para>
         <para>Click the <guimenu>Install</guimenu> or <guilabel>Reinstall</guilabel> button and then click the <guilabel>Install</guilabel> button again to confirm installation.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>To uninstall a package, click the <guimenu>Uninstall</guimenu> toggle button and then click the <guimenu>Uninstall</guimenu> button corresponding to the package and click <guimenu>OK</guimenu> to confirm uninstalling the package.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>


</topic>