<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="concept-cockpit-authentication"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>&cockpit; authentication</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="jsindelarova@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        You do not need separate credentials to log in to &cockpit;. You can
        use the same credentials that you use to log in to &productnameshort;. On top of
        that, &cockpit; enables you to log in to other servers without
        accessing them directly.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <tip os="alp-dolomite">
    <title>Access &cockpit; as a non-privileged user</title>
    <para>
      It is a good practice to create a non-privileged user
      account&mdash;preferably during &productnameshort; deployment&mdash;and
      primarily log in as such user. The same applies to logging in to
      &cockpit;. If you need <emphasis>Administrative access</emphasis> in
      &cockpit;, click <guimenu>Limited access</guimenu> in the top right menu
      and unlock it by entering &rootuser; password.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <para>
    &cockpit; enables you to log in directly to each machine that can expose the
    9090 port. This machine is sometimes referred to as the primary server. It
    is the primary server that runs the <literal>cockpit-ws</literal> through
    which connections to additional servers are established.
  </para>
  <para>
    If the port cannot be accessed on the particular machine, you can still use
    &cockpit; to administer the machine by using it as a secondary server. For a
    procedure of adding a server as secondary, refer to
    <xref linkend="cockpit-logging-adding-secondary"/>.
  </para>
  <note>
    <title>A limited number of secondary servers</title>
    <para>
      The number of secondary servers that you can administer from one primary
      server is limited to 20. If you need to administer more servers, add
      other primary servers or use another tool for cluster administration.
    </para>
  </note>
</topic>
