<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="copy-file-using-rsync-concept"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>The rsync concept</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Files stored in multiple devices or directories must be in synchronization with each other to ensure accuracy and maintainability of data. rsync is a tool used for transferring or copying files locally and remotely. rsync is unidirectional and it copies files only in one direction, it does not synchronize data. 
Instead of transmitting all the contents in the file, rsync minimizes the amount of data copied by moving only the changes within the file. Hence, this supports transfer of data over slow network connection.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>To use rsync for large files, detecting changes requires certain computing power. So ensure that machines on both source and destination have enough resources, including RAM. </para>
<para>You can use rsync when large amounts of data containing only minor changes need to be transmitted regularly. Hence, this is useful when working with backups. rsync can also be useful for mirroring staging servers that store complete directory trees of Web servers to a Web server in a DMZ.</para>
<para>This article includes examples that shows the usage of the rsync command to copy files locally and remotely. This document also explains how to configure and use an rsync server.</para>
</topic>
