<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="freeradius-concept-server"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>About FreeRADIUS</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        The RADIUS (Remote Authentication Dial-In User Service) protocol is a standard service for managing network access. FreeRADIUS is the open source RADIUS server implementation and the most widely used RADIUS server.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>FreeRADIUS verifies users and clients and manages network access and operations. FreeRADIUS ensures secure communication between network devices and user authentication servers.</para>
<para>FreeRADIUS performs authentication, authorization and accounting (AAA) for very large businesses such as Internet service providers and cellular network providers, and is also popular for small networks. It authenticates users and devices, authorizes those users and devices for certain network services, and tracks the use of services for billing and auditing. You do not have to use all three of the AAA protocols, use only the ones you need.
</para>
<para>
  RADIUS operates over a distributed architecture and runs separately from the Network Access Server (NAS). User access data is stored on a central RADIUS server that is available to multiple NAS devices. The NAS provides physical access to the network, such as a managed Ethernet switch or a wireless access point. FreeRADIUS verifies and manages network access and operations. FreeRADIUS ensures secure communication between network devices and user authentication servers. To set up a FreeRADIUS server, you must install, configure and define user accounts, and define and determine authentication and authorization for FreeRADIUS. After installing FreeRADIUS, you must test the function by integrating FreeRADIUS with the devices to be managed.
</para>
<figure>
  <title>FreeRADIUS Architecture</title>
  <mediaobject>
    <imageobject role="pdf">
      <imagedata fileref="freeradius-setup-server-architecture.png" width="70%"/>
    </imageobject>
    <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="freeradius-setup-server-architecture.png" width="75%"/>
    </imageobject>
  </mediaobject>
</figure>
<para>This article includes an example that shows installing FreeRADIUS, creating a set of test certificates, starting the server, adding client server and user, testing authentication, and testing multiple clients.</para>
</topic>
