<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_concepts.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-core-concepts"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Core concepts</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
       This section explains the core concepts of &sleha;.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-cluster-nodes">
    <title>Clusters and nodes</title>
    <para>
      A <emphasis>high-availability</emphasis> cluster is a group of servers that work together to
      ensure the availability of applications or services. Servers that are configured as members of
      the cluster are called <emphasis>nodes</emphasis>. If one node fails, the resources running on
      it can move to another node in the cluster. &sleha; supports clusters with up to 32 nodes.
      However, clusters usually fall into one of two categories: two-node clusters, or clusters with
      an odd number of nodes (typically three or five).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-communication-channels">
    <title>Communication channels</title>
    <para>
      Internal cluster communication is handled by <emphasis>&corosync;</emphasis>. The &cce;
      is a group communication system that provides messaging, membership and quorum information
      about the cluster. In &sleha; 16, &corosync; uses kronosnet (<literal>knet</literal>)
      as the default transport protocol.
    </para>
    <para>
      We highly recommend configuring at least two communication channels for the cluster. The preferred
      method is to use network device bonding. If you cannot use a network bond, you can set up a
      redundant communication channel in &corosync; (also known as a second <quote>ring</quote>).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-resource-management">
    <title>Resource management</title>
    <para>
      In a High Availability cluster, the applications and services that need to be highly available
      are called <emphasis>resources</emphasis>. Cluster resources can include Web sites, e-mail
      servers, databases, file systems, virtual machines and any other server-based applications or
      services you want to make available to users at all times. You can start, stop, monitor and
      move resources as needed. You can also specify whether specific resources should run
      together on the same node, or start and stop in sequential order. If a cluster node fails,
      the resources running on it <emphasis>fail over</emphasis> (move) to another node instead of
      being lost.
    </para>
    <para>
      In &sleha;, the <emphasis>cluster resource manager</emphasis> (CRM) is
      <emphasis>&pace;</emphasis>, which manages and coordinates all cluster services. &pace; uses
      <emphasis>resource agents</emphasis> (RAs) to start, stop and monitor resources. A resource
      agent abstracts the resource it manages and presents its status to the cluster. &sleha;
      supports many different resource agents that are designed to manage specific types of
      applications or services.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-node-fencing">
    <title>Node fencing</title>
    <xi:include href="../snippets/ha-fencing.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="../snippets/ha-stonith.xml"/>
  </section>

 <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-quorum-calculation">
    <title>Quorum calculation</title>
    <xi:include href="../snippets/ha-quorum.xml"/>
    <para>
      &corosync; calculates quorum based on the following formula:
    </para>
<screen>N ≥ C/2 + 1

N = minimum number of operational nodes
C = number of cluster nodes</screen>
    <para>
      For example, a five-node cluster needs a minimum of three operational nodes to maintain quorum.
    </para>
    <para>
      Clusters with an even number of nodes, especially two-node clusters, might have equal
      numbers of nodes in each partition and therefore no majority. To avoid this situation,
      you can configure the cluster to use &qdevice; in combination with &qnet;. &qnet; is an
      <emphasis>arbitrator</emphasis> running outside the cluster. It communicates with the
      &qdevice; daemon running on the cluster nodes to provide a configurable number of votes for
      quorum calculation. This lets a cluster sustain more node failures than the standard quorum
      rules allow.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-storage-data-replication">
    <title>Storage and data replication</title>
    <para>
      &ha; clusters might include a shared disk subsystem connected via Fibre Channel or iSCSI. If
      a node fails, another node in the cluster automatically mounts the shared disk directories
      that were previously mounted on the failed node. This gives users continuous access to the
      directories on the shared disk subsystem. Content stored on the shared disk might include
      data, applications and services.
    </para>
    <para>
       The following figure shows what a typical Fibre Channel cluster configuration might look like.
       The green lines depict connections to an Ethernet power switch, which can reboot a node if a
       ping request fails.
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="ha-example-shared-storage-fibre-channel">
      <title>Typical Fibre Channel cluster configuration</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-fibre-channel.svg" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-fibre-channel.svg" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject role="description">
          <phrase>
            This diagram shows shared storage connected to a Fibre Channel switch. The switch is
            then connected to six servers. Each of the six servers is also connected to a network
            hub, which is then connected to an Ethernet power switch.
          </phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      The following figure shows what a typical iSCSI cluster configuration might look like.
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="ha-example-shared-storage-iscsi">
      <title>Typical iSCSI cluster configuration</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-iscsi.svg" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-iscsi.svg" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject role="description">
          <phrase>
            This diagram shows shared storage connected to an Ethernet switch. The switch is
            then connected to six servers. Each of the six servers is also connected to a network
            hub, which is then connected to an Ethernet power switch and backed by a network backbone.
          </phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Although most clusters include a shared disk subsystem, you can also create a cluster without
      a shared disk subsystem. The following figure shows what a cluster without a shared disk
      subsystem might look like.
    </para>
    <figure xml:id="ha-example-no-shared-storage">
      <title>Typical cluster configuration without shared storage</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
        <imagedata fileref="ha-example-no-shared-storage.svg" width="90%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
        <imagedata fileref="ha-example-no-shared-storage.svg" width="80%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <textobject role="description">
          <phrase>
            This diagram shows an Ethernet power switch connected to a network hub. The hub is
            then connected to six servers.
          </phrase>
        </textobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</topic>
