<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_concepts.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-core-concepts"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>&sleha; core concepts</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
       This section explains the core concepts of a &sleha; cluster. This is about broad concepts, not specific architectural components.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-cluster-nodes">
    <title>Cluster nodes</title>
    <para>Clusters usually fall into one of two categories:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>Two-node clusters</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Clusters with more than two nodes. This usually means an odd number of nodes.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
              &sleha; supports different geographical scenarios,
    <!--including &geo.dispersed; clusters (&geo; clusters)-->.
   </para>
   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Local clusters</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A single cluster in one location (for example, all nodes are located
       in one data center). The cluster manages failover internally.
       Network latency is negligible. Storage is typically accessed
       synchronously by all nodes.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Metro clusters</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       A single cluster that can stretch over multiple buildings or data
       centers, with all sites connected by Fibre Channel. The cluster manages
       failover internally. Network latency is usually low (&lt;5&nbsp;ms for
       distances of approximately 20 miles). Storage is frequently
       replicated (mirroring or synchronous replication).
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <!--varlistentry>
     <term>&geo; clusters (multi-site clusters)</term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       Multiple, &geo.dispersed; sites with a local cluster each. The
       sites communicate via IP. Failover across the sites is coordinated by
       a higher-level entity. &geo; clusters need to cope with limited
       network bandwidth and high latency. Storage is replicated
       asynchronously.
      </para>
      <note>
       <title>Geo clustering and SAP workloads</title>
       <para>
        Currently &geo; clusters support neither &hana; system replication
        nor &s4h; and &nw; enqueue replication setups.
       </para>
      </note>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry-->
   </variablelist>
   <para>
    The greater the geographical distance between individual cluster nodes,
    the more factors may potentially disturb the high availability of
    services the cluster provides. Network latency, limited bandwidth and
    access to storage are the main challenges for long-distance clusters.
            </para>
      <para>
       We strongly recommend to use either a two-node cluster or an odd number
       of cluster nodes.
       Two-node clusters make sense for stretched setups across two sites.
       Clusters with an odd number of nodes can either be built on one single
       site or might be spread across three sites.
      </para>
   <para>
    The following use cases are the most common:
   </para>

   <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Two-node cluster in one location</term>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Configuration:</title>
       <para>FC SAN or similar shared storage, layer 2 network.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Usage scenario:</title>
       <para>Embedded clusters that focus on service high
       availability and not data redundancy for data replication.
       Such a setup is used for radio stations or assembly line controllers,
       for example.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Two-node clusters in two locations (most widely used)</term>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Configuration:</title>
       <para>Symmetrical stretched cluster, FC SAN, and layer 2 network
        all across two locations.</para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Usage scenario:</title>
       <para>Classic stretched clusters, focus on high availability of services
        and local data redundancy. For databases and enterprise
        resource planning. One of the most popular setups.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
     <term>Odd number of nodes in three locations</term>
     <listitem>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Configuration:</title>
       <para>2&times;N+1 nodes, FC SAN across two main locations. Auxiliary
        third site with no FC SAN, but acts as a majority maker.
        Layer 2 network at least across two main locations.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
      <formalpara>
       <title>Usage scenario:</title>
       <para>Classic stretched cluster, focus on high availability of services
        and data redundancy. For example, databases, enterprise resource planning.
       </para>
      </formalpara>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>
  </section>

    <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-communication-channels">
    <title>Communication channels</title>
    <para>
      For a supported cluster setup, two or more communication channels are required, using one of the following methods: network bonding (preferred), or creating a second communication channel in &corosync;.
    </para>
    <para>
      &sleha; uses knet as the default transport protocol.
    </para>
    <para>
      Redundant Ring Protocol (RRP) allows the use of multiple redundant local area networks for resilience against partial or total network faults. This way, cluster communication can still be kept up as long as a single network is operational. &corosync; supports the Totem Redundant Ring Protocol. A logical token-passing ring is imposed on all participating nodes to deliver messages in a reliable and sorted manner. A node is allowed to broadcast a message only if it holds the token.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-resource-management">
    <title>Resource management</title>
    <para>
      In a High Availability cluster, the applications and services that need to be highly available are called <emphasis>resources</emphasis>. Cluster resources can include Web sites, e-mail servers, databases, file systems, virtual machines and any other server-based applications or services you want to make available to users at all times.
    </para>
    <para>
      The cluster can start, stop, monitor and migrate resources as needed. You can also specify whether specific resources should run together on the same node, or start and stop in sequential order. If a cluster node fails, the resources running on it <emphasis>fail over</emphasis> (move) to another node instead of being lost.
    </para>
    <para>
      The cluster manages resources via <emphasis>resource agents</emphasis> (RAs). A resource agent abstracts the application or service it manages and presents its status to the cluster. The cluster relies on the resource agent to start, stop and monitor the resource. &sleha; supports many different resource agents that are designed to manage specific types of applications or services.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-node-fencing">
    <title>Node fencing</title>
    <para>
      In a <emphasis>split-brain scenario</emphasis>, cluster nodes are divided into two or more groups (or <emphasis>partitions</emphasis>) that do not know about each other. This might be because of a hardware or software failure, or because of a cut network connection, for example. A split-brain scenario can be resolved by <emphasis>fencing</emphasis> one or more of the nodes. Node-level fencing prevents a failed node from accessing shared resources and prevents cluster resources from running on a node with an uncertain status. This is usually done by resetting or powering off the node.
    </para>
    <para>
      In &sleha;, the node fencing mechanism is &stonith; (<quote>Shoot the other node in the head</quote>). To be supported, all &sleha; clusters <emphasis>must</emphasis> have at least one &stonith; device. This can be either a physical device (a power switch) or &sbd; (&sbd.long;) in combination with a watchdog. &sbd; can be used either with shared storage or in diskless mode.
    </para>
  </section>

 <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-quorum-determination">
    <title>Quorum determination</title>
    <para>
      When communication fails between one or more nodes and the rest of the cluster (a <emphasis>split-brain scenario</emphasis>), a cluster <emphasis>partition</emphasis> occurs. The nodes can only communicate with other nodes in the same partition and are unaware of the separated nodes. A cluster partition is defined as having <emphasis>quorum</emphasis> (or being <quote>quorate</quote>) if it has the majority of nodes (or <quote>votes</quote>). This is determined by <emphasis>quorum calculation</emphasis>. Quorum is a requirement for fencing.
    </para>
    <para>
      &corosync; calculates quorum based on the following formula:
    </para>
<screen>N ≥ C/2 + 1

N = minimum number of operational nodes
C = number of cluster nodes</screen>
    <para>
      For example, a five-node cluster needs a minimum of three operational nodes to maintain quorum.
    </para>
    <para>
      Clusters with an odd number of nodes can calculate quorum easily because one partition will have more nodes than the other partition. However, clusters with an even number of nodes, especially two-node clusters, might have equal numbers of nodes in each partition and therefore no majority. To avoid this situation, you can configure the cluster to use &qdevice; in combination with &qnet;. &qnet; is an <emphasis>arbitrator</emphasis> running outside the cluster. It communicates with the &qdevice; daemon running on the cluster nodes to provide a configurable number of votes for quorum calculation. This lets a cluster sustain more node failures than the standard quorum rules allow.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-core-concepts-storage-data-replication">
    <title>Storage and data replication</title>
    <para>
      &sleha; clusters might or might not include a shared disk subsystem. The shared disk subsystem
      can be connected via Fibre Channel or iSCSI. If a node fails, another designated node in the
      cluster automatically mounts the shared disk directories that were previously mounted on the
      failed node. This gives network users continuous access to the directories on the shared disk
      subsystem. Content stored on the shared disk might include data, applications and services.
    </para>
    <para>
       The following figure shows what a typical Fibre Channel cluster configuration might look like.
       The green lines depict connections to an Ethernet power switch, which can reboot a node if a
       ping request fails.
    </para>
    <figure>
    <title>Typical Fibre Channel cluster configuration</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-fibre-channel.svg" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-fibre-channel.svg" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="description">
        <phrase>
          This diagram shows shared storage connected to a Fibre Channel switch. The switch is
          then connected to six servers. Each of the six servers is also connected to a network hub,
          which is then connected to an Ethernet power switch.
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Although Fibre Channel provides the best performance, you can also configure your cluster to
      use iSCSI. The following figure shows what a typical iSCSI cluster configuration might look like.
    </para>
    <figure>
    <title>Typical iSCSI cluster configuration</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-iscsi.svg" width="100%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="ha-example-shared-storage-iscsi.svg" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="description">
        <phrase>
          This diagram shows shared storage connected to an Ethernet switch. The switch is
          then connected to six servers. Each of the six servers is also connected to a network hub,
          which is then connected to an Ethernet power switch and backed by a network backbone.
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Although most clusters include a shared disk subsystem, you can also create a cluster without
      a shared disk subsystem. The following figure shows what a cluster without a shared disk
      subsystem might look like.
    </para>
    <figure>
    <title>Typical cluster configuration without shared storage</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
      <imagedata fileref="ha-example-no-shared-storage.svg" width="90%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <imageobject role="html">
      <imagedata fileref="ha-example-no-shared-storage.svg" width="80%"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="description">
        <phrase>
          This diagram shows an Ethernet power switch connected to a network hub. The hub is
          then connected to six servers.
        </phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
</topic>
