<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_maintenance.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-overview"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Cluster maintenance modes and workflows</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
         To perform maintenance tasks on the cluster nodes, you might need to stop the resources running on that node, to move them, or to shut down or reboot the node. It might also be necessary to temporarily take over the control of resources from the cluster, or even to stop the cluster service while resources remain running.
         This chapter explains how to manually take down a cluster node without negative side-effects. It also gives an overview of different options the cluster stack provides for executing maintenance tasks. If you don't protect the cluster before performing maintenance tasks, you risk unwanted side effects such as resources not starting in an orderly fashion, unsynchronized CIBs across the cluster nodes, or even data loss.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-steps">
    <title>General workflow</title>
    <para>
      To do testing or maintenance work on the cluster, nodes or individual resources, follow these general steps:
   </para>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-ha-maintenance-workflow-steps">
      <step>
        <para>
          Determine the workflow you need, depending on your maintenance tasks.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Apply one or more administrative modes, depending on the workflow.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Perform your maintenance tasks or tests on the cluster, nodes or individual resources.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Put the cluster, node or resource back into <quote>normal</quote> operation.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-modes">
    <title>Administrative modes</title>
    <para>
      &sleha; has the following modes for protecting the cluster during maintenance tasks. Depending
      on your task, you might need to use one of these modes or a combination of multiple modes.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stopping the cluster services</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Stopping the cluster services means stopping &pace; and &corosync;. In this mode, the
            cluster is <emphasis>no longer running</emphasis>, either entirely or just on one node.
            Use this mode when you need to manage infrastructure, such as storage, networking or
            hardware.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For the whole cluster:</emphasis> Stopping the cluster
                services on all nodes at once allows you to shut down a cluster while avoiding
                the mass migration of resources that would happen if you shut down each node one
                by one. When this mode is used in combination with maintenance mode, the resources continue to run but have no cluster protection. When this mode is used on its own, all resources are stopped. However, this doesn't guarantee a graceful shutdown&mdash;if stopping a resource fails or times out, the node is fenced.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For one node:</emphasis> Stopping the cluster services on just one node allows the resources to move to another node. If no other node is eligible to run a resource, the resource stops. However, if stopping a resource fails or times out, the node is fenced. Therefore, we recommend using this mode in combination with standby mode or maintenance mode.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maintenance mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In maintenance mode, the cluster stops managing the resources and won't start, stop or
            monitor them. Use this mode when you need to manually manage applications or services
            without interference from the cluster. However, be aware that the resources won't have
            cluster protection while in maintenance mode.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For the whole cluster:</emphasis> Cluster maintenance mode
                puts <emphasis>all</emphasis> the resources into maintenance mode at once.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For one node:</emphasis> Node maintenance mode puts all the
                resources that are running on a specific node into maintenance mode at once.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For one resource:</emphasis> Resource maintenance mode puts
                a single resource into maintenance mode. You can also use this mode for resource
                groups and clones.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Standby mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When a <emphasis role="bold">node</emphasis> is in standby mode, it can't run resources.
            The resources move to another node. If no other node is eligible to run a resource,
            the resource stops. This mode is useful for gracefully evacuating a node before
            stopping the cluster services.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unmanaged mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When a <emphasis role="bold">resource</emphasis> is in unmanaged mode, the cluster
            won't start or stop it. However, unlike maintenance mode, the cluster still
            <emphasis>monitors</emphasis> the resource. Use this mode when you need to manually
            manage an application or service, but still want the cluster to report any failures.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-more-info">
    <title>For more information</title>
    <para>

    </para>
  </section>
</topic>
