<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_maintenance.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-overview"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Maintenance workflow overview</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
         To perform maintenance tasks on the cluster nodes, you might need to stop the resources running on that node, to move them, or to shut down or reboot the node. It might also be necessary to temporarily take over the control of resources from the cluster, or even to stop the cluster service while resources remain running.
         This chapter explains how to manually take down a cluster node without negative side-effects. It also gives an overview of different options the cluster stack provides for executing maintenance tasks.
      </para>
      <para>
        When you shut down or reboot a cluster node (or stop the cluster services on a node), the following processes are triggered:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          The resources that are running on the node are stopped or moved off the node.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          If stopping a resource fails or times out, the &stonith; mechanism fences the node and shuts it down.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-steps">
    <title>General workflow</title>
    <para>
    If you need to do testing or maintenance work, follow the general steps
    below.
   </para>
   <para>
    Otherwise, you risk unwanted side effects, like resources not starting in an
    orderly fashion, unsynchronized CIBs across the cluster nodes, or even data loss.
   </para>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-ha-maintenance-workflow-steps">
      <step>
        <para>
          Before you start, choose the appropriate option
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Apply this option with &hawk; or &crmsh;.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Execute your maintenance task or tests.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          After you have finished, put the resource, node or cluster back to <quote>normal</quote> operation.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-options">
    <title>Options</title>
    <para>
      &pace; offers the following options for performing system maintenance:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Putting the cluster in maintenance mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The global cluster property <literal>maintenance-mode</literal> puts all
      resources into maintenance state at once. The cluster stops monitoring them
      and becomes oblivious to their status. <emphasis>Only</emphasis> the resource management
      by &pace; is disabled. &corosync; and SBD are still functional. Use maintenance
      mode for any tasks involving cluster resources. For any tasks involving
      infrastructure, such as storage or networking, the safest method is to stop
      the cluster services completely.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stopping the cluster services for the whole cluster</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Stopping the cluster services on all nodes at once allows you to shut down
      a cluster while avoiding the mass migration of resources that would happen
      if you shut down each node one by one. Because there are no nodes to migrate
      to, all resources are stopped.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Putting a node in maintenance mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option allows you to put all resources running on a specific node into
      maintenance state at once. The cluster ceases monitoring them and
      becomes oblivious to their status.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Putting a node in standby mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A node that is in standby mode can no longer run resources. Any resources
      running on the node are moved away or stopped (if no other node
      is eligible to run the resource). Also, all monitoring operations are
      stopped on the node (except for those with
      <literal>role="Stopped"</literal>). You can use this option if you need to stop a node in a cluster while continuing to provide the services running on another node.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stopping the cluster services on a node</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            This option stops all the cluster services on a single node. Any resources
      running on the node are moved away or stopped (if no other node is
      eligible to run the resource). This is risky because if stopping a resource fails or times out,
      the node is fenced. Therefore, we recommend using standby or maintenance mode before stopping the cluster services on a node.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Putting a resource in maintenance mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When this mode is enabled for a resource, no monitoring operations are
      triggered for the resource. Use this option if you need to manually touch the service that is managed
      by this resource and do not want the cluster to run any monitoring
      operations for the resource during that time.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Putting a resource into unmanaged mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The <option>is-managed</option> meta attribute allows you to temporarily
      <quote>release</quote> a resource from being managed by the cluster
      stack. This means you can manually touch the service that is managed by
      this resource (for example, to adjust any components). However, the
      cluster continues to <emphasis>monitor</emphasis> the resource and to
      report any failures. If you want the cluster to also cease <emphasis>monitoring</emphasis> the
      resource, use the per-resource maintenance mode instead.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-more-info">
    <title>More information</title>
    <para>

    </para>
  </section>
</topic>
