<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>

<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sleha/blob/main/xml/ha_maintenance.xml -->

<topic xml:id="ha-maintenance-for-clusters"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Maintenance for &ha; clusters</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tahlia.richardson@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        While under &ha; cluster management, the application or service that a resource represents
        must <emphasis>not</emphasis> be started or stopped from outside the cluster. This means
        that if you need to manually touch a resource, you need to release it from cluster
        management first. Resources are also vulnerable if something goes wrong when you make
        changes to the cluster nodes or infrastructure. You must protect the cluster and its
        resources before performing maintenance tasks or you risk unwanted side effects such as
        resource failure, unsynchronized CIBs, or even data loss.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-basic-steps">
    <title>Basic steps</title>
    <para>
      These are the basic steps for performing any maintenance tasks in a &ha; cluster:
   </para>
    <procedure xml:id="pro-ha-maintenance-workflow-steps">
      <step>
        <para>
          Determine the workflow you need, depending on your maintenance tasks.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Apply one or more administrative modes, depending on the workflow.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Perform your maintenance tasks on the cluster, node or individual resource.
        </para>
      </step>
      <step>
        <para>
          Put the cluster, node or resource back into <quote>normal</quote> operation.
        </para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-modes">
    <title>Administrative modes</title>
    <para>
      &sleha; has the following modes for protecting the cluster during maintenance tasks. Depending
      on your task, you might need to use one of these modes or a combination of multiple modes.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stopping the cluster services</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Stopping the cluster services means stopping &pace; and &corosync;. In this mode, the
            cluster is <emphasis>no longer running</emphasis>, either entirely or just on one node.
            Use this mode when you need to manage infrastructure, such as storage or networking, or
            when you need to change the configuration of the cluster services.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For the whole cluster:</emphasis> Stopping the cluster
                services on all nodes at once allows you to shut down a cluster while avoiding
                the mass migration of resources that would happen if you shut down each node one
                by one. When this mode is used on its own, all the resources stop. However, this
                doesn't guarantee a graceful shutdown&mdash;if stopping a resource fails or
                times out, the resource's node is fenced. Alternatively, you can avoid resource
                downtime by using this mode in combination with maintenance mode.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For one node:</emphasis> Stopping the cluster services on
                just one node allows the rest of the cluster to continue running while you perform
                maintenance tasks on the offline node. The node's resources either move to another
                node, or stop if constraints prevent them from moving. However, if stopping a
                resource fails or times out, the node is fenced. To avoid attempting to stop
                resources and the cluster services at the same time, we recommend using this mode
                in combination with standby mode.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Maintenance mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            In maintenance mode, the cluster stops managing the resources and won't start, stop or
            monitor them. This allows you to manually manage applications or services without
            interference from the cluster. However, resources aren't highly available while in this
            mode, so they won't fail over to another node if the current node shuts down or reboots.
          </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For the whole cluster:</emphasis> Cluster maintenance mode
                puts <emphasis>all</emphasis> the resources into maintenance mode at once.
                If you stop or restart the cluster services while in this mode, most resources can
                continue to run even while the cluster is offline. This allows you to make cluster
                configuration changes with minimal resource downtime. However, any resources that
                depend on &corosync;, such as &dlm;, must be stopped.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For one node:</emphasis> Node maintenance mode puts all the
                resources that are running on a specific node into maintenance mode at once.
                <emphasis>Don't</emphasis> stop or restart the cluster services while in this mode.
                This can lead to concurrency violations, where resources mistakenly run on multiple
                nodes instead of only one node.
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">For one resource:</emphasis> Resource maintenance mode puts
                a single resource into maintenance mode. You can also put groups and clones into
                resource maintenance mode.
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Standby mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When a <emphasis role="bold">node</emphasis> is in standby mode, it can't run
            resources. Any resources that were running on it either move to another node, or
            stop if constraints prevent them from moving. Standby mode gives the resources more
            time to move or stop successfully because they aren't limited by the shutdown timeout
            of the cluster services. Therefore, this mode is useful for gracefully evacuating a
            node before stopping the cluster services or rebooting the node.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Unmanaged mode</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            When a <emphasis role="bold">resource</emphasis> is in unmanaged mode, the cluster
            won't start or stop it. However, unlike maintenance mode, the cluster still
            <emphasis>monitors</emphasis> the resource and reports any failures. This can be useful
            for troubleshooting. In most other cases, maintenance mode is more appropriate.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="ha-maintenance-workflow-more-info">
    <title>For more information</title>
    <para>
      For more information, see
      <link xlink:href="https://clusterlabs.org/projects/pacemaker/doc/3.0/Pacemaker_Administration/html/administrative.html"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
</topic>
