<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="intro-lsm"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>About the Linux Security Module Framework</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
The LSM (Linux Security Module) framework is a modular architecture within the Linux kernel that allows for the implementation of various security models, primarily MAC (Mandatory Access Control).
   </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
    <para>
Rather than hard-coding a specific security policy into the kernel, LSM provides a set of hooks at every critical system call,such as opening files, creating sockets, or starting processes that allow security modules like &selnx;, AppArmor, or Yama to verify actions.
When a process attempts a sensitive operation, the kernel triggers these hooks to ask the loaded security module for permission; if the module's specific policy denies the request, the action is blocked even if the user has root privileges.
This framework ensures that Linux remains flexible, allowing users to choose or stack different security layers based on their specific needs for system hardening.
  </para>
<para> The Linux security module framework includes the following modules:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Lockdown:</emphasis> The Lockdown module is a LSM, designed to strengthen the boundary between user-space processes and the kernel by restricting access to features that could allow even a root user to modify the running kernel image.
 It operates in two primary modes:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para><emphasis>integrity:</emphasis> which blocks features that allow user-space to modify the kernel such as, unsigned module loading or direct memory access via <filename>/dev/mem</filename>.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><emphasis>confidentiality:</emphasis> which extends these restrictions to prevent users from extracting sensitive information from kernel memory such as RSA private keys.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
  <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Landlock:</emphasis>The Landlock module empowers unprivileged processes to restrict their own access rights, effectively creating a tailored sandbox without requiring administrative or root privileges.
    Unlike traditional security modules that enforce system-wide policies, Landlock allows an application developer to define a safe subset of the file system that the program is permitted to access, blocking any unauthorized file reads, writes, or executions outside of that scope.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Capability:</emphasis> breaks down the traditionally all-or-nothing power of the root user into distinct and granular privileges. Instead of granting a process full administrative control, Linux assigns specific capabilities such as <literal>CAP_NET_BIND_SERVICE</literal> to open low-numbered ports.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">&selnx;:</emphasis> is a robust LSM module that implements a MAC (Mandatory Access Control) architecture, moving beyond the traditional user-owner permission model. It works by assigning security labels (contexts) to every process, file, and network port on the system, and then enforces a central policy that dictates exactly how these entities can interact.</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <section xml:id="how-does-lsm-work">
    <title>How LSM works? </title>
    <para>Whenever a process tries to access an object like opening a file, sending a network packet, or creating a directory, the kernel first performs its standard  DAC (Discretionary Access Control). This is the basic root versus user or <literal>read/write/execute</literal> permission check.
If the DAC allows it, the LSM framework then steps in:</para>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>The kernel calls a hook which is a redirection point.</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
  <para>The Security Module, for example &selnx; checks its own specific policy.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>The security module then returns a decision; <literal>Allowed</literal> or <literal>Denied</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>You can check which security modules are currently initialized on your Linux system:</para>
<screen>cat /sys/kernel/security/lsm
lockdown,capability,landlock,yama,selinux,bpf,ima,evm
</screen>
<para>sysctl is a powerful interface used to examine and modify kernel parameters at runtime. However, because these settings can fundamentally change how the OS behaves, they are guarded by specific permissions.
When a setting is writable only with <literal>CAP_SYS_PTRACE</literal>, it means the kernel requires the process attempting the change to possess a specific capability.
The sysctl settings writable only with <literal>CAP_SYS_PTRACE</literal> are: </para>
<table>
<title>sysctl settings explained </title>
<tgroup cols="3">
  <thead>
    <row>
      <entry>Level</entry>
      <entry>Name</entry>
      <entry>Description</entry>
       </row>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <row>
      <entry>0</entry>
      <entry>Classic</entry>
      <entry>Regular Linux ptrace permissions (owner can attach).</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>1</entry>
      <entry>Restricted</entry>
      <entry>Only a parent process can ptrace its descendants.</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>2</entry>
      <entry>Admin-only</entry>
      <entry>Only processes with <literal>CAP_SYS_PTRACE</literal> can ptrace (usually root).</entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry>3</entry>
      <entry>No-attach</entry>
      <entry>Ptrace is disabled globally. Cannot be changed until reboot. </entry>
    </row>
    </tbody>
</tgroup>
</table>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="imp-lsm">
      <title>Why is LSM important? </title>
      <para>Before LSM was introduced, users who want to add a new security feature to Linux had to hack the kernel code directly.
    LSM solved this by:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
 <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Standardization:</emphasis> It created a stable interface so security developers did not have to rewrite their code every time the kernel updated.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Modularity:</emphasis> It allows users to choose the security model that fits their needs, for example, AppArmor for ease of use or &selnx; for high-security environments.</para></listitem>
 <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Stacking:</emphasis> Modern kernels allow you to stack multiple modules, so you can run something like Yama to protect against <literal>ptrace</literal> attacks alongside AppArmor.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
     </section>
 </topic>