<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="intro-lsm-yama"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to the YAMA security module</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
Yama is a Linux security module designed to enhance system-wide security by implementing DAC (Discretionary Access Control) for certain kernel functionalities.
It focuses on restricting the use of the <literal>ptrace</literal> system call, which is commonly used for debugging but can also be exploited for malicious purposes.
<literal>ptrace</literal> is a short form of process call, which is a powerful system call that allows one process to observe, control, and manipulate another process.
</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
    <para>
The Yama module is vital because it addresses a fundamental weakness in the traditional Linux process model, where any process could freely peek and poke into the memory of any other process owned by the same user.
By introducing configurable scopes, most notably the restriction that a process can only trace its own descendants Yama prevents lateral movement by attackers. This means a compromised low-privilege application, like a Web browser or a chat client, cannot easily reach out to steal sensitive data from an SSH agent or a password manager running in the same session.
You can implement Yama which is selectable at build-time with <literal>CONFIG_SECURITY_YAMA</literal> and can be controlled at run-time through <literal>sysctls</literal> in <filename>/proc/sys/kernel/yama</filename>.
  </para>
  <para>sysctl is a powerful interface used to examine and modify kernel parameters at runtime. However, because these settings can fundamentally change how the OS behaves, they are guarded by specific permissions.
    When a setting is writable only with <literal>CAP_SYS_PTRACE</literal>, it means the kernel requires the process attempting the change to possess a specific capability.
    The sysctl settings writable only with <literal>CAP_SYS_PTRACE</literal> are: </para>
    <table>
    <title>sysctl settings explained </title>
    <tgroup cols="3">
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry>Level</entry>
          <entry>Name</entry>
          <entry>Description</entry>
           </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry>0</entry>
          <entry>Classic</entry>
          <entry>Regular Linux ptrace permissions (owner can attach).</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>1</entry>
          <entry>Restricted</entry>
          <entry>Only a parent process can ptrace its descendants.</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>2</entry>
          <entry>Admin-only</entry>
          <entry>Only processes with <literal>CAP_SYS_PTRACE</literal> can ptrace (usually root).</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry>3</entry>
          <entry>No-attach</entry>
          <entry>Ptrace is disabled globally. Cannot be changed until reboot. </entry>
        </row>
        </tbody>
    </tgroup>
    </table>
 </topic>