<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="about-iscsi"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>About iSCSI</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
 iSCSI (Internet Small Computer Systems Interface) is a networking protocol that enables the transmission of SCSI commands over IP networks, allowing a computer to access remote storage as if it were a locally attached hard drive.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
    <para>
   By wrapping storage-level data blocks into standard TCP/IP packets, it bridges the gap between local storage performance and network flexibility, using existing Ethernet infrastructure like switches and cables rather than expensive, specialized hardware. In an iSCSI setup, the "initiator" (the client) connects to a "target" (the storage server) to claim a portion of disk space known as a LUN (Logical Unit Number), which the client can then format and manage with its own native file system.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="features-iscsi">
      <title>Key characteristics of remote iSCSI storage</title>
      <para>Following are some the common characteristics of iSCSI:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Block-Level Access:</emphasis> Unlike a network share where you see files, with iSCSI, your system sees raw sectors. This allows you to format the remote drive with any file system such as NTFS, ReFS, or ext4.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Distance and Flexibility:</emphasis> The storage can be in a server rack across the room or in a data center across the city. As long as there is a network connection, the system treats it as local storage.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Low Latency Requirement:</emphasis> Because the OS thinks the drive is local, it expects fast responses. This is why remote iSCSI usually requires a high-speed network ( preferably 10Gbps or higher).</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
        </section>
        <section xml:id="usecase-iscsi">
          <title>Use cases for remote iSCSI storage</title>
          <para>Following are some of the common use cases for iSCSI:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Virtualization:</emphasis> Servers running VMware or Hyper-V store virtual machines on remote iSCSI targets so that if one physical server dies, another can immediately take over the disk over the network.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Database Hosting:</emphasis> High-performance databases like SQL Server or Oracle require block-level access to manage data placement and logging. Since iSCSI presents itself as a local physical disk rather than a shared folder, it satisfies the strict technical requirements of database software while keeping the data on a secure and centralized server.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para><emphasis role="bold">Consolidated Backup and Disaster Recovery:</emphasis> iSCSI allows organizations to centralize backups from various machines onto one large and manageable storage array. It also supports diskless booting, where a server with no internal hard drive can load its entire operating system directly from a remote iSCSI target, making hardware replacement much faster.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
            </section>
      </topic>