<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="concept-about-journald"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>About journald</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        <command>systemd</command> uses <command>journald</command> as its logging system. All system events are written to the journal, a system service managed by <command>systemd-journald</command> service.  This allows you to search and manage all system logs. It collects and stores logging data by maintaining structured indexed journals based on logging information received from the kernel, user processes, standard input, and system service errors.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    The <command>systemd-journald</command> service is enabled by default.
  </para>
  <para>The journal records nearly every type of event generated on the system, including Kernel messages, Initrd (initial RAM disk) messages, Service startup/shutdown, Application events, and Authentication and session data. Journal allows centralization and unification of logs from all sources, and it records events in structured manner which in turn helps identifying errors and in crash recovery.</para>
  <para>The <command>journald</command> command collects log data from several sources simultaneously logs are then managed in a structured, binary format within files in <filename>/run/log/journal/</filename> by default. Because the <filename>/run/ directory</filename> is volatile by nature, log data is lost at reboot. To make the log data persistent, create the directory <filename>/var/log/journal/</filename> and make sure it has the correct access modes and ownership, so the <command>systemd-journald</command> service can store its data. To switch to persistent logging, execute the following commands:</para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;  mkdir /var/log/journal
&prompt.sudo;  systemd-tmpfiles --create --prefix=/var/log/journal
&prompt.sudo;  journalctl --flush</screen>
<para>All log data stored in <filename>/run/log/journal/</filename> are flushed into <filename>/var/log/journal/</filename>.</para>
  <section>
   <title>Journal entry structure</title>
  <para>Log entry in the journal is a data structure containing the log message and  metadata fields:</para>
<itemizedlist><listitem><para>Timestamp: The exact time the event occurred.</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Source Fields</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>_PID: Process ID of the sender.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>_UID/_GID: User/Group ID of the sender.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>_EXE: Path to the executable.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>_COMM: Name of the executable.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>System Fields</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>_SYSTEMD_UNIT: The systemd unit (service) that generated the log (e.g., sshd.service).</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>_BOOT_ID: A unique identifier for the specific system boot session.</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem>
<listitem><para>Kernel Fields</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>_TRANSPORT: How the message was logged (e.g., kernel, syslog, stdout).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</listitem><listitem><para>Priority level: A numeric value indicating the severity of the message (0=emerg, 7=debug).</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</section>
 <section xml:id="sec-journalctl-usage">
  <title><command>journalctl</command> usage</title>

  <para>
   Running the <command>journalctl</command> without any options displays all logged messages, usually starting from the oldest, and pipes the output through a pager (like less) for easy navigation.
  </para>
<para>Listed below are the common  useful options to enhance the default <command>journalctl</command> behavior. All switches are described in the <command>journalctl</command> man page, man 1 <command>journalctl</command>. </para>
  <tip>
   <title>Messages related to a specific executable</title>
   <para>
    To show all journal messages related to a specific executable, specify the
    full path to the executable:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl /usr/lib/systemd/systemd</screen>
  </tip>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-f</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Shows only the most recent journal messages, and prints new log entries
      as they are added to the journal.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term/>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Prints the messages and jumps to the end of the journal, so that the
      latest entries are visible within the pager.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-r</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Prints the messages of the journal in reverse order, so that the latest
      entries are listed first.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-k</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Shows only kernel messages. This is equivalent to the field match
      <literal>_TRANSPORT=kernel</literal> (see
      <xref linkend="sec-journalctl-filter-fields"/>).
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>-u</term>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Shows only messages for the specified &systemd; unit. This is equivalent
      to the field match
      <literal>_SYSTEMD_UNIT=<replaceable>UNIT</replaceable></literal> (see
      <xref linkend="sec-journalctl-filter-fields"/>).
     </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl -u apache2</screen>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>
  <para/>
</section>
  <section xml:id="sec-journalctl-filter">
  <title>Filtering the journal output</title>

  <para>
   This section describes how to refine the search in logs according to boot numbers, for specific time interval or to view specific data fields.
   content of the journal, the oldest entries listed first. The output can be
   filtered by specific switches and fields.
  </para>

  <section xml:id="sec-journalctl-filter-boot">
   <title>Filtering based on a boot number</title>
   <para>
    <command>journalctl</command> can filter messages based on a specific
    system boot. To list all available boots, run
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl --list-boots</screen>
   <para>
    The first column lists the boot offset: <literal>0</literal> for the
    current boot, <literal>-1</literal> for the previous one,
    <literal>-2</literal> for the one before that, etc. The second column
    contains the boot ID followed by the limiting time stamps of the specific
    boot.
   </para>
   <para>
    Show all messages from the current boot:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl -b</screen>
   <para>
    If you need to see journal messages from the previous boot, add an offset
    parameter. The following example outputs the previous boot messages:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl -b -1</screen>
   <para>
    Another way is to list boot messages based on the boot ID. For this
    purpose, use the _BOOT_ID field:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _BOOT_ID=156019a44a774a0bb0148a92df4af81b</screen>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-journalctl-filter-time">
   <title>Filtering based on time interval</title>
   <para>
    You can filter the output of <command>journalctl</command> by specifying the
    starting and/or ending date. The date specification should be of the format
    <literal>2025-06-30 9:17:16</literal>. If the time part is omitted, midnight
    is assumed. If seconds are omitted, <literal>:00</literal> is assumed. If
    the date part is omitted, the current day is assumed. Instead of numeric
    expression, you can specify the keywords <literal>yesterday</literal>,
    <literal>today</literal> or <literal>tomorrow</literal>. They refer to
    midnight of the day before the current day, of the current day, or of the
    day after the current day. If you specify <literal>now</literal>, it refers
    to the current time. You can also specify relative times prefixed with
    <literal>-</literal> or <literal>+</literal>, referring to times before or
    after the current time.
   </para>
   <para>
    Show only new messages since now, and update the output continuously:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl --since "now" -f</screen>
   <para>
    Show all messages since last midnight till 3:20am:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl --since "today" --until "3:20"</screen>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-journalctl-filter-fields">
   <title>Filtering based on fields</title>
   <para>
    You can filter the output of the journal by specific fields. The syntax of
    a field to be matched is <literal>FIELD_NAME=MATCHED_VALUE</literal>, such
    as <literal>_SYSTEMD_UNIT=httpd.service</literal>. You can specify multiple
    matches in a single query to filter the output messages even more. See
    <command>man 7 systemd.journal-fields</command> for a list of default
    fields.
   </para>
   <para>
    Show messages produced by a specific process ID:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _PID=1039</screen>
   <para>
    Show messages belonging to a specific user ID:
   </para>
<screen># journalctl _UID=1000</screen>
   <para>
    Show messages from the kernel ring buffer (the same as
    <command>dmesg</command> displays):
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _TRANSPORT=kernel</screen>
   <para>
    Show messages from the service's standard or error output:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _TRANSPORT=stdout</screen>
   <para>
    Show messages produced by a specified service only:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _SYSTEMD_UNIT=avahi-daemon.service</screen>
   <para>
    If two different fields are specified, only entries that match both
    expressions at the same time are shown:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _SYSTEMD_UNIT=avahi-daemon.service _PID=1488</screen>
   <para>
    If two matches refer to the same field, all entries matching either
    expression are shown:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _SYSTEMD_UNIT=avahi-daemon.service _SYSTEMD_UNIT=dbus.service</screen>
   <para>
    You can use the <literal>+</literal> separator to combine two expressions in
    a logical <literal>OR</literal>. The following example shows all messages
    from the Avahi service process with the process ID 1480 together with all
    messages from the D-Bus service:
   </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;journalctl _SYSTEMD_UNIT=avahi-daemon.service _PID=1480 + _SYSTEMD_UNIT=dbus.service</screen>
  </section> 
</section>
</topic>
