<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="klp-intro"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to &klp;</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="dpopov@suse.com" its:translate="yes"/>
  </info>
  <para>
    &klp; (&klpa;) makes it possible to apply the latest security updates to
    Linux kernels without rebooting. This maximizes system uptime and
    availability, which is particularly important for mission-critical systems.
    As such, &klpa; offers several benefits.
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Keeping a large number of servers automatically up-to-date is essential
        for organizations obtaining or maintaining certain compliance
        certifications. &klpa; can help achieve compliance, while reducing the
        need for maintenance windows.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Companies that work with service-level agreement contracts must
        guarantee a certain level of the system accessibility and uptime.
        Live patching makes it possible to patch systems without incurring
        downtime.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Since &klpa; is part of the standard system update mechanism, there is
        no need for specialized training or introduction of additional
        maintenance routines.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <section xml:id="sec-klp-scope">
    <title>&klp; scope</title>

    <para>
      The scope of &productnameshort; Live Patching includes fixes for SUSE Common
      Vulnerability Scoring System (CVSS) level 7+ vulnerabilities and bug fixes related to system
      stability or data corruption. However, it may not be technically feasible
      to create live patches for all fixes that fall under the specified
      categories. &suse; therefore reserves the right to skip fixes in
      situations where creating a kernel live patch is not possible for
      technical reasons. Currently, over 95% of qualifying fixes are released
      as live patches. SUSE CVSS is based on the CVSS v3.0
      system. For more information on CVSS, see <link xlink:href="https://www.first.org/cvss/">Common
      Vulnerability Scoring System SIG</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sec-klp-limitations">
    <title>&klp; limitations</title>

    <para>
      &klpa; involves replacing functions and gracefully handling replacement
      of interdependent function sets. This is done by redirecting calls to old
      code to updated code in a different memory location. Changes in data
      structures make the situation more complicated, as the data remain in
      place and cannot be extended or reinterpreted. While there are techniques
      that allow indirect alteration of data structures, certain fixes cannot
      be converted to live patches. In this situation, a system restart is the
      only way to apply the fixes.
    </para>
  </section>
</topic>
