<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="manage-vm-on-commandline-benefits"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Benefits of using libvirt</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract><para>libvirt is a software that enables you to manage different virtual machines. You can use libvirt to start, stop, monitor, and manage virtual machines.</para></abstract></info>
    <para>The benefits of using libvirt are given below:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Provides a unified management interface for diverse virtualization technologies.</para></listitem>
        
        <listitem><para>Modular architecture allows developers to extend the functionality.</para></listitem>   
        <listitem><para>Allows live migration of virtual machines between physical hosts without downtime. This facilitates load balancing and maintenance.</para></listitem>     
        <listitem><para>Enables managing remote virtual machines. </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Allows storage, resource, and network management.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Allows event monitoring and this helps in tracking changes of virtual machines and related resources.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Allows managing different types of storage that are available to VM Guests on a host running the <literal>libvirtd</literal> service.</para></listitem>
     <listitem><para>Allows managing physical and logical network interfaces that are available to VM Guests on a host running the <literal>libvirtd</literal> service.</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>Provides resource efficiency as command-line tools have less resource requirements compared to graphical user interface.</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>Allows scripting and automation of repetitive tasks.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Provides snapshot support thereby enabling you to capture the state of virtual machines at a specific point in time.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Allows using any Linux distribution as libvirt is cross-platform compatible.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Simplifies the management of virtual machines with existing libvirt-based utilities.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
    </topic>
