<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="manage-vm-on-commandline-vmm"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
<info><title>Virtual Machine Manager</title>
  <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
  <abstract><para>
    Virtual Machine Manager is a GUI (graphical user interface) application for viewing and configuring virtual machines managed by libvirt</para></abstract></info>
    <para>The Virtual Machine Manager displays the summary of running domains, their live performance and resource utilization statistics. Use wizards to create new domains, configure and adjust resource allocation and virtual machine.</para>
    <figure><title>libvirt Overview</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="pdf">
          <imagedata fileref="libvirt_vmm.png" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></figure>   
    <para>Listed below are a few configuration options available on Virtual Machine Manager:</para>
<variablelist>
  <varlistentry>
    <term>View and configure VM Guest details</term>
    <listitem><para>The <keycap>Details</keycap> view of the Virtual Machine Manager displays detailed information about the VM Guest's complete configuration and hardware equipment. Using this view, you can also change the guest configuration or add and modify virtual hardware to an existing virtual machine.</para></listitem>
  </varlistentry><varlistentry><term>View Performance Statistics of CPU usage, memory usage, disk and network I/O of the VM guest.</term>
  <listitem><para>The <keycap>Performance</keycap> view shows regularly updated charts of CPU and memory usage, and disk and network I/O of the VM guest. </para><para>You can also set up the virtualized processor and memory. In the CPUs section, you can configure the number of virtual CPUs allocated to the VM Guest. Logical host CPUs shows the number of online and usable CPUs on the VM Host Server. In the <keycap>Configuration</keycap> you can configure the CPU model and topology. </para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Configure Boot options, Storage, Controllers, Networking, Input devices</term>
  <listitem><para>You can configure options affecting the VM Guest boot process and you can configure both hard disks and removable media, such as USB or CD-ROM drives in <keycap>Storage</keycap>. <keycap>Controllers</keycap> and <keycap>Networking</keycap> allows you to add and configure new controllers and network device respectively. The configuration of input devices such as mouse, keyboard or tablet is possible through the <keycap>Input</keycap> option.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Assign a host PCI device to a VM Guest</term><listitem><para>You can directly assign PCI devices on the VM Host Server to guests (PCI pass-through). When the PCI device is assigned to one VM Guest, it cannot be used on the host or by another VM Guest unless it is re-assigned.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>Take snapshot of the VM host</term><listitem><para>You can take snapshots of the VM host and you can access the option from VM Details toolbar. </para></listitem></varlistentry>
<varlistentry><term>View and configure details of VM Host</term><listitem><para>You can create and manage connection, storage pools, and virtual networks.</para></listitem></varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</topic>
