<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="manage-vm-on-commandline-concept"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
<info><title>What is &libvirt;?</title>
  <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
  <abstract><para>
    libvirt is a collection of software that provides a common API (Application Programming Interface) for managing popular virtualization solutions, for example KVM and Xen. libvirt consists of an API library, a system service libvirtd, and a command line utility virsh. 
    </para></abstract></info>
    <para>Using the libvirt-based tools is a recommended way of managing VM Guests. You can use <command>virsh</command> to configure virtual machines (VM) on the command line as an alternative to using the graphical &vmm;. Interoperability between libvirt and libvirt-based applications has been tested and is an essential part of SUSE's support stance.</para>
    <para>The libvirtd service runs on the server and performs management tasks, for example, starting, stopping, and migrating guests between host servers. The libvirt client libraries and utilities connect to libvirtd and collect configuration information and resources of the host servers. </para>
    <para>The configuration of each virtual machine is stored in an xml file and you can manage this configuration in different ways. To manage the configuration on the command-line, you can use <command>virsh</command></para>
    <para>The management of virtual machines on command-line provides more control over the host machines than using the graphical interface applications. This also enables you to add on to scripting and automation.</para>
    <para>Using <command>virsh</command> enables you to start, configure, pause, list, and stop virtual machines. You can also manage virtual disks using this utility.
    </para><note><para>You must be a root user to manage virtual machines using <command>virsh</command>. However, as a non-root user you enter an unprivileged libvirt session in which you can not see or interact with any virtual machines.</para></note>
   <para>Benefits of using &libvirt;</para>
     <para>libvirt is a software that enables you to manage different virtual machines. You can use libvirt to start, stop, monitor, and manage virtual machines.</para>
        <para>The benefits of using libvirt are given below:</para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Provides a unified management interface for diverse virtualization technologies.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Modular architecture allows developers to extend the functionality.</para></listitem>   
            <listitem><para>Allows live migration of virtual machines between physical hosts without downtime. This facilitates load balancing and maintenance.</para></listitem>     
            <listitem><para>Enables managing remote virtual machines. </para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Allows storage, resource, and network management.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Allows event monitoring and this helps in tracking changes of virtual machines and related resources.</para></listitem>
            <listitem><para>Allows managing different types of storage that are available to VM Guests on a host running the <literal>libvirtd</literal> service.</para></listitem>
         <listitem><para>Allows managing physical and logical network interfaces that are available to VM Guests on a host running the <literal>libvirtd</literal> service.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Provides resource efficiency as command-line tools have less resource requirements compared to graphical user interface.</para></listitem>
       <listitem><para>Allows scripting and automation of repetitive tasks.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Provides snapshot support thereby enabling you to capture the state of virtual machines at a specific time.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Allows using any Linux distribution as libvirt is cross-platform compatible.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Simplifies the management of virtual machines with existing libvirt-based utilities.</para></listitem></itemizedlist>
  
</topic>
