<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="manage-vm-on-commandline-vmm"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
<info><title>Virtual Machine Manager</title>
  <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
  <abstract><para>
    Virtual Machine Manager is a GUI (graphical user interface) application for configuring virtual machines managed by libvirt.</para></abstract></info>
    <para>You can start Virtual Machine Manager by running the <command>virt-manager</command> command from the command line. The Virtual Machine Manager displays the summary of running domains, their live performance and resource utilization statistics. You can use Wizards to create new domains, configuration and adjustment of a domain’s resource allocation and virtual hardware.</para>
    <note><para>Some configuration changes take effect immediately after you make the changes in the GUI, while others need a reboot of the machine. The Virtual Machine Manager warns you that you must reboot the machine.</para>
</note>
<para>You can do the following configurations from Virtual Machine Manager:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>View details of the VM Guest</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Add hardware</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Remove hardware</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>View Performance Statistics of CPU and memory usage, and disk and network I/O</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Configure virtualized processor and memory.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Configure boot options affecting the VM Guest boot process</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Configure Storage, Controller, Network, Input devices, Graphics, Video, and so on.</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Redirect USB devices that are connected to the client machine to the VM Guest</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Add a CD/DVD-ROM device with Virtual Machine Manager</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Add a floppy device with Virtual Machine Manager</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Eject and changing floppy or CD/DVD-ROM media with Virtual Machine Manager</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Assign a host PCI device to a VM Guest</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist></topic>
