<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="micro-public-clouds" xml:lang="en"
 role="concept"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
           <info>
            <title>Basic information about the &productnameshort; public cloud images</title>
      <abstract>
        <para>
          &productnameshort; is a light-weight operating system designed mainly to run in the edge environment.  uses several tools for its deployment in public clouds. This topic also describes required disk size and registration, and provides details about the default user.
        </para>
      </abstract>
    </info>
    <para>
      This article provides details specific to &productnameshort; images that
      are intended for deployment in public cloud environments. The 
      generic information about public cloud images is provided in the
      <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-public-cloud/all/html/public-cloud/public-cloud.html">Public Cloud Guide</link>. For more &productnameshort; 
      documentation, refer to the
      <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-micro/">&productname;
      documentation set</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Before you start the deployment, you should check the default configuration if it suits your need.    
      The initial &productnameshort; configuration creates a default user called <literal>suse</literal>. To add another user, you can change the default initial configuration or you can create a new user from an already running system. To change the default initial configuration, refer to <xref linkend="modifying-ignition-cnfiguration-cloud"/> for the procedure. For the procedure of adding users to already running system, refer to <xref linkend="slemicro-useradd-introduction"/>.
    </para>
    <para>
      The deployment procedure itself depend on the cloud vendor. For details, refer to its documentation.
    </para>

<para>
  After the deployment, you need to register the system. In newer
      images, you can use the <command>registercloudguest</command> command to
      register the system. For details, refer to the
      <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-public-cloud/all/html/public-cloud/cha-admin.html#sec-admin-register">Public Cloud Guide</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Alternatively, you can register your system as described in
      the <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-micro/5.3/html/SLE-Micro-all/cha-postintall-registration.html#sec-images-registration">&productnameshort;
      registration</link>.
</para>


    <section xml:id="micro-cloud-tools-deployment">
    <title>Tools involved in initializing &productnameshort; in public clouds</title>
    <para>
      The instance initialization is performed using &ignition; and Afterburn.
      In the default &ignition; configuration, &ignition; is responsible for
      creating the default user: <literal>suse</literal>. &ignition; interacts
      with the instance metadata service of the cloud provider only to get the
      so-called user data. Other data, like the user specified in Azure
      or SSH key from the GCE, are not parsed from this metadata service.
    </para>
    <para>
      Afterburn writes the SSH key to the <literal>suse</literal> home
      directory using the instance metadata service (IMDS). To transfer the SSH
      key from the IMDS, the <literal>afterburn-sshkeys@suse</literal> is used.
      The service is started automatically by &systemd;.
    </para>
    <para>
      &ignition; runs on the first boot only. To distinguish the first boot
      from succeeding boots, the flag file
      <filename>/boot/writable/firstboot_happened</filename> is created.
      Whenever you want to trigger &ignition; again, you need to remove this
      file.
    </para>
    <para>
      The default &ignition; configuration is stored in the configuration file:
      <filename>/usr/lib/ignition/base.d/base.ign</filename>. You can modify
      this file to perform configuration changes. For details, refer to
      <xref linkend="task-modifying-ignition-cloud"/>.
    </para>
    <note>
      <title>&combustion; not included in the &productnameshort; public 
      cloud images</title>
      <para>
        To configure your instance with &combustion;, you need to
        create a separate disk in the cloud framework. The disk must have
        the required directory structure. Then you need to create an instance
        with this configuration disk attached. If the use of &combustion; is
        needed for integration into your environment, you can build your own
        images using keg and keg-recipes. The keg-recipes project contains the
        image description used by SUSE to build the images we publish. For
        details, refer to
        <link xlink:href="https://github.com/SUSE-Enceladus/keg-recipes/">keg-recipes</link>.
      </para>
    </note>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="micro-cloud-disk-size-clouds">
    <title>Required and available disk size</title>
    <para>
      The root volume is set to the size specified by the cloud vendors, for
      example, 10&nbsp;GB in AWS and GCE and 30&nbsp;GB in Azure.
    </para>
    <para>
      The recommended size for &productnameshort; is 12&nbsp;GB. However, the
      size depends on the number and size of workloads you intend to run.
    </para>
    <para>
      As with each run of the &tr-up; command, a new snapshot is created. Keep
      in mind that these snapshots also take up some size, even though Btrfs
      snapshots are space-efficient.
    </para>
    <para>
      The root volume automatically grows as you change the size of the
      underlying disk. When you are running low on disk space, you can always
      stop your instance and increase the size of the system disk, up to the limitation
      of individual disk sizes in each cloud framework.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="micro-cloud-snapshots-cloud-vs-slema">
    <title>Snapshotting</title>
    <para>
      &productnameshort; creates its own internal snapshots that are not related
      nor can interfere with the external snapshots of the disk. External 
      snapshots can be created using the cloud framework tools for backup 
      purposes or for making new images. For details about &productnameshort; 
      snapshots, refer to
      <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-micro/html/SLE-Micro-all/cha-snapshots.html">&productnameshort; snapshotting</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="micro-cloud-registration">
    <title>Registration</title>
    <para>
      After you deploy the image, you need to register the system. In newer
      images, you can use the <command>registercloudguest</command> command to
      register the system. For details, refer to the
      <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-public-cloud/all/html/public-cloud/cha-admin.html#sec-admin-register">Public Cloud Guide</link>.
    </para>
    <para>
      Alternatively, you can register your system as described in
      the <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-micro/5.3/html/SLE-Micro-all/cha-postintall-registration.html#sec-images-registration">&productnameshort;
      registration</link>.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="micro-cloud-default-users">
    <title>Default users of &productnameshort;</title>
    <para>
      &productnameshort; images come with a predefined user
      <literal>suse</literal> that has <command>sudo</command> privileges
      assigned. Therefore, you can switch to the &rootuser; using the
      <command>sudo -i</command> command.
    </para>
    <para>
      As the default user possibly does not suit your needs, you have several
      options for adding users. You can either define users in the &ignition;
      configuration file, or use the <command>useradd</command> command
      to add users to the running system.
    </para>
    <para>
      For more details about adding users via &ignition;, refer to the
      <link xlink:href="https://documentation.suse.com/sle-micro/html/SLE-Micro-all/cha-images-ignition.html#sec-ignition-examples">deployment guide</link>
      and <xref linkend="modifying-ignition-cnfiguration-cloud"/>. For more 
      details about using the <command>useradd</command> command, see
      <xref linkend="task-slemicro-useradd"/>.
    </para>
  </section>
</topic>
