<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="networkmanager-nmcli-concept"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>The &nm; concept</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        &nm; is a tool that enables managing network connections and devices.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>&nm; allows you to create, configure and manage network connections and devices. You can enable &nm; to manage primary network connection and other network interfaces. &nm; supports desktop distros as well as laptops and other portable computers. It supports state-of-the-art encryption types and standards for network connections, including connections to 802.1X protected networks. 802.1X is the “IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks—Port-Based Network Access Control”.</para>
<para>
  You can switch between  wired or wireless networks seamlessly as &nm; automatically connects to known wireless networks or manage several network connections in parallel. You can also manually switch between available networks and manage your network connection using an applet in the system tray. 
</para>
<para>The two components of &nm; are:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>&nm daemon</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Graphical front-ends and command-line interfaces</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>&nm; stores all network configuration as a connection, which is a collection of data that describes how to create or connect to a network. These connections are stored as files in the <filename>/etc/NetworkManager/system-connections/</filename> directory by default. Each network connection (Wi-Fi, Ethernet, VPN) is represented by a separate file in this directory.</para>
<para>A connection is active when a particular device uses the connection. The device may have more than one connection configured, but only one can be active at a given time. The other connections can be used to fast switch from one connection to another. For example, if the active connection is not available, &nm; tries to connect the device to another configured connection.</para>
<para>The &nm; daemon manages the network connections and the graphical front-ends and command-line interfaces allows you to interact with the &nm; daemon. The widely used graphical-front ends and command-line interfaces are nm-applet, nmcli, nmtui and so on.</para>
<para>The central configuration file for &nm; <filename>NetworkManager.conf</filename> is the primary location for configuring behavior and settings of &nm;, including logging, connection management, and network device handling.</para>
</topic>
