<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->
<topic xml:id="networkmanager-nmcli-concept"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>The NetworkManager concept</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="shalaka.harne@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        NetworkManager is a tool that enables managing network connections and devices.</para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>NetworkManager allows you to create, configure, and manage network connections and devices. You can install and enable NetworkManager to manage primary network connection and other network interfaces. NetworkManager supports desktop distros as well as laptops and other portable computers. It supports state-of-the-art encryption types and standards for network connections, including connections to 802.1X protected networks. 802.1X is the “IEEE Standard for Local and Metropolitan Area Networks—Port-Based Network Access Control”.</para>
<para>
  You can switch between  wired or wireless networks seamlessly as NetworkManager automatically connects to known wireless networks or manage several network connections in parallel. You can also manually switch between available networks and manage your network connection using an applet in the system tray. 
</para>
<para>The two components of NetworkManager are:</para>
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>NetworkManager daemon</para></listitem>
  <listitem><para>Graphical front-ends and command-line interfaces</para></listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<para>The NetworkManager daemon manages the network connections and the various graphical front-ends and command-line interfaces allows you to interact with the NetworkManager daemon. Some of the widely used graphical-front ends and command-line interfaces are nm-applet, nmcli, nmtui, and so on.</para>
<para>You must install and enable NetworkManager to manage your connections and devices.</para>
</topic>
