<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="ntp-time-synchronization-concept"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Time synchronization using NTP</title>
    <!--add author's email address-->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com"/>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="time-synchronization-concept">
    <title>What is time synchronization?</title>
    <para>
      Maintaining an accurate and synchronized system time on the computer is
      vital for team work. Planning and calendaring applications rely on it to
      track time correctly and notify users about appointments on time. For
      clustered applications, individual host machines often require
      synchronized system time for mutual communication.
    </para>
    <para>
      The built-in hardware clock is not a reliable time source. Manual
      correction of the system time may cause malfunction of critical
      applications due to sudden time leaps. Therefore the system time needs to
      be synchronized against an external reliable time source over network.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ntp-concept">
    <title>What is NTP?</title>
    <para>
      The NTP (NTP) is designed to synchronize the system time over the
      network. Its goal is to maintain the absolute time, and use it to
      synchronize the system time of all machines within a network.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ntp-time-synchronization-how-it-works">
    <title>How does NTP work?</title>
    <para>
      When the NTP service is properly configured, it continuously queries and
      adjusts the system time with reliable time servers. Typically, home
      computers and other devices connected to the internet are configured to
      query a public time server on the Internet.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Individual devices querying a public time server</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="desktop-machine-ntp.png" width="50%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="desktop-machine-ntp.png" width="50%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para>
      Conversely, desktop computers and servers that reside inside a corporate
      subnet are configured to query a dedicated time server within the local
      network. The time server itself synchronizes its time with a public time
      server.
    </para>
    <figure>
      <title>Multiple hosts querying an internal time server</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="multiple-machines-ntp.png" width="50%"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="multiple-machines-ntp.png" width="50%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <section xml:id="time-synchronization-ntp-implementation">
      <title>Implementation</title>
      <para>
        &chrony; is the default implementation of NTP in &productname;.
        &chrony; includes two parts:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            &chronyd; is a &systemd; service that can be started at boot time.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            &chronyc; is a command line interface program to monitor the
            performance of &chronyd;, and to change specific operating
            parameters at runtime.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="ntp-operate-chronyd-service">
      <title>Operating the &chronyd; service</title>
      <para>
        The main part of &chrony; is the &chronyd; &systemd; service that runs
        in the background and synchronizes system time with selected time
        servers.
      </para>
      <para>
        You can start, stop and view the status of &chronyd; with the following
        commands:
      </para>
<screen>
&prompt.sudo;systemctl start chronyd.service
&prompt.sudo;systemctl status chronyd.service
&prompt.sudo;systemctl stop chronyd.service
</screen>
      <para>
        To start &chronyd; automatically during system boot, run the following
        command:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl enable chronyd.service</screen>
    </section>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="time-synchronization-ntp-benefits">
    <title>Benefits</title>
    <para>
      Using NTP to maintain the accurate time has the following benefits:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          People can rely on their clocks when following a planned schedule,
          and applications can trigger scheduled actions accurately.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Cluster nodes often need to follow the same accurate time source to
          keep their data synchronized and up-to-date.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Using an internal time server to maintain the exact system time on
          multiple machines within the same network allows for a more secure
          setup with restricted access to the internet.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</topic>
