<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: https://github.com/SUSE/doc-unversioned/blob/main/openscap/xml/article_openscap.xml -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<topic xml:id="openscap-scap-overview"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>SCAP and &openscap;</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="souvik.sarkar@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        SCAP is a framework of specifications for automating security compliance. &openscap;
        implements this framework for Linux, and together with the &ssg;, enables automated
        auditing and hardening of &suselinux;.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="openscap-scap-overview-what-is-scap">
    <title>What is SCAP?</title>
    <para>
      SCAP stands for <emphasis>Security Content Automation Protocol</emphasis>. It is a framework
      of specifications developed and maintained by the National Institute of Standards and
      Technology (NIST) that supports automated configuration, vulnerability scanning, and policy
      compliance evaluation of systems in an organization. SCAP also standardizes how
      vulnerabilities and security configurations are communicated, both to machines and to human
      beings.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="openscap-scap-overview-what-is-openscap">
    <title>What is &openscap;?</title>
    <para>
      &openscap; is a collection of open source tools that implement the SCAP framework for Linux.
      It received the SCAP 1.2 certification from NIST in 2014. &openscap; works together with the
      <literal>&ssg;</literal> (SSG), which implements security guidelines recommended by respected
      authorities in a machine-readable format. This allows &openscap; to automatically audit and
      harden your &suselinux; system against recognized security baselines.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="openscap-scap-overview-components">
    <title>Key SCAP components</title>
    <para>
      SCAP consists of the following components, which interact to describe,
      evaluate and report on the security state of a system.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Open Vulnerability and Assessment Language (OVAL)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An XML format for testing the presence of a specific state on a system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Extensible Configuration Checklist Description Format (XCCDF)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An XML format that specifies security checklists, benchmarks, and configuration
            documentation. An XCCDF file contains a benchmark consisting of different profiles,
            where each profile is a set of rules with OVAL definitions. Profiles correspond to
            security practices such as HIPAA, PCI-DSS, and ANSSI-BP-028.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Common Platform Enumeration (CPE)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A structured naming scheme maintained by NIST for identifying IT systems, platforms,
            and software packages. A CPE name has the following format:
            <literal>cpe:/<replaceable>part</replaceable>:<replaceable>vendor</replaceable>:<replaceable>product</replaceable>:<replaceable>version</replaceable>:<replaceable>update</replaceable>:<replaceable>edition</replaceable>:<replaceable>language</replaceable></literal>
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>DataStream (DS)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            An XML format that bundles multiple SCAP components (CPE, XCCDF, OVAL) into a single
            file for distribution over a network. DataStream files are the primary input format for
            &openscap; when hardening and auditing a &suselinux; system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Common Configuration Enumeration (CCE)</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Unique identifiers assigned to security-related system configuration issues, used to
            track individual rules across profiles and tools.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="scap-security-guide-whatis">
    <title>What is the &ssg;?</title>
    <para>
      The <literal>&ssg;</literal> is an open source project that provides machine-readable
      security policies for Linux systems. It translates established security benchmarks, such as
      <orgname>Defense Information Systems Agency (DISA)</orgname>
      STIGs and
      <orgname>Center for
      Internet Security (CIS)</orgname>
      benchmarks, into SCAP content that can be automatically applied and verified. The
      <literal>&ssg;</literal> delivers XCCDF checklists, OVAL checks, and ready-to-use remediation
      scripts in the form of Ansible playbooks and Bash scripts.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="openscap-scap-overview-benefits">
    <title>Benefits of using &openscap; with the &ssg;</title>
    <para>
      Using &openscap; together with the &ssg; provides the following benefits:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Security guidelines from recognized authorities are transformed into a machine-readable
          format, removing the need for manual interpretation.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Scanning and remediation can be automated and run repeatedly, ensuring consistent policy
          enforcement across all systems in your infrastructure.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Results are stored in standardized XML formats and can be rendered as human-readable HTML
          reports for audit and compliance purposes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Multiple security profiles are available out of the box, covering regulations such as
          HIPAA, PCI-DSS v4, and ANSSI-BP-028, reducing the effort required to achieve and
          demonstrate compliance.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</topic>
