<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit
-->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic [ <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities; ]>
<topic xml:id="openwebui-introduction" role="concept" xml:lang="en"
xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to &owui;</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        This document provides an overview of &owui; and its user interface.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="what-is-openwebui">
    <title>What is &owui;?</title>
    <para>
      &owui; is a Web-based interface that allows you to interact with AI
      models, such as <emphasis>large language models</emphasis> (LLM). It
      simplifies working with AI by providing a graphical user interface (GUI)
      instead of relying on command-line tools. The goal of &owui; is to make AI
      accessible to a broader audience, including those without technical
      expertise in AI development.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="benefits-of-openwebui">
    <title>What are the key benefits of using &owui;?</title>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">Interaction with AI models</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can load a preferred AI model and interact with it using prompts
            in your natural language.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">Custom data handling for RAG workflows</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            &owui; allows you to upload documents or specify URLs of pages that
            the AI can parse and reference during interaction, which is
            particularly useful for RAG workflows.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">User-friendly interface</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            By providing a graphical user interface, &owui; makes AI tools more
            accessible to non-technical users. It helps them use the power of
            advanced AI models with no need for technical knowledge.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">Data privacy</emphasis></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            You can deploy &owui; locally or in a private environment. Such
            deployment is required for users concerned about privacy and data
            security.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="ai-prompt-answer">
    <title>How does an AI chatbot process user queries?</title>
    <para>
      When you enter a user prompt, several processes happen in the background
      to generate the response.
    </para>
    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Input processing</emphasis>. The AI first
          processes the text of your prompt to understand its meaning. This
          involves identifying the subject, intent and any details or context
          provided. This process is called <emphasis role="bold">Natural
          Language Understanding</emphasis> (NLU).
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Contextual analysis</emphasis>. If you are
          interacting with AI in a session where you have already asked previous
          questions, the AI considers the context of the conversation. This
          results in more relevant and coherent answers.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Knowledge retrieval</emphasis>. The AI retrieves
          information from its pre-trained knowledge base. This database
          includes facts, data and concepts that the AI has been trained on. AI
          models can also utilize retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) systems
          to get contextual information from the data provided by the
          organization. If the AI has access to real-time data, it can search
          for the latest information online to provide an up-to-date response.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Response generation</emphasis>. Using natural
          language generation (NLG) techniques, the AI constructs a coherent and
          grammatically correct response based on the information it retrieved.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Output</emphasis>. The AI delivers the response
          in a requested form, usually in a human-readable format. This can be a
          detailed explanation, a step-by-step guide, or a customized image,
          depending on the complexity of your query.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Feedback Loop</emphasis> (optional). In specific
          AI systems, your feedback or follow-up questions can help refine
          future responses, allowing the AI to improve its answers over time.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
  </section>
</topic>
