<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<topic xml:id="sles-pxe-server-introduction"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Overview of PXE booting with &productname; &productnumber;</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="souvik.sarkar@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        PXE booting enables machines to boot over the network into an installation or runtime
        environment without local storage. This section explains how PXE works in &productname;
        &productnumber;, with a focus on &grub;, &agama; and live installer images.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-what-is">
    <title>What is PXE booting?</title>
    <para>
      PXE (Preboot Execution Environment) is a method that allows systems to retrieve bootloaders
      and OS installers from a network server using DHCP and TFTP or HTTP. It is widely used for
      provisioning machines without physical media or preinstalled operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-how-it-works">
    <title>How PXE booting works in &productname; &productnumber;</title>
    <para>
      PXE booting in &productname; &productnumber; uses &grub; as the bootloader and the &agama;
      installer as the installation interface. Bootloaders and installer files are provided over
      the network using HTTP or TFTP, with &grub; fetching the kernel, initrd and live image. PXE
      clients can use either BIOS or UEFI firmware and work in both IPv4 and IPv6 networks.
    </para>
    <para>
      The bootloader passes kernel parameters such as <literal>root=live:</literal> to load the
      squashfs-based root filesystem from a live ISO image, starting the &agama; interface either
      locally or using a remote web UI.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-benefits">
    <title>Benefits of PXE booting</title>
    <para>
      PXE booting simplifies provisioning by removing the need for local installation media or
      manual setup. It enables:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Unattended installation of many systems over the network.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Centralized management of installer versions and boot configurations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for diverse architectures and firmware types, including Secure Boot.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Dynamic selection of installers or installation parameters using &grub; menus.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</topic>
