<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<topic xml:id="sles-pxe-server-introduction"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Overview of PXE booting with &productname; &productnumber;</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="souvik.sarkar@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        PXE booting enables machines to boot over the network into an installation or runtime
        environment without local storage. This section explains how PXE works in &productname;
       &productnumber; &agama; and live installer images with a focus on &grub;.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-what-is">
    <title>What is PXE booting?</title>
    <para>
      PXE (Preboot Execution Environment) is a method that allows systems to retrieve bootloaders
      and OS installers from a network server using DHCP and TFTP or HTTP. It is widely used for
      provisioning machines without physical media or preinstalled operating systems.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-benefits">
    <title>Benefits of PXE booting</title>
    <para>
      PXE booting simplifies provisioning by removing the need for local installation media or
      manual setup. It enables:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Unattended installation of many systems over the network.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Centralized management of installer versions and boot configurations.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Support for diverse architectures and firmware types, including Secure Boot.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          Dynamic selection of installers or installation parameters using &grub; menus.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-how-it-works">
    <title>How PXE booting works in &productname; &productnumber;</title>
    <para>
      PXE booting in &productname; &productnumber; uses &grub; as the bootloader and the &agama;
      installer as the installation interface. Bootloaders and installer files are provided over
      the network using HTTP or TFTP, with &grub; fetching the kernel, initrd and live image. PXE
      clients can use a variety of firmware (including the most common ones such as BIOS or UEFI),
      bootloader executable or image formats, as required by their architectures such as &x86-64;,
      &aarch64;, &ppc64le; and s390x. In addition, they must work in both IPv4 and IPv6 networks.
    </para>
    <para>
      The bootloader passes kernel parameters such as <literal>root=live:</literal> to load the
      squashfs-based root filesystem from a live ISO image, starting the &agama; interface either
      locally or as a web service for a remote web UI.
    </para>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-backward-compatibility-with-sle-15">
    <title>Backward compatibility with &productnameshort; 15.x</title>
    <para>
      The information in this article applies primarily to &productname; 16.0 and later. It focuses
      on PXE booting workflows that integrate with the &agama; installer and rely on live
      installation images. In the context and scope of this article, &productnameshort; 16.0 and
      later versions differs
      from &productnameshort; 15.x in the following ways:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Installer</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Uses <literal>dracut</literal> and &agama; instead of <literal>linuxrc</literal> and
            &yast;.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>DHCP server</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Use of ISC DHCP is discontinued (EOL 2022). For DHCP server, use any one of Kea or dnsmasq instead.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Boot parameters</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Uses <literal>root=live:</literal> or <literal>rd.kiwi.*</literal> parameters instead
            of <literal>install=</literal>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
      The bootloader choice (&grub;, pxelinux, etc.) remains flexible and is not version-dependent.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="sles-pxe-server-how-to-use-article">
    <title>How to use the information in this article</title>
    <para>
      This article consists of mandatory setup steps and optional or alternative configurations.
      Follow only the sections relevant to your deployment, and skip any alternatives that do not
      apply to your deployment.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Mandatory</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Tasks like installing components, preparing the installer image, configuring &grub;,
            and validating the server must be completed in all setups.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Delivery method</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Choose one: HTTP (recommended with &agama;) or TFTP.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>DHCP provider</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Choose one of dnsmasq, or Kea.
          </para>
          <note>
            <title>Limitations of your chosen method</title>
            <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  In &productnameshort; &productnumber;, ISC DHCP is discouraged because it has
                  been declared as <emphasis>end of life</emphasis> in 2022 by ISC. For more
                  information, refer to <link xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/dhcp/"></link>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  Use <emphasis role="strong">Kea</emphasis>&mdash;the new DHCP server from
                  ISC&mdash;as a modern replacement for ISC DHCP. For more information, refer to
                  <link xlink:href="https://www.isc.org/kea/"></link>.
                </para>
              </listitem>
              <listitem>
                <para>
                  You can use <emphasis role="strong">dnsmasq</emphasis> as a combination of a TFTP
                  server, a DHCP server, and a DNS server. In fact, you can use it to serve the
                  bootloader, kernel, initrd over TFTP, and an HTTP server such as nginx to serve
                  other files over HTTP. For PXE boot, nginx is used to serve the the files used in initrd, such as the
                  <filename>squashfs.img</filename>. dnsmasq provides DHCPv4 options for UEFI
                  HTTPBoot but requires a separate HTTP server such as nginx to deliver the boot files.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>IPv6 support</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Needed if you operate in an IPv6-only or a dual-stack (IPv4 and IPv6) network environment.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <figure xml:id="sles-pxe-server-setup-workflow">
      <title>Sample PXE server set-up workflow</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="sles-pxe-server-setup-workflow.svg"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata fileref="sles-pxe-server-setup-workflow.svg" width="85%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>
  </section>
</topic>
