<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
  <!ENTITY snapper "Snapper">
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="snapper-default-setup"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
 <info>
  <title>&snapper; default setup</title>    
    <meta name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
       <para>
        Learn about subvolumes, the default setup of &snapper; and its default settings.
       </para>
     </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>&snapper; is set up as an undo and recovery tool for system
    changes. By default, the root partition (<filename>/</filename>) of 
    &productname; is formatted with <literal>Btrfs</literal>. Taking snapshots
    is automatically enabled if the root partition (<filename>/</filename>) 
    is big enough (more than approximately 16&nbsp;GB). 
    By default, snapshots are disabled on partitions other than <filename>/</filename>.</para>
    
    <section xml:id="snapper-subvolumes">
      <title>What are subvolumes and why are certain subvolumes excluded from snapshots?</title>
      <para>
        A Btrfs subvolume is a part of a file system with its own independent file and directory 
        hierarchy. Unlike LVM logical volumes, which operate at the block level, Btrfs 
        subvolumes are file extent-based. A snapshot is also considered a subvolume, 
        carrying the initial content of the original subvolume. Subvolumes appear 
        as directories and can be manipulated like any other directory, including being 
        renamed or moved.</para>
      <para>One purpose of subvolumes is to be explicitly included or excluded from snapshots.
        Because the primary use case for snapshots is to roll back the system to a previous state,
        the following rules apply:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
           <listitem>
              <para>
                No loss of user-created data during a rollback (therefore <filename>/home</filename>
                is excluded via a subvolume)
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Keep the snapshot size to a minimum (therefore all temporary data in 
                <filename>/tmp</filename> is excluded via subvolumes)
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Exclude application-specific data (therefore <filename>/srv</filename> that hosts
                Web or FTP server data is excluded)
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Exclude application runtime data (<filename>/run</filename>, <filename>/var</filename>)
              </para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Exclude third-party applications (<filename>/opt</filename>, <filename>/usr/local</filename>)
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
  <note><title>Why is there a space limit?</title>
    <para>
      When creating a snapshot, no physical data copies are created. A snapshot only consists of 
      pointers to the respective data blocks. As long as the snapshot remains consistent with 
      the current system, it occupies almost no additional disk space (apart from the metadata 
      it contains). However, if a file is modified on the system, the changed data is recorded
      in the snapshot. Over time, as more changes accumulate and the snapshot diverges from 
      the live system, the snapshot's size increases accordingly.</para>
      <para>To prevent disks from running full (and the system becoming inoperable as a result), we 
      recommend having a minimal root file system size. The required size depends on system usage:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>The frequency of snapshot creation</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>The duration for which snapshots are retained</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>The rate of changes to the system</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
      <para>In general, the more snapshots you have, the longer they are kept, and the more 
        frequently the system changes, the larger the root partition needs to be.</para>
    </note>
</section>

<section xml:id="snapper-default-basics">
   <title>&snapper; on root</title> 
    <para>When &snapper; is configured to operate on root, every Btrfs subvolume is
    excluded by default.</para>
   <para>The default behavior of &snapper; is defined in a configuration file that 
    is specific for each partition or Btrfs subvolume. These configuration files reside
    under <filename>/etc/snapper/configs/</filename>.</para>
    <tip>
      <title>Enabling &snapper; in the installed system</title>
      <para>
       If you disabled &snapper; during the installation, you can enable it at
       any time later. To do so, create a default &snapper; configuration for the
       root file system by running:
      </para>
<screen>&prompt.sudo;snapper -c root create-config /</screen>
      <para>
       Afterward, enable the different snapshot types as described in <!--<xref
       linkend="sec-snapper-setup-customize-auto-snapshots"/>.-->
      </para>
      <para>
       Note that on a Btrfs root file system, snapshots require a file system with
       subvolumes configured as proposed by the installer and a partition size of at
       least 16&nbsp;GB.
      </para>
     </tip>
    </section>

  <section xml:id="snapper-default-settings">
    <title>&snapper; default settings</title>
      <para>By default, &snapper; on &productname; is automatically configured during 
      system installation if the following requirements are met:</para>
 <itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
  <para>Root partition size: &gt; 16&nbsp;GB</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>Root partition file system: Btrfs</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>Snapshots are created for the root partition only, and the following 
  directories are excluded by means of subvolumes. For the list of excluded subvolumes, 
  see <xref linkend="snapper-excluded-directories"/>.</para>
  <para>With the default configuration, &snapper; creates snapshots on the 
    following occasions:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
      <para>Installation. Three snapshots are created.</para> 
        <para>Snapshot <literal>0 single</literal>
        is created automatically and always refers to the current system, as indicated in the 
        <literal>Description</literal> column. This snapshot captures the state of 
        the system right after the installation process has concluded.</para>
        <para>Snapshot <literal>1 single</literal> for root partition (/) is taken automatically 
        with the name <literal>first root filesystem</literal>. This snapshot is 
        taken after the first set of system updates or configurations.</para>
        <para>Snapshot <literal>2 single</literal> is taken automatically with the 
        name <literal>after installation</literal>. This snapshot is created 
        towards the end of the installation process and marked as 
        <literal>important</literal>. It represents the state of the system after 
        all initial setup has been completed.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>System administration. A pair of snapshots is created whenever a user 
        makes changes to the system using &zypper; or &yast;.
        These snapshots are of the type <literal>pre/post</literal>. One snapshot is created 
        prior to the system change, a second one after the system change.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
      <para>Regular creation of timeline snapshots. Based on the configuration, 
        timeline snapshots can be taken at different intervals: hourly, daily, weekly, 
        monthly and yearly.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>This is the list of snapshots directly after a fresh installation of a system 
      with a root partition &gt; 16&nbsp;GB:</para>
<screen>
# | Type   | Pre # | Date                     | User | Used Space | Cleanup | Description           | Userdata     
-----+--------+-------+--------------------------+------+------------+---------+-----------------------+--------------
0  | single |       |                          | root |            |         | current               |              
1  | single |       | Thu Mar 24 12:14:34 2022 | root |  32.44 MiB |         | first root filesystem |              
2  | single |       | Thu Mar 24 12:25:55 2022 | root | 280.40 MiB | number  | after installation    | important=yes
45 | pre    |       | Mon Apr 25 17:58:45 2022 | root |  27.52 MiB | number  | zypp(zypper)          | important=yes
46 | post   |    45 | Mon Apr 25 18:00:07 2022 | root |  39.04 MiB | number  |                       | important=yes
    </screen>
      <para>&snapper; provides automatic snapshot cleanup algorithms to prevent running 
        out of space on the root partition. These algorithms differentiate 
        between timeline snapshots and <emphasis>numbered</emphasis> snapshots 
        (administration plus installation snapshot pairs). The cleanup behavior can 
        be configured based on the following criteria:</para>
<itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Number limit: The system can be set to automatically delete old snapshots 
        when a certain count of snapshots is reached.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Age limit: Old snapshots can be deleted if they exceed a certain age, while 
        still preserving a number of snapshots for each time period (hourly, daily, monthly, yearly).</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><literal>Pre</literal> and <literal>post</literal> snapshot pairs: 
          <literal>pre</literal> and <literal>post</literal> snapshot pairs that do not 
          differ can be automatically deleted.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For numbered snapshots, which include administration and installation snapshot 
          pairs, the cleanup is controlled by parameters such as <literal>NUMBER_CLEANUP</literal>,
        <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal>, <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>, and <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>. 
          The default values are 2&ndash;10 for <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> and 4&ndash;10 for
          <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>, meaning that only the youngest snapshots are kept.</para>
          <para>For timeline snapshots, the cleanup is based on the number of snapshots to keep for 
          each type (hourly, daily, weekly, monthly, yearly). For example, the last 24 hourly
          snapshots, the first daily snapshot from the last seven days, the first snapshot 
          made on the last day of the month for the last twelve months, and so forth. The parameters 
          include <literal>TIMELINE_CLEANUP</literal>, <literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal> and 
          interval parameters such as <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY</literal>, 
          <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_HOURLY</literal> and so on.</para>
      <para>You can roll back to an existing snapshot at any time by booting from 
        the respective snapshot and making it active afterwards.</para> <!--For more details refer to ???.</para>-->
        <note>
          <title>Disabling &snapper; automatically and manually</title>
          <para>If your root partition is smaller than 16&nbsp;GB, the automatic creation 
          of snapshots as described above is disabled by default. In this case, 
          you can manually create snapshots.<!-- (refer to ??? for more instructions)--> Keep an 
          eye on the available disk space.</para><!-- (see ??? for more information)-->
          <para>To disable automatic snapshots even if your root partition is sufficiently 
          sized, disable snapshots manually during the installation in the partition setup 
          step.</para><!-- For more information on how to do this, see ????-->
        </note>
      </section>
</topic>
