<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
  <!ENTITY snapper "entity-value">
]>
<topic xml:id="snapper-undo-changes-compare-undo-and-rollback"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Undoing changes compared to rollback with &snapper;</title><!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
     <meta name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
     <abstract>
      <para>When working with snapshots to restore data, it is important to know that
        there are two fundamentally different scenarios &snapper; can handle: 
        undoing changes and rollback. The key difference between them is the level 
        of granularity and the scope of the operation.</para>
    </abstract>
    <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
  </info>
  
  <section xml:id="sec-snapper-undo">
    <title>Undoing changes with &snapper;</title>
     <para>To undo changes made between two snapshots, the <command>undochange</command> 
      command is used. This command allows you to reverse the effects of a specific 
      action within a transaction without impacting subsequent changes. For example, 
      if you have a configuration file that was modified in a certain snapshot and 
      you want to revert that change, use the <command>undochange</command> 
      command to do so.</para>
     <para>
      When undoing changes, two snapshots are
      being compared and the changes between these two snapshots are made
      undone. Using this method, you can explicitly select the files
      that need to be restored.
     </para>
    </section>

  <section xml:id="sec-snapper-rollback">
    <title>Rollback with &snapper;</title>
    <para>In comparison with undoing changes, a rollback is a more comprehensive 
      operation that reverts the entire file system to a previous snapshot, including 
      configurations and system files. This is useful when you want to revert 
      multiple transactions and return the system to a previous state, erasing 
      all changes made after a specific transaction.</para> 
    <para>
      When doing rollbacks, <!-- as described in <xref linkend="sec-snapper-snapshot-boot"/> -->
      the system is reset to the state at which the snapshot was taken.
     </para>
     <para>
      When undoing changes, it is also possible to compare a snapshot against the
      current system. When restoring <emphasis>all</emphasis> files from such a
      comparison, this will have the same result as doing a rollback. <!--However,
      using the method described in <xref linkend="sec-snapper-snapshot-boot"/> 
      for rollbacks should be preferred, since it is faster and allows you to
      review the system before doing the rollback.-->
     </para>
</section>
</topic>
