<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
  <!ENTITY snapper "Snapper">
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="snapper-default-setup"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
 <info>
  <title>&snapper; default setup</title>    
    <meta name="maintainer" content="daria.vladykina@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
       <para>
        Learn about the default setup of &snapper; and its default settings.
       </para>
     </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>&snapper; is set up as an undo and recovery tool for system
    changes. By default, the root partition (<filename>/</filename>) of 
    &productname; is formatted with <literal>Btrfs</literal>. Taking snapshots
    is automatically enabled if the root partition (<filename>/</filename>) 
    is big enough (more than approximately 16&nbsp;GB). 
    By default, snapshots are disabled on partitions other than <filename>/</filename>.</para>
    <important>
      <para>We do not recommend activating snapshots manually after the system 
        has been installed with snapshots. Enabling &snapper; after the installation 
        results in a different setup compared to what is described here.</para>
    </important>
<tip>
  <title>Checking root partition size</title>
  <para>The size of the root partition is product-specific. To find out the disk 
    space that the root partition occupies, run:</para>
<screen>&prompt.user;<command>df -h</command></screen>
</tip>

    <section xml:id="snapper-default-settings">
    <title>&snapper; default settings</title>
      <para os="sles">By default, &snapper; on &productname; is automatically configured during 
      system installation if the following requirements are met:</para>
 <itemizedlist os="sles">
  <listitem>
  <para>Root partition size: &gt; 16&nbsp;GB</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
  <para>Root partition file system: Btrfs</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
 <para>Snapshots are created for the root partition only, and certain 
  directories are excluded by means of subvolumes. For the list of excluded subvolumes, 
  see <xref linkend="snapper-subvolumes"/>.<phrase os="sles"> For detailed information about the types
  of snapshots, the time and occasions of their creation, see <xref linkend="snapshot-types"/>.</phrase></para>
 <para>&snapper; provides automatic snapshot cleanup algorithms to prevent running 
        out of space on the root partition. These algorithms differentiate 
        between timeline snapshots and <emphasis>numbered</emphasis> snapshots 
        (administration plus installation snapshot pairs). The cleanup behavior can 
        be configured based on the following criteria:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Number limit: The system can be set to automatically delete old snapshots 
        when a certain count of snapshots is reached.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Age limit: Old snapshots can be deleted if they exceed a certain age, while 
        still preserving a number of snapshots for each time period (hourly, daily, monthly, yearly).</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><literal>Pre</literal> and <literal>post</literal> snapshot pairs: 
          <literal>pre</literal> and <literal>post</literal> snapshot pairs that do not 
          differ can be automatically deleted.</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>For numbered snapshots, which include administration and installation snapshot 
          pairs, the cleanup is controlled by parameters such as <literal>NUMBER_CLEANUP</literal>,
        <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal>, <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>, and <literal>NUMBER_MIN_AGE</literal>. 
          The default values are 2&ndash;10 for <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT</literal> and 4&ndash;10 for
          <literal>NUMBER_LIMIT_IMPORTANT</literal>, meaning that only the youngest snapshots are kept.</para>
          <para>For timeline snapshots, the cleanup is based on the number of snapshots to keep for 
          each type (hourly, daily, weekly, monthly, yearly). For example, the last 24 hourly
          snapshots, the first daily snapshot from the last seven days, the first snapshot 
          made on the last day of the month for the last twelve months, and so forth. The parameters 
          include <literal>TIMELINE_CLEANUP</literal>, <literal>TIMELINE_MIN_AGE</literal> and 
          interval parameters such as <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_DAILY</literal>, 
          <literal>TIMELINE_LIMIT_HOURLY</literal> and so on.</para>
      <para>You can roll back to an existing snapshot at any time by booting from 
        the respective snapshot and making it active afterwards.</para> <!--For more details refer to ???.</para>-->
        <note>
          <title>Disabling &snapper; automatically and manually</title>
          <para>If your root partition is smaller than 16&nbsp;GB, the automatic creation 
          of snapshots as described above is disabled by default. In this case, 
          you can manually create snapshots.<!-- (refer to ??? for more instructions)--> Keep an 
          eye on the available disk space.</para><!-- (see ??? for more information)-->
          <para>To disable automatic snapshots even if your root partition is sufficiently 
          sized, disable snapshots manually during the installation in the partition setup 
          step.</para><!-- For more information on how to do this, see ????-->
        </note>
</section>

<section xml:id="snapper-on-root">
        <title>&snapper; on root</title> 
         <para>When &snapper; is configured to operate on root, every Btrfs subvolume is
         excluded by default.</para>
        <para>The default behavior of &snapper; is defined in a configuration file that 
         is specific for each partition or Btrfs subvolume. These configuration files reside
         under <filename>/etc/snapper/configs/</filename>.</para>
         <warning os="sles">
          <title>Enabling &snapper; in the installed system</title>
          <para>
            If you disabled &snapper; during the installation, it is possible to enable it later.
            However, enabling &snapper; after the installation results in differences
            in the subvolume layout and variables, among other things. We strongly recommend
            deciding whether you need snapshots in your system <emphasis>before</emphasis>
            starting the installation.
          </para>
         </warning>
</section>

<section xml:id="snapper-subvolumes">
        <title>Subvolumes excluded from snapshots</title>
         <para>The primary use case for snapshots is to roll back the system 
          to a previous state. Therefore, there are certain subvolumes (directories)
          for which snapshotting is disabled.</para>
          <para>The following list contains directories that are excluded from snapshots. 
            Depending on your product and architecture, not all of them may be available
            on your system.
          </para>
          <variablelist>
          <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/boot/grub2/i386-pc</filename>,
             <filename>/boot/grub2/x86_64-efi</filename>,
             <filename>/boot/grub2/powerpc-ieee1275</filename>,
             <filename>/boot/grub2/s390x-emu</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              A rollback of the boot loader configuration is not supported. The
              directories listed above are architecture-specific. The first two
              directories are present on AMD64/Intel 64 machines, the latter two are
              on IBM &power; and on &zseries;, respectively.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/home</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              If <filename>/home</filename> does not reside on a separate partition, it
              is excluded to avoid the loss of user-created data on rollbacks.
             </para>
            </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
          <varlistentry>
           <term><filename>/opt</filename>, <filename>/usr/local</filename>
           </term>
           <listitem>
            <para>
              These directories are used when manually installing third-party products.
              They are excluded to avoid uninstalling these installations on rollbacks.
            </para>
           </listitem>
          </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/srv</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              Contains data for Web and FTP servers. It is excluded to avoid data loss on
              rollbacks.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/tmp</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              All directories containing temporary files and caches are excluded from
              snapshots.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>           
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/var</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              This directory contains many variable files, including logs, temporary
              caches, third-party products in <filename>/var/opt</filename>, and is the
              default location for virtual machine images and databases. Therefore, this
              subvolume is created to exclude all of this variable data from snapshots
              and has copy-on-write disabled.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
           <varlistentry>
            <term><filename>/run</filename>
            </term>
            <listitem>
             <para>
              This directory contains application runtime data and is excluded from
              snapshots to reduce the size of the snapshot and to avoid including 
              potentially sensitive information.
             </para>
            </listitem>
           </varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
         <tip>
            <para>
              The list of subvolumes is product-specific. To see what subvolumes 
              are created under <filename>/</filename> and 
              therefore see which directories are excluded from the 
              default snapshots behavior, run:</para>
            <screen>&prompt.sudo;btrfs subvolume list /</screen>
         </tip>  
      <note><title>Why is there a space limit?</title>
      <para>
        When creating a snapshot, no physical data copies are created. A snapshot only consists of 
        pointers to the respective data blocks. As long as the snapshot remains consistent with 
        the current system, it occupies almost no additional disk space (apart from the metadata 
        it contains). However, if a file is modified on the system, the original data is recorded
        in the snapshot. Over time, as more changes accumulate and the snapshot diverges from 
        the live system, the snapshot's size increases accordingly.</para>
        <para>To prevent disks from running full (and the system becoming inoperable as a result), we 
        recommend having a minimal root file system size. The required size depends on system usage:</para>
        <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
        <para>The frequency of snapshot creation</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>The duration for which snapshots are retained</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
        <para>The rate of changes to the system</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
        <para>In general, the more snapshots you have, the longer they are kept, and the more 
          frequently the system changes, the larger the root partition needs to be.</para>
      </note>
  </section>
    </topic>
