<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="sudo-configure-intro"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>An introduction to &sudo; configuration</title><!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
    <!--add author's email address-->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="jana.jaeger@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract><!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
      <para>
       &sudo; provides a means to securely and efficiently delegate superuser
       privileges to specific users or groups.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

    <para>
      Certain operations on a Linux system require &rootuser; or administrator
      privileges. Home users who administer their own system do not have to
      delegate superuser privileges, because the administrator and the normal
      user are the same person in this scenario. But as soon as a system is part
      of a larger environment with multiple users,
      groups and hosts, it becomes essential to maintain control over who is allowed
      to do what and where. At the same time, it is important to provide all
      users and groups with the necessary privileges to carry out their tasks.
    </para>
    <important>
    <para>
       In the new policy implemented in the <literal>sudo-policy-wheel-auth-self</literal> package,
    the <literal>wheel</literal> group is used to track if a user can become a &rootuser;
    with the user password. The first user created by the &agama; installer is added to the <literal>wheel</literal> group.
    </para>
   <para>Additionally, when running <command>sudo </command> command:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>If you are part of the <literal>wheel</literal> group, you are prompted to enter your user password.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>If you are not part of the <literal>wheel</literal> group, you are prompted to enter the &rootuser; password.</para></listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
     </important>
     <para> &sudo; provides: </para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Enhanced system security</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            &sudo; offers fine-grained control over users, groups, hosts and
             commands and thus increases system security by reducing the risk of
             malicious or accidental damage by an intruder or a
             system user.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Complete audit trail</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Whenever a user switches privileges, this appears in the system's
            log, and all operations carried out by this user with elevated
            privileges can be traced back to them.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>A means to delegate &rootuser;-specific tasks</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Using &sudo;, system administrators can enable single users or
            groups to carry out certain tasks without the need to enter
            the &rootuser; password and switch to the &rootuser; account.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </topic>
