<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="supportconfig-overview"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>The <command>supportconfig</command> tool</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="jsindelarova@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
      <para>
        The topic covers basic information regarding the <command>supportconfig</command> tool.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>The tool creates a tar ball in the <filename>/var/log</filename> directory. Attach the log file tar ball to your
    service request or if you cannot, email it to the engineer.
    For more detailed information on working with SUSE Technical Support, see <link xlink:href="https://www.suse.com/support/handbook/"/>.</para>
  <para>
    If problems occur, use the <command>supportconfig</command> command-line tool to collect and organize system information
    and logs. This helps reduce the time needed to resolve service requests. The collected data includes details such as the current kernel version,
    hardware, installed packages, partition setup and more, and is automatically attached to your service request.
  </para>
    <para>
    The command-line tool is provided by the package <systemitem>supportutils</systemitem>, which is installed by default.
    If the package is not installed, install it with:</para>
   <screen>&prompt.sudo;zypper install supportutils</screen>
   <para>
    The <command>supportconfig</command> tool can integrate plug-ins that run
    automatically each time the command is executed. Which plug-ins are available on your system, depends on the installed packages. The plug-ins
    are stored in the <filename>/usr/lib/supportconfig/plugins/</filename>
    directory.
  </para>
  <para>
    The <command>supportconfig</command> tool creates a TAR archive with
    detailed system information that you can hand over to Global Technical
    Support.
  </para>
</topic>
