<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
<!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
%entities;
]>
<!-- refers to https://github.com/SUSE/doc-sle/blob/main/xml/systemd.xml [sec-boot-systemd-timer-units] -->

<topic xml:id="systemd-timer-concept"
       role="concept" xml:lang="en"
       xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
       xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
       xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <title>The &systemd; timer concept</title>
  <info>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        &systemd; timer units provide a modern mechanism for scheduling jobs on Linux, replacing
        cron.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    Similar to cron, systemd timer units provide a mechanism for scheduling jobs on Linux. Although
    systemd timer units serve the same purpose as cron, they offer several advantages:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Jobs scheduled using a timer unit can depend on other &systemd; services. Timer units are
        treated as regular &systemd; services, so can be managed with <command>systemctl</command>.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Timers can be realtime (being triggered on calendar events) and monotonic being triggered
        at a specified time elapsed from a certain starting point.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Time units are logged to the system journal, which makes it easier to monitor and
        troubleshoot them.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Uses the centralized &systemd; management services.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        If the system is off during the expected execution time, the timer is executed once the
        system is running again.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>
    &systemd; timer units are identified by the <filename class="extension">.timer</filename> file
    name extension. Each timer file requires a corresponding service file it controls. In other
    words, a timer file activates and manages the corresponding service file. For a full refernce
    on systemd timers including advanced configuration options (like delays or handling clock or
    time zone changes) refer to <command>man 5 systemd.timer</command>.
  </para>
</topic>
