<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="systemd-secure-services"
  role="concept" xml:lang="en"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
  xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Secure &systemd; services</title>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Linux increases its security by separating privileges between individual components of the
        operating system. System services already have a default level of security. For example,
        their processes run under their own user ID, which limits the changes they can perform on
        the system.
      </para>

      <para>
        The default level of privilege separation provides only a basic protection. Services can
        still perform as many changes as normal local users, though not as many as &rootuser;. A
        higher level of system security requires limiting what services can perform and prevents
        them from certain privileges that normal users are allowed to use.
      </para>
    </abstract>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
  </info>
   <section xml:id="benefits-securing-with-systemd">
    <title>Why is securing &systemd; services important?</title>
    <para>
      Securing &systemd; services increases the security of the whole operating system and protects
      sensitive data contained on its file system. With &systemd;, you can configure your system in many ways.
      &systemd; runs as the first process on boot (PID1) which means that it has a lot of power on your Linux environment.
    </para>
    <para>&systemd; can apply additional restrictions to local services by using technologies included in the kernel.
      These restrictions are activated by adding specific options to the systemd service definition and restarting the service.
      &systemd; has a command-line tool <command>systemd-analyze security</command>. This command analyses the services and checks
      if the services are using its security options.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="what-is-systemd-aalyze-security-command">
      <title>What is the <command>systemd-analyze security</command> command?</title>
      <para>
       The command analyzes the security and sandboxing settings of the specified service units.
       A detailed analysis of the security settings is executed and displayed.
       If a service unit is not specified, all currently loaded, long-running service units are inspected and the results are displayed in a terse table.
       </para>
  <para>Upon checking the security settings, the command assigns a numeric value , also known as <emphasis>exposure level</emphasis>.
    This value is dependent on how important a setting is. It then calculates an overall exposure level for the whole unit. This value ranges
    from 0.0-10.0, which is an indicator of how exposed a service is security wise.
    High exposure levels indicate that the service might benefit from additional security settings.
    While low exposure levels indicate tight security restrictions.
  </para>
   </section>
   <section xml:id="systemd-analyze">
    <title>Using the <command>systemd-analyze security</command> command </title>
    <para>
      Use the <command>systemd-analyze security</command> command to analyze the security settings of a  &systemd; service.
      The <literal>security</literal> option analyzes the security and the sandboxing settings of one or more specified services.
      </para>
    <procedure>
         <step><para>Create a &systemd; service in the <filename>/etc/systemd/system</filename>. </para>
             </step>
             <step><para>Reload the service files to include the new service:</para>
              <screen>&prompt.sudo; systemctl daemon-reload</screen>
             </step>
             <step><para>Start,enable, and check the status of the service:</para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo; systemctl start <replaceable>SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></screen>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo;systemctl enable <replaceable>SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></screen>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo; systemctl status <replaceable>SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></screen>

                </step>
                <step><para>Analyze the security settings of the service:</para>
                  <screen>&prompt.sudo; systemd-analyze security <replaceable>SERVICE_NAME</replaceable></screen>
                  <para>For example:</para>
  <screen>&prompt.sudo; systemd-analyze security test.service
  NAME                DESCRIPTION                              EXPOSURE
  ✗ PrivateNetwork=     Service has access to the host's network      0.5
  ✗ User=/DynamicUser=  Service runs as root user                     0.4
  ✗ DeviceAllow=        Service has no device ACL
  ...
  → Overall exposure level for test.service: 9.6 UNSAFE 😨
  </screen>
                 </step>
                </procedure>
              </section>
  <section xml:id="systemd-exposure">
    <title>How to improve the overall exposure</title>
                <para><emphasis>How to improve the overall exposure</emphasis></para>
                  <para>If you get <emphasis>9.6 UNSAFE</emphasis>, you can use <literal>[Service]</literal> part of the service definition file to add any of the below options. For example:</para>
  <screen>
  [Service]
  NoNewPrivileges=yes
  PrivateTmp=yes
  PrivateNetwork=yes
  InaccessibleDirectories=/home
  .....
  </screen>
                  <variablelist>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>NoNewPrivileges=yes</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                       New privileges are not required.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>PrivateTmp=yes</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                       Private directory for temporary files. This option provides the service with a private <filename>/tmp</filename> isolated from
                       the host system's <filename>/tmp</filename>. The shared host <filename>/tmp</filename>
                       directory is a major source of security problems, such as symlink attacks and DoS
                       <filename>/tmp</filename> temporary files.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>PrivateNetwork=yes</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This option isolates the service and its processes from networking. This prevents
                        external network requests from reaching the protected service. Be aware that certain
                        services require the network to be operational.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>InaccessibleDirectories=/home</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This option makes the specified directories inaccessible to the service. This option
                        narrows the range of directories that can be read or modified by the service, for
                        example, to secure users' private files.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>ReadOnlyDirectories=/var</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This option makes the specified directories inaccessible for writing to the service. The
                        example configuration makes the whole tree below <filename>/var</filename> read-only.
                        This option prevents the service from damaging the system files.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>CapabilityBoundingSet=CAP_CHOWN CAP_KILL</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This option restricts the kernel capabilities that a service can retain. In the example
                        above, only the <literal>CAP_CHOWN</literal> and <literal>CAP_KILL</literal> capabilities
                        are retained by the service, and the service and any processes it creates cannot obtain
                        any other capabilities, not even via setuid binaries.
                      </para>
                      <tip>
                       <title>The <command>pscap</command> command tool</title>
                        <para>
                                                To easily identify which processes on your system retain which capabilities, use the
                          <command>pscap</command> command tool from the <package>libcap-ng-utils</package> package.
                        </para>
                      </tip>

                        <para>
                          The <literal>~</literal> prefix inverts the meaning of the option&mdash;. Instead of
                          listing all capabilities that the service retains, you can list the ones it does not
                          retain:
                        </para>
  <screen>...
  [Service]
  CapabilityBoundingSet=~CAP_SYS_PTRACE
  ...</screen>

                    </listitem>

                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>LimitNPROC=1, LimitFSIZE=0</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        You can use <emphasis>resource limits</emphasis> to apply security limits on services.
                        Two of them can disable specific operating system features:
                        <option>RLIMIT_NPROC=1</option> disables precess forking, while
                        <option>RLIMIT_FSIZE=0</option> disables creating non-empty files on the file system.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                  <varlistentry>
                    <term>DeviceAllow=/dev/null rw</term>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>
                        This option limits access to <filename>/dev/null</filename>, disallowing access to any
                        other device nodes.
                      </para>
                    </listitem>
                  </varlistentry>
                </variablelist>
  <para>These are some options you can use.</para>
  </section>
  </topic>
