<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE article
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="systemd-secure-services"
  role="concept" xml:lang="en"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
  xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Introduction to securing &systemd; services</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Linux increases its security by separating privileges between individual components of the
        operating system. System services already have a default level of security. For example,
        their processes run under their own user ID, which limits the changes they can perform on
        the system.
      </para>

      <para>
        The default level of privilege separation provides only a basic protection. Services can
        still perform as many changes as normal local users, though not as many as &rootuser;. A
        higher level of system security requires limiting what services can perform and prevents
        them from certain privileges that normal users are allowed to use.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>

  <section xml:id="benefits-securing-with-systemd">
    <title>Why is securing &systemd; services important?</title>
    <para>
      Securing &systemd; services increases the security of the whole operating system and protects
      sensitive data contained on its file system. With &systemd;, you can configure your system in many ways.
      &systemd; runs as the first process on boot (PID1) which means that it has a lot of power on your Linux environment.
    </para>
    <para>&systemd; can apply additional restrictions to local services by using technologies included in the kernel.
      These restrictions are activated by adding specific options to the systemd service definition and restarting the service.
      &systemd; has a command-line tool <command>systemd-analyze security</command>. This command analyses the services and checks
      if the services are using its security options.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="what-is-systemd-aalyze-security-command">
    <title>What is the <command>systemd-analyze security</command> command?</title>
    <para>
     The command analyzes the security and sandboxing settings of the specified service units.
     A detailed analysis of the security settings is executed and displayed.
     If a service unit is not specified, all currently loaded, long-running service units are inspected and the results are displayed in a terse table.
     </para>
<para>Upon checking the security settings, the command assigns a numeric value , also known as <emphasis>exposure level</emphasis>.
  This value is dependent on how important a setting is. It then calculates an overall exposure level for the whole unit. This value ranges
  from 0.0-10.0, which is an indicator of how exposed a service is security wise.
  High exposure levels indicate that the service might benefit from additional security settings.
  While low exposure levels indicate tight security restrictions.
</para>
  </section>
</topic>
