<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="targetcli-iscsiadm-iscsi" role="concept" xml:lang="en"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
  xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Understanding <command>targetcli</command> and <command>iscsiadm</command> command-line utilities </title>    <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
    <!--add author's email address-->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>      <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
      <para>
To understand the ecosystem of Linux storage networking, it is essential to distinguish between the two pillars of the iSCSI framework; <command>targetcli</command>  <command>iscsiadm</command> command-line utilities.
        </para>
</abstract>
</info>
<para>
While they both facilitate the transmission of SCSI commands over IP networks, they operate on opposite ends of the connection. <command>targetcli</command> is the administration tool for the Linux-IO (LIO) target subsystem, used on the server-side to define, export, and manage the physical or virtual storage volumes that will be shared.
In contrast, <command>iscsiadm</command> is the primary utility for the Open-iSCSI project, functioning on the client-side (the initiator) to discover, log into, and manage the remote disks provided by the target.
</para>
<section xml:id="about-targetcli">
<title>The <command>targetcli</command> command-line utility </title>
<para> The <command>targetcli</command> tool is the primary command-line administration tool used to configure and manage the LIO (Linux-IO) target subsystem, which is the standard open-source storage target for the Linux kernel.
 It operates as an interactive shell with a hierarchical file-system-like structure and allows system administrators to export local storage resources—such as physical disks, files, or LVM (Logical Volumes) to remote clients via various fabrics, most notably iSCSI.
 It provides a unified interface to define back stores, creates IQNs (iSCSI Qualified Names), and establishes ACLs (Access Control Lists).</para>
</section>
<section xml:id="about-iscsiadm">
  <title>The <command>iscsiadm</command> command-line utility</title>
  <para>The <command>iscsiadm</command> tool is used in Linux environments to manage and administer the Open-iSCSI implementation, acting as the primary interface for configuring and managing iSCSI connections.
    It allows administrators to discover targets on a network, log in or out of specific storage portals, and manage a local database of persistent iSCSI nodes.
    By communicating with the <literal>iscsid</literal> daemon, it facilitates the mapping of remote block storage devices over an IP network, making remote disks appear as local SCSI devices, such as <filename>/dev/sdb</filename> to the operating system.</para>
  </section>
</topic>