<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="tls-certificates-introduction"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>Securing communication using TLS</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <para>
        Two systems, such as client and server hosts, communicate by exchanging
        data over network. To avoid exposing such communication and possibly
        sensitive data, you can configure the systems to encrypt the mutual
        communication using TLS certificates.
      </para>

      <para>
        This topic introduces basic terms and theory behind establishing
        encrypted communication.
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <section xml:id="tls-certificates-terminology">
    <title>Terminology</title>
    <para>
      Here is an explanation of terms that are specific to the topic TLS
      encryption.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>TLS</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Transport Layer Security (TLS) is a protocol that provides secure
            communication between client-server applications. TLS uses
            asymmetric cryptography with a pair of private and public keys. TLS
            is the successor to the SSL (Secure Sockets Layer) protocol.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Public key</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A part of a TLS certificate which acts as a digital identity for the
            server. When a client connects to the server over TLS, it requests
            the server's certificate, which contains the public key. The public
            key is freely distributable and is used for data encryption.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Private key</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A counterpart to the public key in asymmetric cryptography. It is
            kept secret and known only to the owner of the key pair. When a
            client connects to a server over TLS, the server sends its digital
            certificate with a public key. The client uses it to encrypt data,
            ensuring that only the server's private key can decrypt it.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>X.509</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A standard that defines the format of a public key certificates.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>TLS certificate</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            A digital X.509 certificate that helps to secure communication
            within a client-server systems. Using TLS certificate, the client
            can authenticate the identity of the server and encrypt their mutual
            communication. The certificate usually includes information about
            its issuer (CA), identity of its holder, the associated public key,
            digital signature, and its validation period.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
</topic>
