<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- This file originates from the project https://github.com/openSUSE/doc-kit -->
<!-- This file can be edited downstream. -->
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<topic xml:id="tls-certificates-store"
 role="concept" xml:lang="en"
 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
 xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
 xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>System-wide CA certificate store</title>
    <meta name="maintainer" content="tbazant@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>
      <xi:include href="../snippets/tls-certificates-introduction.xml"/>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
    A shared system-wide CA store is a centralized repository for storing
    trusted root certificates and user-specific certificates on a system. This
    store is used by software applications and components within the
    operating system to establish secure connections, validate the authenticity
    of TLS certificates presented by servers, and verify the identity of
    individuals or entities. By default, the store contains the Mozilla CA
    certificate list included in the <package>ca-certificates-mozilla</package>
    package. You can either update this list or select another certificate list.
  </para>
  <tip>
    <title>OpenSSL vs NSS certificate store</title>
    <para>
      By default, there are two different CA certificate stores in
      &productnameshort;: the OpenSSL-based store and the NSS (Network Security
      System)-based store. Many GUI-based Web browsers&mdash;such as
      Firefox&mdash;use the NSS certificate store. To avoid installing CA
      certificates in both certificate stores, install the plug-in package
      <package>p11-kit-nss-trust</package> that makes the NSS store look up
      certificates in the OpenSSL store automatically.
    </para>
  </tip>
  <section xml:id="tls-certificates-store-file-system">
    <title>Where is the CA certificate store on the file system?</title>
    <para>
      In &productnameshort;, the shared system-wide certificate store is located
      in the following directories:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>/usr/share/pki/trust/anchors</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            CA certificates trust anchors provided by the system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>/usr/share/pki/trust/blacklist</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Distrusted CA certificates provided by the system.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>/etc/pki/trust/anchors</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            CA certificates trust anchors provided by the system administrators.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>/etc/pki/trust/blacklist</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Distrusted CA certificates provided by the system administrators.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="tls-certificates-store-benefits">
    <title>Benefits of using a system-wide CA certificate store</title>
    <para>
      Some of the key benefits of using a shared certificate store are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Security:</emphasis> Centralizing trusted
          certificates helps ensure that all applications and services use a
          consistent set of trusted certificates to verify the authenticity
          of TLS connections.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Simplified management:</emphasis> Instead of
          each application or service maintaining its own list of trusted
          certificates, they can rely on the system-wide certificate store.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Ease of update:</emphasis> System administrators
          can update the trusted certificates in the system-wide store as
          needed, either manually or through automated mechanisms such as
          operating system updates. This ensures that systems remain up to date
          with the latest trusted certificates and security standards.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</topic>
