<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE topic
[
  <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "../common/generic-entities.ent">
    %entities;
]>
<!-- refers to legacy doc: <add github link to legacy doc piece, if applicable> -->
<!-- point back to this document with a similar comment added to your legacy doc piece -->
<!-- refer to README.md for file and id naming conventions -->
<!-- metadata is dealt with on the assembly level -->
<topic xml:id="valkey-about" role="concept" xml:lang="en"
  xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" version="5.2"
  xmlns:its="http://www.w3.org/2005/11/its"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:trans="http://docbook.org/ns/transclusion">
  <info>
    <title>About Valkey</title>    <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
    <!--add author's email address-->
    <meta name="maintainer" content="amrita.sakthivel@suse.com" its:translate="no"/>
    <abstract>      <!-- can be changed via merge in the assembly -->
      <para>
      Valkey is an open-source, in-memory data structure store, licensed under the BSD (Berkeley Software Distribution) license, that serves as a versatile platform for various applications.
      It excels as a database, providing fast and flexible data storage; as a cache, significantly improving application performance; as a message broker, enabling asynchronous communication; and even as a streaming engine for real-time data processing.
      Valkey builds upon the foundation of Redis OSS, incorporating multi-threading for enhanced performance and offering a robust solution for applications demanding speed, scalability, and diverse data handling capabilities. </para>
      <para>
      </para>
    </abstract>
  </info>
  <para>
   Valkey has many benefits, which include the following:
  </para>
  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para>
       Fast, low-latency access to data stored in memory, ideal for caching, real-time analytics, and message brokering.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Supports powerful and versatile data structures like strings, hashes, lists, sets, sorted sets, streams, and geo-spatial indexes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Offers RDB (Redis Database Backup ) snapshot and AOF (append-only file) persistence for recovering data after restarts.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Enables horizontal scaling by partitioning data across multiple nodes.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        It maintains compatibility with Redis 7.2, making it easy to migrate without changing existing client libraries or application logic.
      </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>
        Provides built-in publish/subscribe capabilities for building event-driven or messaging-based systems.
      </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
<para>For more information on Valkey, refer to <link
  xlink:href="https://valkey.io/docs/"/></para>
  </topic>
